<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ML | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/ml/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-02T15:02:39+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Repost] Timeline: The Advance of the Data Civilization]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/02/15/repost-timeline-the-advance-of-the-data-civilization/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-15T21:24:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/02/15/repost-timeline-the-advance-of-the-data-civilization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a repost read from <a href="http://www.popsci.com/technology/article/2011-10/timeline-advance-data-civilization">here</a>. If any copyright is offended, please contact
me immediately and I will remove this post.</p>

<p>In 2009, English scientist Stephen Wolfram started a website–an “answer”
engine–to redefine how information is gathered on its greatest-ever conduit.
In this timeline, he catalogs “how our civilization has systematized knowledge,
and gradually made it amenable to automation. This is about data and how it
came to be the way it is in our world.”</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="bc-to-2500-bc">20,000 B.C. to 2,500 B.C.</h2>

<p><strong>20,000 B.C.</strong>: The invention of arithmetic provides a way to abstractly compute
numbers of objects. </p>

<p><strong>15,000 B.C.</strong>: The Lascaux cave paintings record some of the first known
narrative constructions. </p>

<p><strong>3,800 B.C.</strong>: The Babylonian census begins the practice of systematically
counting and recording people. </p>

<p><strong>3,500 B.C.</strong>: Written language emerges , providing a systematic way to record
and transmit knowledge. </p>

<p><strong>2,500 B.C.</strong>: The first known calendar system is established in Mesopotamia,
creating a 360-day year.</p>

<h2 id="bc-to-400-bc">1,770 B.C. to 400 B.C.</h2>

<p><strong>1,170 B.C.</strong>: Hammurabi writes down 282 laws prescribing civil behavior in
the kingdom of Babylon. </p>

<p><strong>1,250 B.C.</strong>: The library at Thebes in ancient Greece gathers the world’s
knowledge and makes it available in one place. </p>

<p><strong>1,150 B.C.</strong>: The Turin papyrus is the first known topographic map. </p>

<p><strong>560 B.C.</strong>: Lydia, in modern-day Turkey, introduces gold and silver coins to
represent monetary value. </p>

<p><strong>500 B.C.</strong>: Babylonians invent mathematical calculation as a way to track the
movement of planets. </p>

<p><strong>400 B.C.</strong>: Hippocrates identifies causes of human diseases. Panini creates a
grammar for Sanskrit, forming the basis for systematic linguistics.</p>

<h2 id="bc-to-45-bc">387 B.C. to 45 B.C.</h2>

<p><strong>387 B.C.</strong>: Plato founds his Academy, which continues to operate in Athens
for nine centuries. </p>

<p><strong>300 B.C.</strong>: Euclid writes his Elements, systematically presenting theorems of geometry and arithmetic. </p>

<p><strong>100 B.C.</strong>: A gear-based device, the Antikythera mechanism, is created to
compute calendrical computation. It survives today. </p>

<p><strong>45 B.C.</strong>: Julius Caesar institutes the Julian calendar, establishing the lengths
of the 12 months.</p>

<h2 id="ad-to-1361-ad">105 A.D. to 1361 A.D.</h2>

<p><strong>105 A.D.</strong>: Ts’ai invents paper in China. </p>

<p><strong>125</strong>: Philo of Byblos compiles the earliest known thesaurus. </p>

<p><strong>150</strong>: Ptolemy’s Almagest introduces epicycles to describe the detailed
motion of planets. </p>

<p><strong>200</strong>: Galen organizes anatomy and physiology, defining many terms and
concepts used today. </p>

<p><strong>1028</strong>: Italian Benedictine monk Guido d’Arezzo invents musical stave
notation. </p>

<p><strong>1361</strong>: French philosopher Nicole Oresme introduces the notion of drawing
graphs of values.</p>

<h2 id="to-1591">1408 to 1591</h2>

<p><strong>1408</strong>: The Yongle dadian, assembled by more than 2,000 scholars, fills more than 11,000 volumes with the collected knowledge of Chinese civilization. </p>

<p><strong>1453</strong>: Moveable type makes it economical to print many kinds of documents. </p>

<p><strong>1538</strong>: Parishes in England begin keeping weekly records of all christenings,
marriages and burials. </p>

<p><strong>1561</strong>: French mathematician Franciscus Vieta begins writing mathematical
formulas with letters as variables, using vowels for unknowns and consonants
for parameters.</p>

<h2 id="to-1654">1604 to 1654</h2>

<p><strong>1604</strong>: British teacher Robert Cawdry publishes a dictionary with definitions
for 2,543 terms. </p>

<p><strong>1614</strong>: Scottish mathematician John Napier publishes the first tables of
logarithms. </p>

<p><strong>1623</strong>: German astronomer Wilhelm Schickard creates a gear-based, six-digit
mechanical calculator.</p>

<p><strong>1627</strong>: German astronomer Johannes Kepler’s Rudolphine Tables list the
positions of 1,005 stars and procedures for locating the planets. </p>

<p><strong>1654</strong>: Physician William Petty, traveling with Oliver Cromwell’s army,
systematically surveys and assigns value to land in Ireland.</p>

<h2 id="to-1688">1659 to 1688</h2>

<p><strong>1659</strong>: The Central England Temperature record begins, and continues today.</p>

<p><strong>1662</strong>: English statistician John Graunt and others start to systematically
summarize demographic and economic data using statistical ideas based on
mathematics. </p>

<p><strong>1686</strong>: English astronomer Edmond Halley creates a map showing prevailing
winds at different locations.</p>

<p><strong>1687</strong>: Isaac Newton introduces the idea that systems in nature can be
described by math. </p>

<p><strong>1688</strong>: Joseph de la Vega’s book Confusion of Confusions describes
fluctuations in Dutch stock-market prices.</p>

<h2 id="to-1830">1750 to 1830</h2>

<p><strong>1750</strong>: Swedish botanist Carl Linnaeus introduces binomial designations and
classifies living organisms. </p>

<p><strong>1755</strong>: Japanese merchant Munehisa Homma invents an early candlestick chart
for prices in the Japanese rice market. </p>

<p><strong>1795</strong>: France becomes the first nation to officially adopt the metric system
of measurement. </p>

<p><strong>1801</strong>: French inventor Joseph-Marie Jacquard creates a loom that weaves
patterns specified by punched cards. </p>

<p><strong>1830</strong>: English mathematician Charles Babbage constructs a mechanical
computer to automate the creation of mathematical knowledge.</p>

<h2 id="to-1861">1836 to 1861</h2>

<p><strong>1836</strong>: The General Register Office is founded. Births and deaths begin to be
systematically recorded by the British government. </p>

<p><strong>1839</strong>: French artist and physicist Louis Daguerre uses a copper plate and
silver to capture photographs. </p>

<p><strong>1839</strong>: English cartographer and printer George Bradshaw publishes the first
train timetables. </p>

<p><strong>1844</strong>: American inventor Samuel Morse sends the first public telegraph
message. </p>

<p><strong>1850</strong>: German entrepreneur Paul Julius Reuter uses pigeons to transmit stock
prices from Aachen, Germany, to Brussels, Belgium. </p>

<p><strong>1861</strong>: British naval officer and meteorologist Robert FItzRoy uses a network
of telegraph stations and systematic charts to forecast British weather.</p>

<h2 id="to-1876">1867 to 1876</h2>

<p><strong>1867</strong>: Edward Calahan of the American Telegraph Company invents a system to
transmit price changes from the floor of the New York Stock Exchange. </p>

<p><strong>1869</strong>: Russian chemist Dmitry Mendeleev designs the periodic table of
chemical elements. </p>

<p><strong>1872</strong>: Scottish physicist Lord Kelvin creates an analog computer for
predicting ocean tides.</p>

<p><strong>1876</strong>: American librarian Melvil Dewey debuts the Dewey Decimal system for
classifying the world’s knowledge and specifying how to organize books in
libraries.</p>

<h2 id="to-1935">1877 to 1935</h2>

<p><strong>1877</strong>: Thomas Edison invents the phonograph.</p>

<p><strong>1878</strong>: By an act of Congress, the collection of morbidity data on cholera,
smallpox and yellow fever begins. </p>

<p><strong>1895</strong>: Belgian lawyers Paul Otlet and Henri La Fontaine begin to collect
index cards of information to answer factual questions by mail. By 1934, they
had amassed 15.6 million cards. </p>

<p><strong>1935</strong>: George Gallup founds the American Institute of Public Opinion and
begins the first rigorous collection of opinion polls.</p>

<h2 id="to-1953">1936 to 1953</h2>

<p><strong>1936</strong>: English mathematician Alan Turing proposes the stored computer
program. </p>

<p><strong>1936</strong>: The U.S. federal government issues the first Social Security numbers. </p>

<p><strong>1940s</strong>: Electronic computers allow computations of all kinds to be automated
with increasing efficiency. </p>

<p><strong>1945</strong>: American engineer Vannevar Bush speculates on the idea of a “Memex”
device that would provide computerized access to the world’s knowledge–a
precursor to hyperlinks. </p>

<p><strong>1953</strong>: James Watson and Francis Crick determine the physical structure of
DNA.</p>

<h2 id="to-1982">1957 to 1982</h2>

<p><strong>1957</strong>: Fortran, COBOL and other early computer languages define the concept
of a precise formal representation for tasks to be performed by computers. </p>

<p><strong>1960</strong>: The concept of links between documents–hypertext–begins to be
discussed as a paradigm for organizing textual material and knowledge. </p>

<p><strong>1960</strong>: The first full-text searching of documents by a computer is
demonstrated. </p>

<p><strong>1963</strong>: Zip (Zone Improvement Plan) codes are introduced by the U.S. Post
Office. </p>

<p><strong>1973</strong>: Lexis provides full-text records of U.S. court opinions in Ohio and
New York in an electronic data-delivery system. </p>

<p><strong>1982</strong>: Physicist Walter Goad founds GenBank, an open-access database of
genome sequences. </p>

<h2 id="to-1998">1989 to 1998</h2>

<p><strong>1989</strong>: English computer scientists Tim Berners-Lee creates the World Wide
Web. </p>

<p><strong>1991</strong>: The Virtual Library, the first systematic catalog of the Web, is
created. </p>

<p><strong>1994</strong>: Jerry Yang and David Filo create a hierarchical directory of the Web:
Yahoo. </p>

<p><strong>1996</strong>: Brewster Kahle founds the Internet Archive to begin systematically
capturing and preserving Web pages. </p>

<p><strong>1998</strong>: Google launches. The text-based searching era begins. </p>

<p><strong>1998</strong>: The Sloan Digital Sky Survey systematically maps every visible object
in the astronomical universe.</p>

<h2 id="to-2009">2001 to 2009</h2>

<p><strong>2001</strong>: Volunteer contributors assemble 20,000 pages of encyclopedic material
in all areas of human knowledge for Wikipedia. </p>

<p><strong>2003</strong>: The Human Genome Project, a complete catalog of all the genes
concealed in human DNA, is completed.</p>

<p><strong>2004</strong>: Using GPS, a crowdsourced street-level map of the world is created
for the OpenStreetMap project. </p>

<p><strong>2004</strong>: Facebook begins to catalog social relations among people on a large
scale. </p>

<p><strong>2009</strong>: Wolfram Alpha is launched. It computes answers to language queries
based on a collection of algorithms and curated data</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[k means within point scatter deviation]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/k-means-within-point-scatter-deviation/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-29T19:15:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/k-means-within-point-scatter-deviation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The overall within-point dissimilarity can be replaced with the summation of
dissimilarity between each point in the cluster and the cluster mean. Here is a
detailed proof. See this
<a href="/docs/k_means_within_point_scatter_deviation.pdf">pdf</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Achieve Equal Influence on Attributes]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/achieve-equal-influence-on-attributes/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-29T11:54:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/29/achieve-equal-influence-on-attributes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Elements of Statistical Learning, Chapter 14 Note.</p>

<p>See this <a href="/docs/object_similarity.pdf">pdf</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistic Graphical Model Reading Note -- Chapter One]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/probabilistic-graphical-model-reading-note-chapter-one/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T11:58:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/probabilistic-graphical-model-reading-note-chapter-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the reading notes taken while I am reading the book <em>Probabilistic
Graphical Model</em>. The start point of reading this book is I have a sense of
how the methods in supervised learning, such as least square, logistic
regression, svm, neural network, in unsupervised learning, such as clustering,
and neural network again. However, I do not know much about the role
probabilistic graphical model plays in the ML field.</p>

<p>So I try to get that solved by reading this book.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<h3 id="the-declarative-representation-approach">The Declarative Representation Approach</h3>

<p>One can always write a special-purpose computer program for every domain one
encounters and every type of questiion that one may wish to answer, however,
when the context of the question changes, the program’s capability will degrade
significantly.</p>

<p>The book takes an approach based on declarative representation. The key
property of a declarative representation is the separation of knowledge and
reasoning. The representation has its own clear semantics, separate from the
algorithms that one can apply to it. Thus, we can develop a general suite of
algorithms that apply any model within a broad class, whether in the domina of
medical diagonosis or speech recognition. Conversely, we can improve our model
for a specific application domain without having to modify our reasoning
algorithms constantly.</p>

<h3 id="the-inevitable-uncertainty-of-the-world">The inevitable Uncertainty of the World</h3>

<p>Uncertainty arises because of limitations in our ability to oberserve the
world, limitations in our ability to model it, and possibly even because of
innate nodeterminism.</p>

<h3 id="math-foundation-calculus-of-probability-theory">Math Foundation: Calculus of Probability Theory</h3>

<p>The calculus of probability theory provides us with a formal framework for
considering multiple possible outcomes and their likelihood. It defines a set
of mutually exclusive and exhaustive possibilities, and associates each of them
with a probability – a number between 0 and 1, so that it sums to one.</p>

<h3 id="approximation-is-inevitable">Approximation is inevitable</h3>

<p>Just the title.</p>

<h2 id="structured-probability-models">Structured Probability Models.</h2>

<p>A violent joint probability distribution is too violent and also ignores the
inner connection between different Random Viables. The author put forward a
graph representation to capture the inner connections between Random Viables.</p>

<p>Graphical representation can be viewed in two perspectives(but they are, in a
deep sense, equivalent):</p>

<ol>
  <li>the graph as a representation of a set of independencies.</li>
  <li>the graph as a skeleton for factorizing a distribution.</li>
</ol>

<p>To make the Graphicla Model relevant to real world, there components are
important:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The representation captures one kind of real-world distribution – variables
tend to interact directly only with very few others, and make it can be
written down tractably.</li>
  <li>It can be effectively inferenced.</li>
  <li>It can be effectively constructed, in both sense of taking in the knowledge
of human experts and automatic learning.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is summary given by the author:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>These three components – representation, inference, and learning – are
critical components in constructing an intelligence system. We need a
declarative representation that is a reasonable encoding of our world model. We
need to be able to use this representation effectively to answer a broad range
of questions that are of interest. And we need to be able to acquire this
distribution, combining expert knowledge and accumulated data. Probabilistic
graphical models are one of a small handful of frameworks that support all
three capabilities for a broad range of problems.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="historical-note">Historical Note</h2>

<p>This section definitely worth reading. Here I just takes some notes on why
probability graphical model was rejected at first and rose again.</p>

<p>Despite the success of PGM, the approach fell into disfavor in the AI
community, owing to combination of several factors. One was the belief,
prevalent at the time, that artificial intelligence should be based on similar
methods to human intelligence, combined with a trong impression that people do
not manipulate numbers when reasoning. A second issue was the belief that the
strong independence assumjptions made in the existing expert systmes were
fundamental to the approach. Thus, the lack of a flexible scalable mechanism to
represent interactions between variables in a distirbution was a key factor in
the rejection of the probabilistic framework.</p>

<p>The rejection of probabilistic methods was accompanies by the invention of a
range of alternative formatlisms for reasoning under uncertainty, and the
construction of expert systems based on these formalisms(notably Prospector by
Duda, Gaschnig, and Hart 1979 and Mycin by Buchanan and Shortliffe 1984). Most
of these formalisms used the production rule framework, where each rule is
augemented with some number(s) defining a measure of “confidence” in its
validity. These frameworks largely lacked formal semantics, and many exhibited
significant problems in key reasoning patterns. Other frameworks for handling
uncertainty proposed at the time included fuzzy logic, possibility theory, and
Dempster-Shafer belief functions. For a discusstion of some of these
alternative frameworks see Shafer and Pearl(1990); Horvita at al.(1988);
Halpern(2003).</p>

<p>The widespread acceptance of probabilistic methods began in the late 1980s,
driven forward by two major factors. The first was a series of seminal
theoretical developments. The most influential among these was the development
of the Bayesian network framework by Judea Peal and his colleagues in a series
of paper that culminated in Pearl’s highly influential textbook <em>Probabilistic
Reasoning in Intellligent Systems</em>. In parallel, the key paper by S.L.
Lauritzen and D.J. Spiegelhaltcr 1988 set forth the foundations for efficient
resoning using probabilistic graphical models. The second major factor was the
construction of large-scale highly successfull expert systems based on this
framework that avoided the unrealistically strong assumptions made by early
probabilistic expert systems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proof of close form solution of least square method]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/12/proof-of-close-form-solution-of-least-square-method/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-12T10:12:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/12/proof-of-close-form-solution-of-least-square-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Based on the theorems from <a href="/docs/theorems_about_trace.pdf">this</a>, the close form
solution of least square method is proved
<a href="/docs/solve_optimal_para_of_least_square_using_matrix_calculus.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: The notation used is defined <a href="/docs/theorems_about_trace.pdf">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
