<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Topology | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/topology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-02T15:16:14+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Dig Into Definition of Continuity]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/12/16/a-dig-into-definition-of-continuity/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T15:04:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/12/16/a-dig-into-definition-of-continuity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about explaining intuitions behind the definition of
continuity, in calculus context and topological context, with a focus
on why it is not defined in the other way around. A number of counter
examples are provided.</p>

<p>Note that between calculus context and topological context, there is
still one intermediate step which is metric space context. But it is
basically not different too much in the calculus context so I omit it.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="puzzle-in-calculus-context">Puzzle in Calculus Context</h2>

<p>In Calculus continuity is defined in the following way:</p>

<p>Given a function $f(x)$, we call $f$ is continuous at point $c$, if
for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$, there exists a $\delta &gt; 0$, for $|x - c|
&lt; \delta$ the value of $f(x)$ satisfies</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

|f(x) - f(c)| < \epsilon
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>The intuition continuity want to capture is if there is a small change
in the input(the independent variable), there should be a
corresponding small change in the output(the dependent variable).</p>

<p>It is the small change in $x$ that causes small change in $y$, where
$y$ denotes $f(x)$, but why the definition of continuity is <em>for any
$\epsilon$</em>, which is the change of $y$, <em>there is a $\delta$</em>, which
is the change of $x$? Why not define it as the following way.</p>

<p>Given a function $f(x)$, we call $f$ is continuous at point $c$, if
for any $\delta &gt; 0$, there exists a $\epsilon &gt; 0$, for $|x - c|
&lt; \delta$ the value of $f(x)$ satisfies</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

|f(x) - f(c)| < \epsilon
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>I puzzled on this for a long time but now it feels obvious that the
latter definition is wrong. Before counter example is put forward, I
will explain why the former definition is right.</p>

<p>The point is that it is $y$ that we want to constrain. So for whatever
change $y$ is made as long as it is in the neighborhood of $\epsilon$,
$x$ within the neighborhood of $\delta$ will capture it all. In more
plain English, the change is all caused by those $x$.</p>

<p>Now time for a counter example.</p>

<p>Consider $f(x) = \frac{1}{x}$ defined for $x &gt; 0$. Then $lim_{x
\rightarrow 0.5} f(x) = 2$ in the usual sense. Yet in this case, with
$\delta = \frac{1}{2}$, there is no $\epsilon &gt; 0$ such that $0 &lt; |
x - 0.5| &lt; \delta$ implies $|f(x) - 2| &lt; \epsilon$.</p>

<p>This example comes from
<a href="http://math.stackexchange.com/questions/993866/switching-the-definition-of-epsilon-delta-limit">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="puzzle-in-topology-context">Puzzle in Topology Context</h2>

<p>If we generalize continuity to topological space. Then it is defined
as following.</p>

<p>Mapping of a topological space $(X, T_X)$ into a topological space
$(Y, T_Y)$ is continuous if and only if the inverse image $f^{−1}(W)$
of every open set $W \in T_Y$ is open, i.e. $f^{−1}(W) \in T_X$.</p>

<p>Again why it is not defined in the reverse way:</p>

<p>Mapping of a topological space $(X, T_X)$ into a topological space
$(Y, T_Y)$ is continuous if and only if the image $f(W)$ of every open
set $W \in T_X$ is open, i.e. $f(W) \in T_Y$.</p>

<p>The second definition is called <em>Open mapping</em>, which means map an open
set to an open set.</p>

<p>Similar with the intuition explained in previous section, the
definition of open mapping dose not imply constraint on the image
mapped. <a href="http://mathforum.org/library/drmath/view/62395.html">Here</a> is
an educational example. It constructs a mapping which is open but not
continuous, from $R$ with usual topology to $[0 1]$ with usual
topology. One intuition behind is that even if the image mapped is
open set, no constraint is imposed so it could be too large compared
with the pre-image of it.</p>

<p>If we drop $R$ all together, and only think of open set in the
topological sense. We could think open set as a thing with
semidecidable properties. Below is an explanation from
<a href="http://math.stackexchange.com/questions/932942/why-are-continuous-functions-the-right-morphisms-between-topological-spaces">here</a>. I
copy it here for integrity.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>General topology is actually a kind of logic. I don’t know who this
insight is due to, but see Vickers’ Topology via Logic for much more
on this theme. In particular, the open subsets of a topological
space should be thought of as axiomatizing semidecidable properties:
properties that you can confirm but not necessarily disconfirm,
given limited tools (e.g. finite time and precision).</p>

  <p>For example, you can confirm whether two things are less than 5
inches apart by measuring the distance between them to finite
precision and seeing if it’s less than 5, so an open ball of radius
5 in a metric space describes a semidecidable property, but you
can’t confirm whether two things are less than or equal to 5 inches
apart by measuring the distance between them to finite precision
because if you get 4.99±0.2 inches you don’t know whether that’s
over or under 5.</p>

  <p>Semidecidability can be used to justify all of the topological space
axioms, which is a nice exercise. For example, arbitrary unions of
open sets are open because given a method of confirming whether
you’re in each of those open sets, you get a method of confirming
whether you’re in any of them by running all of the methods
simultaneously and waiting for one to finish. But you only get
finite intersections when you try to do the same thing for waiting
for all of the methods to finish because method n might take n
seconds finish.</p>

  <p>Continuous functions then axiomatize “computable functions”: for f
to be continuous means that it should be possible to compute f(x)
“to arbitrary precision” by computing x “to arbitrary precision,”
where going off of the example of metric spaces “to arbitrary
precision” means “to within an arbitrary open set,” since it’s
semidecidable whether f(x) is contained within an open set. In other
words, to locate f(x) within some open set U, it suffices to locate
x within some open set V. After a moment’s thought you’ll see that
this is precisely the condition that f−1(U)=V.</p>

  <p>(I particularly like this justification of topological spaces and
continuity because, unlike the justification coming from thinking
about metric spaces, it continues to apply to spaces that aren’t
Hausdorff, and in fact it tells you what it means for a space to not
be Hausdorff. One equivalent definition of being Hausdorff is that
the diagonal {(x,x)∈X×X} is closed in X×X. This is equivalent to
“x≠y” being semidecidable, so a space fails to be Hausdorff
precisely when “x≠y” fails to be semidecidable.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would like to read <em>Topology Via Logic</em> some day.</p>

<p>Based on the granularity of your topology space, for instance if $T_X$
is equipped with discrete topology, then any mapping is continuous,
you have different level of continuous. You can tweak your topological
space $T_X$ to make your function continuous.</p>

<p>Now for one counter example that continuous mapping that is not open
mapping.</p>

<p>$f(x) = 1$ for $x \in R$, the mapping is continuous but not open.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
