<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Excerpt | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/excerpt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-30T12:51:12+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt of A Global History]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/05/01/excerpt-of-a-global-history/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T17:20:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/05/01/excerpt-of-a-global-history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Excerpt of <em>A Global History, From Prehistory to 21st Century</em>.</p>

<h2 id="some-points-pops-out-of-mind-when-finalizing-this-excerpt">Some points pops out of mind when finalizing this excerpt</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Selective pressure is the key to evolution of civilization.</li>
  <li>Technology and economics are root cause of politics and relationship between
people. Political system is devised to deal with current technological and
economical status of society. If it is designed against them, its
development will be stagnant.</li>
  <li>The truly new thing rises from ash of past glory – great advance comes from
a fresh start.</li>
  <li>Culture and traditional is wisdom of ancestor to ensure their survival and
prosperity in their society. In this fast changing society, we must change
to master change.</li>
  <li>Humans are raised to be evil or good, not born to.</li>
</ol>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="excerpt">Excerpt</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Each age writes its own history. Not because the earlier history is
wrong, but because each age faces new problems, ask new questions,
and seeks new answers. This precept is self-evident today when the
tempo of change is increasing exponentially, creating a
correspondingly urgent need for new history posing new questions
and offering new answers. – Page xxv</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“For the first time in the course of history,” concludes physicist
Werner Heisenberg, “man on earth faces only himself; he finds no
longer any other partner or foe.” The great irony of our era is
that this primacy is a root cause of our current global malaise and
apprehension. Having eliminated all possible rivals, we humans on
longer confront any foes. We confront only ourselves.<br />
This new confrontation with our inner self rather than with the
outside world is a formidable undertaking. It requires not merely
the acquisition of more knowledge and technology, an enterprise in
which we have proven unequaled. It requires also the crowning of
that knowledge with an ethical compass to provide it with direction
and purpose. In the seventeenth century, when the scientific
revolution was emerging, the English philosopher Francis Bacon
noted its potentiality and warned against its perils. He
enthusiastically endorsed the pursuit of “knowledge and skill”
through science, but he added that the pursuit should be conducted
with “humility and charity,” and not “for the please of mind, or
for contention, or for superiority to others, or for profit or
fame, or power, or any of these inferior things; but for the
benefit and use of life.”<br />
– Page xxvii</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Responsibility lies with the institutions of society, not in the
virtues of the individual.<br />
– Page xxvii, Oceanographer Jacques Cousteau</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Anthropology holds up a great mirror to man and lets him look at
himself in his infinite variety. – Clyde Kluckhohn, Page 3</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In short, our problem as a species is to balance our ever-expanding
knowledge with wisdom in how we use that knowledge. We shall see in
the following chapters that learning how to balance knowledge and
wisdom is becoming so urgent that , as Einstein has warned us, our
future as a species depends on the outcome. – Page 6</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The important lesson that history teaches us is that such wars are
not inevitable. They have occurred not because of human nature but
because of human societies. And human societies have been made by
human beings and can be remade by human beings. This is the gist of
the following conclusion by anthropologist Ashley Montagu
concerning human nature: “Certainly we born with genetically based
capacities for many kinds of behavior, but the manner in which
these capacities become abilities depends upon the training they
receive, upon learning … Our true inheritance lies in our ability
  to make and shape ourselves, not the creatures but the creators of
destiny.” – Page 39</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I have seen the metal-worker at his task at the mouth of his
furnace, with fingers like a crocodile’s. He stank worse than
fish-spawn…. The stonemason finds his work in every kind of hard
stone. When he has finished his labors his arms are worn out, and
he sleeps all doubled up until sunrise, His knees and spine are
broken…. The barber shaves from morning till night; he never sits
down except to meals. He hurries from house to house looking for
business. He wears out his arms to fill his stomach, like bees
eating their own honey…. The farmer wars the same clothes for all
times. His voice is as raucous as a crow’s. His fingers are always
busy, his arms are dried up by the wind. He takes his rest – when
he does get any rest – in the mud. If he’s in good health he
shares good health with the beasts if he is ill his bed is the bare
earth in the middle if his beasts….<br />
Apply your heart to learning. In truth there is nothing that can
compare with it. I f you have profited by a single day at school
it is a gain for eternity. – Page 49</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Although the origins of writing are to be found in the new
circumstances arising from the production of economic surplus, it
has other far-reaching and fateful effects. It stimulated
intellectual development because factual data could now be
collected, recorded, and passed along to successive
generations. Equally significant, writing helped to define and
consolidate individual cultures. It gave permanent written form to
religious traditions, which thereby became sacred books; to social
customs, which became law codes; and to oral myths and stories,
which became classics. Thus writing became the chief means for the
cultural integration of the civilizations of mankind. – Page 53</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>At the core f Buddhism are four great truths: (1) Life is sorrow;
(2) the cause of sorrow is desire; (3) escape is possible only by
stopping desire; and (4) the cessation of desire can only be
achieved by the “eight-fold” path which is comprised of right
belief, right ambition, right speech, right conduct, right living ,
right effort , right thoughts, and right pleasures. The objective
of all this effort is Nirvana, literally meaning “emptiness,” the
“blowing out of the flame.” – Page 84</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Our form of government does not enter into rivalry with the
institutions of others. We do not copy our neighbors, but are an
example to them. It is true that we are called a democracy, for
the administration is in the hands of the many and not the
few. But while the law secures equal justice to all alike in their
private disputes, the claim of excellence is also recognized, and
when a citizen is in any way distinguished, he is preferred to the
public service, not as a matter of privilege, but as the reward of
merit. Neither is poverty a bar, but a man may benefits his
country whatever be the obscurity of his condition. There is no
exclusiveness in our public life, and in our private intercourse
we are not suspicious of one another, nor angry with our neighbor
if he does what he likes…. We are lovers of the beautiful, yet
simple in our tastes, and we cultivate the mind without loss of
manliness. Wealth we employ, not for talk and ostentation, but
when there is a real use for it. To avow poverty with us is no
disgrace; the true disgrace is in doing nothing to avoid it. n
Athenian citizen does not neglect the state because he takes care
of his own household; and even those of us who are engaged in
business have a very fair idea of politics. We alone regard a man
who takes no interest in public affairs, not as a harmless, but as
a useless character; and if few of us are originator, we are all
sound judges of policy. The great impediment to action is , in our
opinion, not discussion, but the want of that knowledge which is
gained by discussion preparatory to action. For we have a peculiar
power of thinking before we at and of acting too….<br />
To sum up: I say that Athens is the school of Hellas….<br />
I have paid the required tribute, in obedience to the law, making
use of such fitting words as I had. The tribute of deeds has been
paid in part; for the dead have been honorably interred, and it
remains only that their children should be maintained at the
public charge until they are grown up: this is the solid prize
with which, as with garland, Athens crowns her sons living and
dead, after a struggle like theirs. – Pericles’s funeral oration
Page 93</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The most successful of the new religious was Christianity. It
offered the doctrine of one God, the Father Omnipotent, in place
of the polytheism of the Greco-Roman gods and the monotheism of
the oriental cult. It brought the solace of a Redeemer, Jesus, who
was not an ambiguous figure in a mythological labyrinth but who
miraculously lived an earthly life, even though he was the Son of
God. “I bring you tidings of great joy which shall be to all
people.” Christianity also guaranteed salvation to the believer,
but instead of a starry eternity, it restored him to life through
a personal resurrection foreshadowed by the Resurrection of Christ
himself. Perhaps most important of all, Christianity provided
fellowship when times were disjointed and common people felt
uprooted and forsaken. All Christians were brothers, and their
meetings were often called agape, meaning “love” in Greek. They
assisted one another, and by their devotion and self-denial they
set an aspiring and contagious example. Thus at a time when the
laws and philosophy of the old order were becoming irrelevant and
inviable, Christianity offered relevance and hope for the meek and
the humble. – Page 112-113</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Today we have that knowledge, and therefore we have the potential
to free ourselves from millennia-old scourges. It is tragic that
the potential has not yet been realized, but the fact remains that
it does exist. And it exists because of the advances made possible
in the past by the different civilizations of the human
race. Therefore, to answer the question, has civilization been a
curse or a blessing? – in the past it has been both. What it will
be in the future depends on whether the knowledge accumulated from
past civilizations is used for destructive or constructive
purposes. – Page 161</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The millennium between the sixth century, when the Sui dynasty
restored imperial unity, and the sixteenth, when the Westerners
began their intrusion by sea, was for China an era of unparalleled
political, social, and cultural stability. But this stability
paradoxically proved to be a curse as well as a blessing. It was a
blessing because Chinese society during this millennium provided
more material advantages and more psychological security for more
people than any other society in the world. But the stability was
also a curse because China was so successful and comfortable that
it remained relatively unchanged, though not completely static. At
the same time, however, as we shall see in the following chapter,
the West was being transformed by its technological achievements,
its economic vitality, and its social and political pluralism. All
this engendered a dynamism that culminated in the West’s
domination of the entire globe. The end result, then, was the
disruption of the beautifully balanced but conservative Chinese
society by the irresistible expansionism of the West. – Page 211</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The renaissance of Confucian thought took place mostly during the
time of troubles following the collapse of the T’ang dynasty, when
the needs of the age clearly called for something more than the
mere memorization of Confucian classics. Accordingly, a number of
scholars undertook a searching reappraisal of the problems of
humankind and of the universe.<br />
A leader in this undertaking was Chu Hsi(1129-1200), who in his
youth had studies both Buddhism and Taoism. Satisfied with
neither, he turned to the Confucian classics, and with his
remarkable talent for synthesis he worked out an interpretation
that combined elements of Buddhism and Taoism with Confucianism
and that was more satisfying and relevant for his time. His
approach – essentially that of the empirical rationalist –
taught that the universe is governed by natural law, which should
be understood and respected. He also believed in the goodness of
people and in their ability to become more perfect. He compared
the individual to a mirror covered with dust, which if cleaned
will be as bright as ever. Evil, therefore, was the result of
neglect and of defective education, and hence could be corrected.<br />
Chu Hsi’s influence in the Confucian world was comparable to that
of Thomas Aquinas in Western Christendom. – Page 219 - 220</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“We should note the force, effort, and consequences of inventions
which are nowhere more conspicuous than in those three which were
unknown to the ancients, namely, printing, gunpowder, and the
compass. For these three have changed the appearance and state of
the whole world.” This statement by the British
philosopher-scientist Francis Bacon (1561-1626) is especially
significant because all three of the inventions that he so wisely
selected originated from China. Yet they had little effect on that
country in comparison with their explosive repercussions in the
West. Chinese civilization was too deeply rooted and Chinese
imperial organization too all-embracing to allow such inventions
to disrupt traditional institutions and practices. Thus printing
was used to disseminate old ideas rather than new; gunpowder
reinforced the position of the emperor  rather than of emerging
national monarchs; and the compass, despite the remarkable
expeditions of Cheng Ho, was not used for  world trade and
exploration and empire building as in the West.<br />
The root of this fateful difference is to be found in the unique
characteristics of the new Western civilization – pluralistic,
adaptable, and free of the shackles of tradition that bound all
the other Eurasian civilizations. The new civilization brought
about historic change not only for the West but also, as Bacon
foresaw, for the entire globe as it came under the influence of
the revolutionary new society. – Page 228</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The history of mankind proves that advances of culture depend upon
the opportunities presented to a social group to learn from the
experience of their neighbors. The discoveries of the group spread
to others and, the more varied the contacts, the greater the
opportunities to learn. The tribes of simplest culture are on the
whole those that have been isolated for very long periods and
hence could not profit from the cultural achievements of their
neighbors.<br />
In other words, the key to different levels of human development
has been accessibility. Those with the most opportunity to
interact with other people have been the most likely to forge
ahead. Indeed, they were driven to do so, for there was selective
pressure as well as opportunity. Accessibility involved the
constant threat of assimilation or elimination if opportunity was
not grasped. By contrast, those who were isolated received neither
stimulus nor threat, were free from selective pressure and thus
could remain relatively unchanged through the millennia without
jeopardizing their existence.<br />
If this hypothesis is applied on a global scale, the remote Australian
aborigines should have been the most culturally retarded of all major
groups; next, the American Indians in the New World; then the Negroes of
sub-Saharan Africa; and finally – the least retarded, or the most
advanced – the various peoples of Eurasia, who were in constant and
generally increasing contact with each other. This, of course, is precisely
the gradation of culture levels found by the European discoverers
after 1500. The Australian aborigines were still at the Paleolithic
food-gathering stage; the American Indians varied from the Paleolithic
tribes of California to the impressive civilizations of Mexico, Central
America, and Peru; the African Negroes presented comparable diversity,
though their overall level of development was higher; and finally, at quite
another level, there were the highly advanced and sophisticated
civilizations found Eurasia – the Moslem in the Middle East, the Hindu in
south Asia, and the Confucian in east Asia.
 – Page 280</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>At its height, the Ottoman Empire was indeed a great imperial
structure. Its heartland was Turkish Asia Minor, but the majority of the
population consisted of Moslem Arabs to the south and Balkan Christians to
the west. The empire sprawled over three continents and comprised some 50
million people, compared to the 5 million of contemporary English. Little
wonder that Christians of the time looked on the ever-expanding Ottoman
Empire with awe and described it as “a daily increasing flame, catching
hold of whatsoever comes next, still to proceed further.”<br />
Page 289</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>General knowledge is, from these causes, little if at all cultivated; every
man is supposed to know his own business or profession, with which it is
esteemed foolish and improper for any other person to interfere. The man of
general science, a character so frequent and so useful in Christian Europe,
is unknown; and nay one, but a mere artificer, who should concern himself
with the founding of cannon, the building of ships, or the like, would be
esteemed little better than a madman. The natural consequence of these
narrow views is, that the professors of any art of science are themselves
profoundly ignorant, and that the greatest absurdities are mixed with all
their speculations.<br />
— Description of Ottoman Empire in Decline Page 294</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Economists define modernization as the process by which humans
have increased their control over their physical environment as a
means to increasing per capita output. Sociologists and
anthropologists point out other features of modernization,
including the awakening and activation of the masses, more
interest in the present, and the future than in the past, a
tendency to view human affairs as understandable rather than as
manipulated by super natural forces, and, until recent years, a
faith in the beneficence of science and technology.<br />
From the viewpoint of world history the significance of this
modernization process is that it led inexorably to European
domination of the globe. The reason is that modernization
provided the Europeans not only with superior economic and
military power but also with superior sociopolitical cohesion and
dynamism. – Page 306</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>These cities were dominated by the great merchant families who controlled
politics s well as trade and crafts. These families were the patrons of
Renaissance artists and writers. Their needs, interests, and tastes colored
the Renaissance cultural revival even though the patrons also included
ducal families such as Sforza of Milan, as well as popes such as Nicholas
V, Pius II, Julius II, and Leo X. This explains the secularism and humanism
of Renaissance – its concern with this world rather than the hereafter and
its focus on pagan classics rather than Christian theology.<br />
At the center of most Renaissance and literature was the person – the
new Renaissance person who was the molder of his or her own destiny rather
than the plaything of supernatural forces. People did not need to be
preoccupied with supernatural forces; rather, the purpose of life was to
develop ones’ innate potentialities. — Page 306 - 307</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The secularism and individualism of the Renaissance were reflected in its
scholarship and education. The so-called father of Renaissance litera,
Francesco Petraca, or Petrarch(1304 - 1374), stressed the value of the
classics as a means for self-improvement and a guide to social action. —
Page 307</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In conclusion, what is the significance of the Renaissance in the
perspective of world history? It is apparent that new emphasis on persons
and on what they could accomplish obviously was more conducive to overseas
expansion than the preceding medieval outlook. On the other hand, this
point can easily be exaggerated and needs serious modification. The fact is
that Renaissance Europe was not science-oriented. The leading figures
tended to be more aesthetic and philosophical than objective and
skeptical. They retained in various degrees certain medieval patterns of
thought. They persisted in admiring and believing the incredible and the
fantastic. They continued to seek the philosopher’s stone that would
convert other metals into gold. They still believed in astrology and
confused it with astronomy. – Page 309</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Europe’s economy was changed not only by the growing use of money but also
by the minting of standardized coins that were acceptable everywhere and by
the development of banks and of credit instruments. Florence led the way in
1252 with gold forin, and other cities and states soon followed. Simple
bills of exchange also apprears in Italy as early as the twelfth
century. Gradually, mighty banking families appeared, first in Italy and
later in northern Europe.<br />
What was happening to Europe, then, was a historic shift to a fundamentally
different type of economic system, the type know today as
capitalism. Capitalism has been defined as “… [a] system in which the
desire for profits is the driving motive and in which large accumulations of
capital are employed to make profits by various elaborate and often indirect
methods.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Equally significant for students of history is the fact that many laypersons
still cherish the vision of assorted Europeans, Asians, or Africans landing
on the shores of the pre-Columbian New World, bearing aloft the torch of
civilization. The fact is that humans today, as in earliest Paleolithic
times, are mesmerized by the cult of the mysterious. They cling to romantic
and simplistic explanations, even when they do not square with known
facts. Our food-gathering ancestors depended on their totems and shamans or
medicine men. Modern humans have similar faith in UFOs, numerology, tarot
cards, intelligent plants, and astrology. Readers of this text will
appreciate the significance of the following report by George Abell ,
professor of astronomy at the University of California, Los Angeles:<br />
    I have polled the general university students taking my survey astronomy
    courses and find that about a thrid have an interest and belief in
    astrology. From discussion with my colleagues in other parts of the
    country I gather that about the same ratio holds everywhere and that it
    probably well represents the fraction of Americans who believe in
    astrology. It is estimated that there are more than 5,000 astrologers
    making a living in the subject in the United States. More than 1,200
    daily newspapers carry astrology columns.<br />
Professor Abell’s report was made in 1975. Polls since that date indicate
that faith in astrology is steadily increasing. Between 1980 and 1985 the
proportion of American teenagers who believe in astrology has grown from 40
to 55 percent. This resurgence of astrology today is especially noteworthy
in view of the fact that it largely disappeared when modern astronomy began
in the sixteen century.<br />
Similarly a 1996 <em>Newsweek</em> poll disclosed that 58 percent of Americans
believe UFOs (Unidentified Foreign Objects) are real, and 29 percent think
we’ve made contact with aliens, while another 48 percent believe there is a
government plot to cover it all up. More specifically, some stargazers claims
to have seen Elvis eating fried chicken on Uranus. Nor are Americans unique
in this respect. In France , nearly 50,000 taxpayers in 1995 declared
income from their work as stargazers, header, mediums, and similar
occupations. By contrast, France has 36,000 Roman Catholic priests and
6,000 psychiatrists.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>On my way to Peking I had to cross the whole of Siberia, Manchuria, and North
China,. No one an fail to be impressed by the journey through Siberia,
especially the first time. The dimensions of Russia are staggering. You
travel a day, you travel a week, you travel ten days, and you are still in
Russia. Except for the Ural Mountains and a stretch near Lake Baikal, the
country is absolutely flat.<br />
After you leave European Russia the population become very scarce, you pass
hours and hours without seeing any village or habitation. Near the stations
there are a few houses. Usually, when the express train arrives at the
station, the entire local population comes to stare at the
travelers. Especially in the evenings, when the train is brilliantly
illuminated by electricity and the elegant figures of some inhabitants of
Shanghai of other Far Eastern ports are visible inside, the travelers must
appear to the local residents like men from another planet. What envy and
dissatisfaction the exotic creatures in furs must provoke in the hearts of
those doomed to spent their entire life in some miserable station!<br />
I imagine a young girl who has nor yet lost the capacity to dream waiting on
the station platform. She hears the express approaching the sees it all
illuminated. The train stops for five minutes. The passengers,looking like
people from a fairy land., jump on the platform; they laugh and joke. There
i a whistle, the train with its passengers disappears, and darkness,
emptiness, and dullness reign again.<br />
It is unjust that some should move from place to place in luxury, while
others must remain in some forsaken place in misery. Small wonder that this
should cause irritation and discontent. I am convinced that the Siberian
express played an important part in the awakening of the population of
Siberia and thereby hasten the coming of the revolution. The sight of
unlimited space and the absence of life- begins to affect you, the passengers
prefer to pass their time in the diner, drinking endless glasses of tea and
playing cards….</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Although the Chinese, the Indians, and the Turks were unimpressed by
European culture during this period, the European, by contract, were very
much impressed by what they saw in Constantinople , in Delhi, and in
Peking. They became familiar first with the Ottoman Empire, and their
reaction was one of respect, admiration, and apprehension. As late as 1634,
after decline of the empire had set in, a thoughtful English traveler
concluded that the Turks were “the only modern people great in action” and
that “he who would behold these times in their greatest glory, could not
find a better scene than Turkey” During the seventeenth century the Ottoman
Empire lost prestige among Europeans. But at the same time European
intellectuals were becoming fascinated with numerous far-off Cathay. They
were entranced as they learned of China’s history, art, philosophy and
government. China came to be held up as a model civilization because of its
Confucian system of morals; its examination system for government service;
its respect for learning rather than for military prowess; and its exquisite
handicraft, including porcelain, silk, and lacquer work. Voltaire(1694 -
1778), for example, adorned the wail of his library with a portrait of
Confucius, and the German philosopher Leibniz(1646 - 1716) extolled the
Chinese emperor K’ang-hsi as “the monarchy .. who almost god-like mortal,
ruling all by a nod of his head, who, however, is educated to virtue and
wisdom … thereby earning the right to rule.”  </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The century and a half between 1763 and 1914 stands out in the course of
world history as the period of European domination over a large part of the
globe. In 1763 Europe was still far from being the master of the world. It
had only coastal footholds in Africa and in Asia. But by 1914 the European
power had annexed the whole of Africa, and they had effectively established
their control over Asia: either directly, as in India and Southeast Asia,
or indirectly, as in the Chinese and Ottoman empires. The unprecedented
expansion of Europe was made possible by the continuation and acceleration
of the modernization process. This process was set in motion earlier by the
Renaissance, Reformation, technological development, capitalist
enterprise, state building and overseas expansion. These triggered a chain
reaction in the form of the three great revolutions – scientific,
industrial, and political – which gave Europe irresistible dynamism and
power.<br />
Two features of these revolutions might be noted at this point. One is that
they were well under way before 1763. The English Civil War, a major phase
of the political revolution, occurred in the 1640s, The scientific
revolution took place primarily during the century and a half between the
publication of Copernicus’ <em>Derevolutionibus orbium coelestium</em>(1543) and
of Newton’s <em>Principia</em>(1687). Likewise, the roots of the industrial
revolution were planed in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, when
the countries of northwestern Europe ‘‘were seething with such genuinely
capitalistic phenomena as systematic mechanical invention, company
formation, and speculation in the shares of financial and trading
concerns.’’ But the worldwide, impact of none of these revolutions was fully
felt until the nineteenth century. That is why we are considering them here
rather than earlier in this text.<br />
The other point to note about the three great revolutions is that they did
not run in parallel or independent lines. Scientific, industrial and
technological events were inderdependent and reacted continuously upon each
other. Nuewton’s discover of the laws governing the movements of heavenly
bodies and Darwin’s theories of biological evolutoin boath had profound
effects on political ideas. Likewise, we cold not conceive of modern
nationalism withough technological innvoations such as printing and the
telegraph. Conversely, politics affeced science, as in the case of the
French Revolutoin, which provided a powerful stimulus to scientific
advancemnt. Politics also affected economics, as was made claer by the
English manufacturer John Wilkinson, who stated bluntly, ``manufacture and
commerce will awlwasy fourish most where Church and King interfere least’’</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Everyone agrees that this increase in the size of the economic cake has been
a great advantage. But there is much dispute over the question of how the
cake has been sliced. Colonial peoples feel that in the past they have had
less than their due share. The total amount that they have received obviously
has increased; otherwise their rising populations could not have been
supported. For example, a British economist has shown that in 1949 European
companies engaged in mining in mineral-rich northern Rhodesia(Zimbabwe) sold
their output for a total of f36.7 million. Of this, they spent only f12.5
million in northern Rhodesia, which meant that two-thirds of the money was
transferred abroad. Moreover, of the f12.5 million spent in northern
Rhodesia, f4.1 million was paid to European living and working there. Only
f2 million out of the f36.7 million went to the Africans working in the
mines. And yet these workers were receiving an average of f41 a year
compared to an average income of f27 a year per adult African male in the
colony.<br />
Under these circumstances it is understandable that colonial peoples are not
very impressed by increased productivity or by the wages paid by foreign
companies. They are more impressed by the wretched level at which they
subsist, especially in comparison with Western levels. They also resent
being cast in the role of hewers of wood and drawers of water, even in
regions where there are human and material resources for industrial
development. – Page 426</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Europe’s domination of the world in the nineteenth century was based not only
on its industrial and scientific revolutions but also on its political
revolution. The essence of the political revolution was the end of the
concept of a divinely ordained division of people into rulers and
ruled. Government was no longer regarded as something above the people and
the people as something below the government. Instead, the political
revolution for the first time history, at least on a scale larger than the
city-state, called for the identification of government with people. The
masses were awakened and activized so that they not only participated in
government but also considered it their inherent right to do so. – Page 428</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Much influenced by the law of gravitation that Newton had demonstrated, the
philosopher believed in the existence of natural laws that regulated, on only
the physical universe, but also human society. Acting on this assumption,
they proceeded to apply reason to all fields in order to discover the natural
laws that operated in each. They subjected everything – all persons, all
institutions, all traditions – to the test of reason. What would be a
rigorous ordeal for any society in any period was particularly unsettling
for France’s ancient regime, past its prime and creaking in many joints. Thus
the philosopher subjected the old regime in France, and throughout Europe,
to a barrage of devastating criticism. More important, they evolved a set of
revolutionary principles by which  they proposed to effect a wholesale
reorganization of society. Of particular interest to us are their specific
proposals in three area – economics, religion , and government.<br />
Their key slogan in economics was laissez-fiare – let the people do what
they will, let nature takes its course. The opposition of government
intervention was a reaction to the rigid regulation of economic life
generally known as mercantilism. In the early period of state building,
mercantilism had been accepted as necessary for national security. But by
the eighteenth century it seems superfluous and damaging. The classic
account laissez-fiare was made by the Scotsman Adam Smith in his famous
work <em>An inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Walth of
Nations</em>(1776). He argued that individuals are motivated by self-interest as
far as their economic activities are concerned, that the national welfare is
simply the sum of the individual interests operating in a nation, and that
each man knows his own interest better than does any statesman.<br />
In religion the key slogan was Ecrasez l’infame – “crush the infamous
thing,” or stamp out religious fanaticism and intolerance. The philosophers
rejected the traditional belief that God controls the universe and
arbitrarily determines the fate of humanity. Instead, they sought a natural
religion that followed the dictates of reason. The outcome was a variety of
radical departures from religious orthodoxy. Some became outright atheists,
denying the existence of God and denouncing religion as a tool of priests
and politicians. Others became agnostics, who neither affirmed nor denied
the existence of God. The majority were deist, willing to go along with
proposition that God existed and had created the universe but insisting
that, after the act of creation, God allowed the universe to function
according to certain natural laws and refrained from intervention. Thus the
deists were able to have their cake and eat it too. They could accept God
and the teaching of Christianity and at the same time reject supernatural
features such as the virgin birth, the resurrection, the divinity of Christ,
and the divine inspiration of the Bible. The important point to note is that
all these new dogmas =- atheism, agnosticism, deism –reflected the
unprecedented growth of skepticism regarding “revealed” or “supernatural”
religion. For the first time since the triumph of Christianity in Europe, a
definite break had occurred with the Christians tradition.
In government, also, the philosophers had a key phrase – “the social
contract.” The contract theory of government was not new. The English
political theorist Jon Locke ahd formulated it in his <em>Essay on Civil
Government</em> (1690), in which he defined government as a political contract
between rulers and ruled. But the French philosopher Jean-Jacques Rousseau
transformed it into a social rather than a political contract. For him it
involved an agreement among the people themselves. In his major political
work, <em>The Social Contract</em>(1762), Rousseau viewed government as imply a
“commission,” by which he justified revolution as a restoration to the
sovereign people of its rightful power. – Page 433</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The declaration set forth certain fundamental mental principles concerning
liberty, property, and security – “Men are born, and always continue, free
and equal, in respect of their right … The Nation is essentially the
source of all sovereignty .. law is an expression of the will of the
community .. liberty consists in the power of doing whatever does not injure
another …” – Page 443</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Liberal doctrines were first clearly formulated and implemented during the
English Revolution. At that time, these doctrines were primarily those of
religious toleration and of security of perosn and of property against the
arbitrariness of the crown. Specifically, carrying out these doctrines
involved parliamentary control of government, the existence of independent
political parties, and the recognition of the need for, and the rights of,
opposition parties. – Page 448</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Karl Max(1818 - 1883), the father of modern socialism, differed
fundamentally from the Utopian Socialists in almost every respect. he was as
materialistic in his outlook as they were idealistic. He spent most of his
life studying the historical evolution and the precise functioning of the
existing capitalist society, whereas Utopians prepared blueprints of
modern communities. Marx was convinced from his study of history that
capitalism would be overthrown by class struggle and would be overthrown by
class struggle and would be replaced by a new type of socialist society. He
reached this conclusion because he believed that the wages paid to workers
were insufficient for them to buy what they produced. This inadequate
purchasing power eventually must lead to the closing of factories,
unemployment, a further decline of purchasing power, and, at length, a
full-scale depression. Furthermore, Marx believed that these depressions
would become increasingly frequent and severe until finally the unemployed
proletariat would be driven in desperation to revolution. In this way
capitalism would be replaced by socialism, as feudalism earlier had been by
capitalism. And the new socialistic society would be depression-proof
because, with government ownership of the means of production, there could
be no private employers, no profits, and the hence no lack of purchasing
power. – Page 450</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Why the yawning and expanding chasm between the utopia expected by some
scientists an d the actually existing dystopia? The answer is to be found
in our cultures. All cultures of all peoples consist of control mechanisms
designed to regulate the behavior of society members. The cultures evolved
gradually during the historical evolution of the societies and therefore
represented their survival wisdom. The values comprising the various
cultures were calculated to enhance community cohesion and
survival. Consequently the values commonly incorporated in cultures favored
maximum fertility for species perpetuation, maximum productivity for
economic sustenance, and maximum military strength for physical survival.<br />
Through the millennia, cultures became the essential underpinnings of their
respective societies. Only through their cultures did individuals know what
they could do and how to do it. Therefore any threat to cultural values
became as serious as any threat to together basic necessities such as food
and water. Hence the extreme reluctance to tolerate any substantive
alternation or modification of traditional values. Hence also the historic
persistence of cultural rigidity, even in periods such as the present, when
rapid technological innovations necessitate correspondingly rapid social
innovations. But technological change customarily has been accepted and
welcomed because it normally raises living standards, while cultural change
has been feared and resisted because it threatens traditional and
comfortable values and practices.<br />
This dichotomy has prevailed throughout history, resulting in the social
stagnation amid the technological storms of our own making. The
disconnection has been responsible for much of the chronic violence and
bloodshed that have stained human history. It persists to the present, when
the disconnection is impacting directly and ominously on many phases of our
lives, as manifested incessantly o television screens and in newspaper
headlines.  — Page 657</p>
  </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt How to Win Friends and Influence People]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/01/25/excerpt-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-25T10:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/01/25/excerpt-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- more -->

<h2 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>In the heyday of his activity, John D. Rockefeller said that “the
ability to deal with people is as purchasable as a commodity as
sugar or coffee.” “And I will pay more for that ability,” said John
D., “than for any other under the sun.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Education,” said Dr. John G. Hibben, former president of Princeton
University, “is the ability to meet life’s situations.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A great man shows his greatness by the way he treats little men. – Carlyle</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Every man I meet is my superior in some way, in that, I learn of him. –
  Emerson</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-value-of-a-smile-at-christmas">The Value of A Smile at Christmas</h2>

<ul>
  <li>It costs nothing, but creates much.</li>
  <li>It enriches those who receive, without impoverishing those who give.</li>
  <li>It happens in a flash and the memory of it sometimes lasts forever.</li>
  <li>None are so rich they can get along without it, and none so poor but are
richer for its benefits.</li>
  <li>It creates happiness in the home, fosters good will in a business, and is the
countersign of friends.</li>
  <li>It is rest to the weary, daylight to the discouraged, sunshine to the sad, and
Nature’s best antidote fee trouble.</li>
  <li>Yet it cannot be bought, begged, borrowed, or stolen, for it is something that
is no earthly good to anybody till it is given away.</li>
  <li>And if in the last-minute rush of Christmas buying some of our salespeople
should be too tired to give you a smile, may we ask you to leave one of yours?</li>
  <li>For nobody needs a smile so much as those who have none left to give.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="never-say-you-are-wrong">Never say you are wrong</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Men must be taught as if you taught them not. And things unknown proposed as
things forgot. – Alexander Pope</li>
  <li>You cannot teach a man anything; you can only help him to find it within
himself. – Galileo</li>
  <li>Be wiser than other people if you can; but do not tell them so. – Lord
Chesterfield</li>
  <li>I have found it of enormous value when I can permit myself to understand the
other people. The way in which I have worded this statement may seem strange
to you. Is it necessary to permit oneself to understand another? I think it
is. Our first reaction to most of the statements (which we hear from other
people) is an evaluation or judgment, rather than an understanding of it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="admit-your-mistakes">Admit your mistakes</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Any fool can try to defend his or her mistakes - and most fools do - but it
raises one above the herd and gives one a feeling of nobility and exultation
to admit one’s mistakes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="let-the-other-person-feel-that-idea-is-his-or-hers">Let the other person feel that idea is his or hers</h2>

<ul>
  <li>In every work of genius, we recognize our own rejected thoughts, they came
back to us with a certain alienated majesty. —— Ralph Waldo Emerson</li>
  <li>The reason why rivers and seas receive the homage of a hundred mountain
streams is that they keep below them. Thus they are able to reign over all the
mountain streams. So the sage, wishing to be above men, put himself below
them; wishing t be before them, he put himself behind them. Thus, though his
place be above men, they do not feel his weight; though his place be before
them, they do not count it an injury. – Lao-tse</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="try-honestly-to-see-things-from-other-persons-point-of-view">Try honestly to see things from other person’s point of view</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I would rather walk the sidewalk in front of a person’ office for two hours
before an interview than step into that office without a perfectly clear idea
of what I was going to say and what that person - from my knowledge of his or
her interests and motives - was likely to answer. – Dean Donham of the
Harvard business school.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="be-hearty-in-your-approbation-and-lavish-in-your-praise">Be “hearty in your approbation and lavish in your praise”</h2>

<p>The principles taught in this book will work only when they come from the
heart. I am not advocating a bag of tricks. I am talking about a new way of
life.</p>

<p>Talking about changing people. If you and I will inspire the people with whom we
come in contact to a realization of the hidden treasures they possess, we can do
far more than changing people. We can literally transform them.</p>

<p>Exaggeration? Then listen to these sage words from William James, one of the
most distinguished psychiatrists and philosopher America has ever produced:</p>

<pre><code>Compared with what we ought to be, we are only half awake. We are making use
of only a small part of our physical and mental resources. Stating the thing
broadly, the human individual thus lives far within his limits. He possesses
powers of various sorts which he habitually fails to use.
</code></pre>

<h2 id="effective-leader">Effective Leader</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Be sincere. Do not promise anything that you cannot deliver. Forget about the
benefits to yourself and concentrate on the benefits to the other person.</li>
  <li>Know exactly what it is you want the other person to do.</li>
  <li>Be empathetic. Ask yourself what is it the other person really wants.</li>
  <li>Consider the benefits that person will receive from doing what you suggest.</li>
  <li>Match those benefits to the other person’s wants.</li>
  <li>When you make your request, put it in a form that covey to the other person
the idea that he personally will benefit.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt from The Will Power Instinct]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/excerpt-from-the-will-power-instinct/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-31T21:06:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/08/31/excerpt-from-the-will-power-instinct</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This excerpt is the final chapter of the book,
<em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Willpower-Instinct-Self-Control-Matters/dp/1583335080/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1409490772&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=the+will+power+instinct">The Will Power Instinct</a></em>,
which summarizes the points in the book.</p>

<p>To try to make the summary more compact, I may summary it into the
following points:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The book utilizes the discoveries from neuroscience, which gives a
simple explanation of the mechanism how human brain works. With
such understanding, it tries to understand self control and makes it
work.</li>
  <li>The key point to self control is you have something to pursue,
fight for or want to protect, which is described as <em>I want</em> power
in the book.</li>
</ol>

<!-- more -->

<p>We started our journey together in the savannah of the Serengeti,
being chased by a saber-toothed tiger. Now we find ourselves here, on
the last few pages, ending our tour. Along the way, we’ve seen chimps
display extraordinary self-control, and quite a few humans lose
control. We’ve visited laboratories where dieters must resist
chocolate cake, and anxiety sufferers must face their fears. We’ve
watched as neuroscientists discovered the promise of reward, and
neuromarketers discovered its payoff. We’ve come across interventions
that use pride, forgiveness, exercise, meditation, peer pressure,
money, sleep, and even God to motivate people to change their
ways. We’ve met psychologists who shock rats, torture smokers, and
tempt four-year-olds with marshmallows —all in the name of the science
of willpower.</p>

<p>I hope this tour has provided more than a voyeur’s glimpse into the
fascinating world of research. Each of these studies teaches us
something about ourselves and our own willpower challenges. They help
us recognize our natural capacity for self-control, even if we
sometimes struggle to use it. They help us understand our failures and
point at possible solutions. They even tell us something about what it
means to be human. For example, we’ve seen again and again that we are
not one self, but multiple selves. Our human nature includes both the
self that wants immediate gratification, and the self with a higher
purpose. We are born to be tempted, and born to resist. It is just as
human to feel stressed, scared, and out of control as it is to find
the strength to be calmand in charge of our choices. Self-control is a
matter of understanding these different parts of ourselves, not
fundamentally changing who we are. In the quest for self-control, the
usual weapons we wield against ourselves—guilt, stress, and
shame—don’t work. People who have the greatest self-control aren’t
waging self-war. They have learned to accept and integrate these
competing selves.</p>

<p>If there is a secret for greater self-control, the science points to
one thing: the power of paying attention. It’s training the mind to
recognize when you’re making a choice, rather than running on
autopilot. It’s noticing how you give yourself permission to
procrastinate, or how you use good behavior to justify
self-indulgence. It’s realizing that the promise of reward doesn’t
always deliver, and that your future self is not a superhero or a
stranger. It’s seeing what in your world—from sales gimmicks to social
proof—is shaping your behavior. It’s staying put and sensing a craving
when you’d rather distract yourself or give in. It’s remembering what
you really want, and knowing what really makes you feel
better. Self-awareness is the one “self ” you can always count on to
help you do what is difficult, and what matters most. And that is the
best definition of willpower I can think of.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excerpt of V for Vendette]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/06/27/excerpt-of-v-for-vendette/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-27T19:21:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/06/27/excerpt-of-v-for-vendette</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="excerpt">Excerpt</h2>

<p>And the truth is, there is something terribly wrong with this country, isn’t
there? Cruelty and injustice, intolerance and oppression. And where once you had
the freedom to object, to think and speak as you saw fit, you now have censors
and systems of surveillance coercing your conformity and soliciting your
submission. How did this happen? Who’s to blame? Well certainly there are those
more responsible than others, and they will be held accountable, but again truth
be told, if you’re looking for the guilty, you need only look into a mirror. I
know why you did it. I know you were afraid. Who wouldn’t be? War, terror,
disease. There were a myriad of problems which conspired to corrupt your reason
and rob you of your common sense. Fear got the best of you, and in your panic
you turned to the now high chancellor, Adam Sutler. He promised you order, he
promised you peace, and all he demanded in return was your silent, obedient
consent.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="content">Content</h2>

<p>Good evening, London.</p>

<p>Allow me first to apologize for this interruption. I do,
like many of you, appreciate the comforts of every day routine – the security
of the familiar, the tranquility of repetition. I enjoy them as much as any
bloke. But in the spirit of commemoration, thereby those important events of the
past usually associated with someone’s death or the end of some awful bloody
struggle, are celebration with a nice holiday, I thought we could mark this
November the 5th, a day that is sadly no longer remembered, by taking some time
out of our daily lives to sit down and have a little chat.</p>

<p>There are of course those who do not want us to speak. I suspect even now,
orders are being shouted into telephones, and men with guns will soon be on
their way. Why? Because while the truncheon may be used in lieu of conversation,
words will always retain their power. Words offer the means to meaning, and for
those who will listen, the enunciation of truth.</p>

<p>And the truth is, there is something terribly wrong with this country, isn’t
there? Cruelty and injustice, intolerance and oppression. And where once you had
the freedom to object, to think and speak as you saw fit, you now have censors
and systems of surveillance coercing your conformity and soliciting your
submission. How did this happen? Who’s to blame? Well certainly there are those
more responsible than others, and they will be held accountable, but again truth
be told, if you’re looking for the guilty, you need only look into a mirror. I
know why you did it. I know you were afraid. Who wouldn’t be? War, terror,
disease. There were a myriad of problems which conspired to corrupt your reason
and rob you of your common sense. Fear got the best of you, and in your panic
you turned to the now high chancellor, Adam Sutler. He promised you order, he
promised you peace, and all he demanded in return was your silent, obedient
consent.</p>

<p>Last night I sought to end that silence. Last night I destroyed the Old Bailey,
to remind this country of what it has forgotten. More than four hundred years
ago a great citizen wished to embed the fifth of November forever in our memory.
His hope was to remind the world that fairness, justice, and freedom are more
than words, they are perspectives.</p>

<p>So if you’ve seen nothing, if the crimes of this government remain unknown to
you then I would suggest you allow the fifth of November to pass unmarked. But
if you see what I see, if you feel as I feel, and if you would seek as I seek,
then I ask you to stand beside me one year from tonight, outside the gates of
Parliament,and together we shall give them a fifth of November that shall </p>

<p>never,</p>

<p>ever</p>

<p>be forgot.</p>

<p>V：晚上好，伦敦。</p>

<p>请允许我为此突然打扰而道歉。是的，正像你们当中的许多人，享受机械而安逸的生活，熟悉的安全感，死气沉沉，周而复始的生活。我也你们一样。但依照纪念的精神，过去的那些重要事情往往同某些人死或者血腥斗争的终结联系起来，成立了一个值得纪念的日子，我们可以称它为历史性的11月5日。不幸的是现在没有人纪念这个日子，取而代之的是从我们的日常生活当中花时间聊天。</p>

<p>确实有人不愿我们谈论此事。我怀疑即使现在，命令通过电话来发布，武装人员随时待命。为什么？因为警棍代替了谈判，对于那些听命的人，命令仍然有它的力量，命令有它的内涵，命令就是对真相的诠释。</p>

<p>但真相是：这个国家出现了很严重的问题！不是吗？残酷和不公，狭隘与压迫。而从前你们有权利置疑，思考你认为正确的事务。但现在却有了完善的监察系统强迫你们服从他们的意志。为什么会这样？谁该为此负责？好吧，有人比其他任何人都赋有责任。但当真相再次被揭穿时，如果你在审视自己是否有负罪感，你只要照照镜子。我知道你们为什么这样做。我知道你们是害怕，谁不会呢？战争、恐怖分子、疾病。无数的阴谋正在腐化你们的原则以及制约你的判断力。恐惧占据了你们的内心，而你们持着这个恐惧的心理投靠了你们的最高长官－－亚当·苏特勒（注意：此名发音同“希特勒”极其相似！）。他保证你们拥有正常社会秩序，允诺你们和平，他像要的回报只有你们的沉默、服从和认同。</p>

<p>昨晚，我看到了沉默的终结；昨晚我炸毁了the
Old
Bailey（建筑，老贝里街）。提醒这个国家他们所忘却的东西。400多年起一个伟人像要将11月5日永远嵌入我们的记忆中。他希望提醒我们：公平、公正和自由并不是文字游戏，他们是理念！</p>

<p>所以如果你什么都没看到，如果你们始终对这个政府的罪恶一无所知，我建议你关注即将来临的那个11月。但如果你看到了我看到的，如果你感受到了我感受到的，如果你寻觅我也在寻觅的，你们明年的这一天站在我身边，在国会大厦的门外，齐心协力，我们将奉献一个让世人永生难忘的11月5日。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
