<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shawn</title>
    <description>&lt;h1&gt;Children of The Sun&lt;/h1&gt; </description>
    <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 11:11:44 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 11:11:44 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Internet in Restricted Regions: Shadowsocks, OpenVPN and BIND</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I would stay in areas of China where the widely used commercial VPNs do not
work very well for some time. Thus, I have to build a customized solution to
access to the restricted Internet. This is the note on how pieces are fit
together to build virtual private network (VPN) so that the Internet access of
software won’t be blocked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-recipe&quot;&gt;The Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A virtual private server (VPS) that is that blocked.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadowsocks (SS), a proxy software that encrypts the traffic between sockets on
end servers and clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OpenVPN, a VPN software that builds virtual private networks through tunnels etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BIND, a software that provides DNS service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;execute-summary&quot;&gt;Execute summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up SS server side on the VPS, cf. the installation guides on
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/shadowsocks/shadowsocks/wiki&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt; of
Shadowsocks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up SS client side on the devices that plan to use the proxy,
also according to the guide referred to previously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up OpenVPN on the server. A guide could be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/OpenVPN#Create_a_Public_Key_Infrastructure_(PKI)_from_scratch&quot;&gt;OpenVPN
page&lt;/a&gt;
on the ArchWiki. The process is broken down briefly at &lt;a href=&quot;#a-quick-explanation-on-the-authentication-setup-of-openvpn&quot;&gt;A quick explanation on the authentication setup of OpenVPN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OpenVPN is setup over SS. Technically, OpenVPN can circumvent
Internet blocking on its own, however, it might be rather signatory. Packing
the traffic through SS would prevent the traffic being easily detected. The
guide to this setup is given in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/shadowsocks/shadowsocks/wiki/Connect-to-OpenVPN-over-Shadowsocks&quot;&gt;Wiki&lt;/a&gt;
of SS, and is copied in &lt;a href=&quot;#connect-to-openvpn-over-shadowsocks&quot;&gt;Connect to OpenVPN over
Shadowsocks&lt;/a&gt;, since it is rather short.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable package forward as guided in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Internet_sharing#Enable_packet_forwarding&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and allow VPN traffic through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;iptables&lt;/code&gt; firewall as guided
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/OpenVPN#Routing_client_traffic_through_the_server&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
(further explanation could be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://openvpn.net/community-resources/how-to/#redirect&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a DNS server on the VPN using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bind9&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-quick-explanation-on-the-authentication-setup-of-openvpn&quot;&gt;A quick explanation on the authentication setup of OpenVPN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certificates and private keys should be created on the VPS, your device using
easyrsa, following the guide
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Easy-RSA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The guide given does the
following. Three pairs of certificates and keys are to be created when setting
up OpenVPN. The first is a pair for a Certificate Authority (CA). The CA
maintains all the trusted ends that operate in the VPN. The Arch Wiki suggests
that the machine that serves as the CA should be separate from the OpenVPN
server. Ideally, this should be so, but it could be the same with the OpenVPN
server. Then, two pairs are created by for the server and the client. The CA
need to sign the certificates of the server and the client. There are some
configuration files to take care of. The process would set up the trust
relationship between nodes in the VPN, and make OpenVPN going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;connect-to-openvpn-over-shadowsocks&quot;&gt;Connect to OpenVPN over Shadowsocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add these lines to the client side conf file of OpenVPN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    socks-proxy 127.0.0.1 1080
    route SHADOWSOCKS_SERVER_IP 255.255.255.255 net_gateway
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 10:26:11 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2020/07/07/open-internet-in-restricted-regions-shadowsocks-openvpn-and-bind/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2020/07/07/open-internet-in-restricted-regions-shadowsocks-openvpn-and-bind/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Linux</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>过去几个月的读书随笔(时代的过渡——知识、社区和自治)</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一些日子以前，我无意在谷歌上搜索了“社会运动”(social movement)一词，然后发现了维基百科上的&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_social_movements&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;社会运动列表&lt;/em&gt;(List of social movements)&lt;/a&gt;的条目。在这篇文章里，我点开了一条&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_citizens_movement&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;全球公民运动&lt;/em&gt;(Global Citizen Movement)&lt;/a&gt;的条目。而其打开了新世界的大门。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some days ago, I accidentally searched for “social movement” on Google, and find the entry &lt;em&gt;List of social movements&lt;/em&gt;. In it, I followed through a movement named Global Citizen Movement. And it opened the door for me the prospect of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;之前，因为信息闭塞的环境，以及高强度的学术研究，我并没有意识到在全球各地萌芽的社会运动，即是它们多数的历史都不足十年——非常可能的是零八年的经融危机是这些社会运动的催化剂。所有的社会运动背后都需要一套哲学，所以我研究方式一直都是由存在的哲学来反推在世界上可能存在的社会运动。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, as a result of the isolating environment, also the high demand of academic research, I did not have access to the whole body of social movement that is budding all over the world, though most of them only rose not more than ten years ago. Very likely, the financial crisis in 2008 is the catalyzer. All movement needs a thematic philosophy behind it. The philosophy is my approach to discover traces of social movements around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;沿着Murray Bookchin的哲学，我了解到了Amir Taaki以及在Rojava的运动。因为当地的政治环境，在Rojava的运动充满了激进，同时令人悲伤的暴力冲突色彩。尽管对这场运动十分有同理心，Amir Taaki的道路(cause)在我来看还是过于激进了。这种方式十分适合北叙利亚的地方情境，却并不像是能够在根本上重新设计其他地方的基于资本主义的社会经济。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following Murray Bookchin’s philosophy, I learned about Amir Taaki, and the movement in Rojava. Due to the local political situation there, the movement is radical, sadly violent. Despite being sympathetic about the movement, and the cause of Amir Taaki, it is a little radical for me. It is highly tailed to the local context of Northern Syria, but it does not feels like reinventing capitalistic economic elsewhere in a fundamental way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;写到这里，我决定开始用中文。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;之后，溯寻约翰杜威(Jhon Dowey)的&lt;a href=&quot;https://americanhumanist.org/what-is-humanism/manifesto3/&quot;&gt;人道主义者宣言（Huamnist Manifesto)&lt;/a&gt;，我了解到了世界各处的人道主义者英国（Humanists UK)。我完成了他们提供的两套课程：&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futurelearn.com/courses/introducing-humanism&quot;&gt;人道主义者介绍——非宗教的生活方式（Introducing Humanism: Non-religious Approaches to Life)&lt;/a&gt;和&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futurelearn.com/courses/humanist-lives&quot;&gt;人道主义者的生活（Humanist Lives）&lt;/a&gt;。整体来说，全球的人道主义者组织，比如美国人道主义协会（American Humanists Association），也是在他们的上下文下开展进行工作。其主要的重心仍在于反对宗教对社会的控制，比如废除亵渎宗教法(Blashphemy Law)。　虽然人道主义者宣言里的内容是联合国普师人权宣言（Universal Declaration of Human Rights）的基础，且是当今可能唯一能够作为世界公民行事准则的一套哲学框架，人道主义者作为一个组织，并没有在处理整个世界最根本的问题。至于什么是如今最根本的问题，以后有机会再详述了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;虽然作为运动而言，人道主义并没有在促进人类发展的道路上有着旺盛的生命力，了解到人道主义者联盟的局限也让我理解到无神论作为如今哲学的一个雨伞式的框架。于是，我想起来我之前搁置的一本思想史，&lt;a href=&quot;https://book.douban.com/subject/25976044/&quot;&gt;《无神论者的时代：在神逝去之后我们寻找如何生活》（The Age of Atheists: How We Have Sought to Live Since the Death of God）&lt;/a&gt;。这本书尚在读，暂按下不表。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这基本是这几个月的在研究人类在处理本世纪困境的进展。总的来说，在这个调研的过程中，虽然看见世界各地各种各样的人和组织仍在思考人类的困境和出路，但总是能够或隐约或明显得看见其方案和行动的局限，从而总是带有一种忧郁。直到最近那一次无意的谷歌搜索。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在全球公民运动的条目的引用里，我找到了一篇06年Tellus研究院关于全球公民运动的研究报告，&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tellus.org/pub/Dawn_of_the_Cosmopolitan.pdf&quot;&gt;《大都会的黎明：全球公民运动的希望》（Dawn of the Cosmopolitan: The Hope of a Global Citizens Movement）&lt;/a&gt;。从而根据该机构的一系列报告报告，找到了当今社会运动的线索。沿溯这条线索，我看到了在蒙特利尔（Montreal）的&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.p2pfoundation.net/tag/sensorica&quot;&gt;Sensorica&lt;/a&gt;，一个通过一套透明的贡献记录系统以社区形式达成协作，从而搭建开放的价值网络；在德国的&lt;a href=&quot;https://primer.commonstransition.org/4-more/5-elements/case-studies/case-study-fairmondo&quot;&gt;Fairmondo&lt;/a&gt;，一个以搭建公有的避免亚马逊和eBay的恶意垄断和不合理分配的网络商贸平台；以及各种处理大规模、跨领域协作的政治哲学方案，比如在&lt;a href=&quot;nextsystem.org&quot;&gt;未来系统&lt;/a&gt;的创始人的&lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextsystem.org/principles&quot;&gt;多元联邦（Pluralist Commonwealth）&lt;/a&gt;。如此类似的内容，多不胜数，尚待整理。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;总结来说，这些努力的背后的哲学和其想要搭建的经济基础和我模糊想象中的不谋而合。简而言之，之所以这些新的生产力组织方式和政治参与制度在我们时代的出现，而不在从前，除去过去一百年在社会改革方面的经验之外，是因为科技的发展，让后稀缺（Post-scarcity）的知识经济，全球化的透明的分布式协作，成为可能。具体可见P2P Foundation的&lt;a href=&quot;https://commonstransition.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Commons-Transition_-Policy-Proposals-for-a-P2P-Foundation.pdf&quot;&gt;《共有过渡：开放知识共有社会的政策提案》（Commons Transition: Policy Proposals for an Open Knowledge Commons Society）&lt;/a&gt;。这篇随笔并不想仔细阐释这背后的逻辑和愿景。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在了解到这个世界上其实是有人意识到我担忧的问题并且已经为之付出行动多年，莫名地感觉有种心头大石落下的放松感。我是一个智性类型的（Intellectual type）的人，如果这个世界能够平稳地向前运转，我更想做的事情其实是安安静静地研究事物的本源，或借古人言，寻道。我暂且把人们的追求分为两类，超越性的和生活性的。虽这两类缺一不可——一个世纪的理性时代之后接着的即是一个世纪的浪漫主义时代——超越性的追求在我的生活里想来应该是占据了绝大部分。大而化之，无论人类的社会还是自然的规律都是有迹可循，虽然最终人们所有的努力都只是在人类这个种族之内有意义，短期内，一个人的努力可能是和当时的社会脱节的，如哥德尔、特斯拉、爱因斯坦在研究不完备定理、行星通讯系统、相对论的时候。当发现这个世界还是正面的领导(Leadership)的时候，心中的那种忧郁仿佛就消散了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;犹记多年以前，阅托克维尔的《论美国的民主》，那时是何等地惊叹在中华还在打鸦片战争的时代，美利坚已经开始建立了一个酝酿美国梦的社会。虽然无论是清朝的1840年还是前废奴战争的美利坚，当时形成的简单化的印象在如今看来都是天真的，那种希望了解如何一个社会能够构建得“美好”的执念却如影随形，直至今日。改变的是对“美好”这个充满无限哲理词汇的理解。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;终于，我可以思考玩闹一些没有使命感的事情，不再杞人忧天了。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 17:00:33 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/notes-knowledge-community-and-municipalism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/notes-knowledge-community-and-municipalism/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Social_Movement</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I Have Lived For</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have sought truth first, in the universal abstract world of mathematics, and
the constructive concrete world of hacking. Meanwhile, I sought the salvation
of humanities, and myself, in the world of philosophers who have sought in the
time before me, and the stories weaved with love and tears in the history of
mankind. In doing so, I hope to find the answer to the existence of life, and
the answer to seemingly unbearable human suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
I found loneliness,
I found the solitary pain
that gnaws the heart,
But also peace I do find.

Sorrow is knowledge; they who know the most
Must mourn the deepest over the fatal truth.
Yet, the tree of Knowledge is also that of Life.

It reveals
Love as our Nature,
and Reason is our Blessing;
Ethereal can weave with Mundane,
and Peace
Lies in Making.

Now, Old yet still Young
I have known you.
And, knowing you,
I have found both ecstasy &amp;amp; peace;
I know the rest.

After so many solitary years,
I know what Life may be,
though I may still not know Love.

Now, if I could keep moving,
I see Possibilities.
I shall Sail,
As if I am still Young.
&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 11:03:38 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/what-i-have-lived-for/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/08/31/what-i-have-lived-for/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intuition That Motivates Inverse Transform Sampling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post notes down the observation that motives inverse transform sampling
(ITS) to sample from any probability distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given a random variable (r.v.) $X$, and a pseudo-random number generator that
can emit uniform random numbers, how to derive a method to sample from any
distribution? The answer has been rather mystic for me at the first time that I
learned about the inverse transform sampling in a distance time ago. I
revisited the issue today, and decide to outline the intuition behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not easy to characterize randomness in a computer that is built on
deterministic Turing model. So the randomness comes from pseudonumber
generator. I did not know the machinery to generate pseudo-random numbers, but
I guess obtaining uniform number are hand-crafted procedure that are manually
designed. So it is probably hard to devise one sampler for uniform
distribution. The difficulty may be similar imagined in the physical world,
where sampling are performed physically relying on the principle of symmetry,
e.g., throwing a coin; we cannot do sampling if we do not have the physical
process that has such type of randomness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, how can be convert the manpower involved in the pseudo-random generator
to generate other probability distributions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To motivate ITS, we need to go back to the measure-theoretical definition of
probability, which I will skip. With necessary background in advanced
probability theory, we can have the following derivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have a transform $T$, such that $\nu(T(X)) = \mu (T^{-1}(X))$. Given
a set $E \in \mathcal{E}$, where $\mathcal{E}$ is the measurable space of $X$,
we have the measure of a set $F \in \mathcal{F}$ as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\nu(T(E)) = \mu (T^{-1}(F))&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the intuition underlying the seeming magic underlying ITS, which is
normally not discussed, as in the Wikipedia
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_transform_sampling&quot;&gt;entry&lt;/a&gt;. That is, we
are manipulating the probability measure to a form that we can compute.
Then, if we can obtain a sample $y$ according to $\nu$, $T^{-1}(y)$ is the
sample we would get if we obtain a sample according to $\mu$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if the above statement were true, $T$ should be monotonous, so measure
of different values does not overlap. Otherwise, the probability to sample $y$
is the probability of all elements of $X$ that are mapped to $y$,
i.e., $\forall x, T(x) = y$. In the one-dimensional case, monotony can
concentrate the measure of an interval, e.g., $[a, b] \subset \mathbb{R}$, to
an interval $[c, d] \subset \mathbb{R}$; that is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\nu ([c, d]) = \int_{a}^{b} \mu(x) dx, c = T(a), d = T(b)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we need to manipulate $F$ so that $T(F)$ is computable, where comes the
Cumulative Distribution Function (CDF). Let $\mu$ be the CDF of $\mu$. Observe
that the meaning of $\nu[0, c]$ are literally, &lt;em&gt;the probability $T(x)$ lies in
$[0, c]$ is $c$&lt;/em&gt;; that is the definition of uniform distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the derivation of Inverse Transform Sampling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 20:37:39 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/02/21/intuition-that-motivates-inverse-transform-sampling/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/02/21/intuition-that-motivates-inverse-transform-sampling/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Math</category>
        
        <category>Statistics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scientific Humanism</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading the Wikipedia page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._O._Wilson#Scientific_humanism&quot;&gt;Edward
 O. Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, I
 re-discovered the &lt;a href=&quot;http://americanhumanist.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/HumanismandItsAspirations_jefferson1.pdf&quot;&gt;Humanism Manifesto
 III&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I have known the manifesto for several years. Back then at the
first time I read the manifesto, it sounded exactly the philosophy that I am
looking for. But, the action of &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanists.international/&quot;&gt;Humanist
International&lt;/a&gt; (HI), the umbrella
organization to advocate scientific humanism does not feel right for me. The
impression I was left was that HI reactively fights against religion, against
non-freedom. Darkness could not be beaten up to bear light; it’s fire that lets
lights born. The fight over freedom, over religion has long been won since the
capitalism revolution against the theological authoritarianism. The victory was
only partly political, which feels like is the focus of HI. The other
indispensable part is social-economical. The old feudal agricultural
social-economical structure was replaced by a commercial cooperative
social-economical structure; and that is the foundation of the political
change. However, the problem of our age is exactly the pathological development
of barbarism capitalism, which was what socialism revolutionized against in the
past, the root of the social tumult in the past century, and the rising of
populism recently. That is to say, I feel that HI is a legacy fighting a ghost
under the banner of scientific humanism. That’s why I gradually lost my
attention on it previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, I did not know Edward O. Wilson, and his &lt;em&gt;Consilient of Knowledge&lt;/em&gt;. I
did not know that the first manifesto was drafted under the leadership of John
Dewey. That is to say, I wrongly mistook HI for Humanist Manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I started to think that the manifesto &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; the philosophy of our time in
its infancy. I am investigating it from time to time. The investigation mostly
focuses on a new social-economical structure could be built on such a
philosophy, and what kind of a new institution that would be devised from the
new social-economical structure; and also the alignment of force that under
such a philosophy — if there exists a community like the Invisible College in
the Age of Reason, the Vienna Circle in the pre-WWII age, or Homebrew Computer
Club in the aftermath of Counter Culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thematic-development-of-western-philosophy-since-renaissance&quot;&gt;Thematic Development of Western Philosophy Since Renaissance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated on May 26th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just start to be aware of the full spectrum of philosophy developed under the
banner of humanism, which is quite diverse, and overwhelming (for now). The
humanist UK has a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://humanism.org.uk/humanism/the-humanist-tradition/&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; of the
philosophers who developed scientific humanism in the 20th centry. I am not
familiar with the development outlined there, though I start to understand the
progress in philosophy in the 20th, which I previously thought has stalled ever
since Satre and Wittgenstein — the political philosophy, e.g., the Theory of
Justice by Rawls in my opinion is derivative philosophy, an extension of
social liberalism, not a very novel philosophical development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would outline an over-simplifying thematic development philosophy since the
Renaissance as follows, partly for research logging purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from the 14th century, the commercial development (further research
needed) at the end of Middle Age led to the social-economical precondition, and
political motivation (to assert the King’s authority instead of the Pope’s), to
make possible the development of the wide awareness of human potential. This
was the start of the modern humanism. It mostly reflected in arts, and a
renewed interests to understand the natural world, instead of settling with
superstitious explanation. The philosophy in this period mostly focused on
counter-strike the established theology, e.g., the works of Erasmus on
Bibles. The corrupted ruling class catalyzed this process, which led to the
Protestant movements. The agents of the development in this period is the
artists gathered under King’s patronage, and the Protestants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crumpling of the worldview build by God and angels led to a reconstruction
of a new worldview. First, the worldview was built by seeking the wisdom in
Ancient Greek philosophers. Then as time passed, intellectuals started to
formulate a systematical rational view of the world. As any novel ideas in its
budding period, an over optimistic outlook prevailed, and it led to the
under-trained to think that a complete explanation of nature, universe and
human society could be achieved through rational thinking. The agents of the
development in this period were the natural philosophers, or initial scientists,
loosely named the Invisible College. They were mostly aristocrats interested in
science. Yet to note that God was never completely disappear in the new
philosophy, as in “All men are created equal, that hat they are endowed by
their Creator with certain unalienable Rights …”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For about a century, the optimistic outlooks started to disappoint people,
especially for the ones that were outsider of the development. The unanswered
emotional parts of rationality led to the development to the Romantic Age in
the first half of the 19th century. This long suppressed philosophy that looks
at the present instead of the future, which reason normally looks at. It let
people to treasure the ephemeral now, and focus on living a life, instead of
rationally thinking what life is, and could be. Ultimately, it is more livable
for the most.  Reason represents the ascetic side of humans, while romantics
represents the aesthetic side. No one can live in either side of them from the
beginning to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the emphasis on individuality, and feeling tends to be self-centered,
and makes people unaware of the struggling of the others. The development of
Romantics accompanied, or co-evolved major political and social-economical
development. First, by the 18th century, the common purpose that bound the
humanists broke loose: the authoritarianism of theological rule had been
overthrown. The dragon slayer became the dragon. Second, the industry
revolution started. The original agricultural style exploitation had morphed to
another form, the capitalism exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world slipped into the imperial period, where major powers fought with each
other to get lands that contained raw materials and produced labor, and markets
where the manufactured goods can be sold to keep the capitalism flying. This
was the darkest time of capitalism. As the dragon slayers turned evil, the new
slayers were born, which was socialism. It gave the poor the Utopian hope that
the Heaven once had given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as liberalism threw away theological authoritarian, it also
destroyed moral constraints that were critical to build community, which was
critical to exist in the ruling class to build bonds that were beyond material
interests. As the lower class turned to socialism, the now ruling liberalism
elites tried to instill the morality back in the Victoria Queen’s reign. And
during the reign, things were good. (more facts check needed)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then time passed into the 20th century. The development of socialism could be
understood as the further broadening of the individual rights not only to the
aristocrats, but also commoners. Its gravest errors were that it takes a
considerable personal journey and education to become an aristocrats, in the
sense of honor, merits, service etc, not in the sense of birth rights. Without
it, it is mob ruling. The Victoria moralism was a look back to the good days of
Christianity, thus it could cease to exist as the legendary Queen stepped down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed, the liberalism society was built on a worldview reconstructed
through rationality. Thus, it subjected to change as the worldview had been
changed by rationality. A very critical development happened at the turn of the
century: a majority of the intellectuals started to realize the so glorified
humans are just another species of animals. The realization mostly based on the
wide acceptance of the bleak view of Darwin’s works, and the mechanical
deterministic physics worldview matured at the turn of the century. In simple
words, the long overdue systematic explanation since the Age of Reason actually
gave the answer that humans are just meaningless in the cosmetic sense. We are
not the beloved children of the God, or the measure of all things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the once respected guiding force of rationality broke down. It was also a
time of sharp conflict. The cake were not big enough for all nations in the
world, especially in the Europe, thus the ruling class clashed with each
other. The problem of fetish capitalism described before had developed to the
point of uncontainable, thus the commoners clashed with the ruling
class. Meanwhile, rationality gave a doomed “Survival of the Fittest”
worldview. People turned to nationalism and to communism for hope. War broke
out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wars started, and wars ended. The wars taught everyone a grave lesson. Nation
should respect each other sovereignty, and try to cooperate no matter how
insignificant the other part may seem. The privileged should respect the
under-privileged, otherwise, no one would live a decent life. The United Nations
finally worked, and social liberalism was born. The new world order started to
build around a new global liberal order, and nations cooperated with each other
on trades. Colonies gradually disappeared. On the pressure of Soviet Union, and
the influence of socialism, unions became a major force in the capitalism
societies, and counter-balanced the fetish for profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the philosophical existential crisis for humans never ceased. To live
without a cosmetic purpose, philosophers tried to find solid ground men’s lives
may build on. One school was the logic school, represented by Bertrand Russell
etc., that tried to build a solid foundation of the world through axioms and
logic. The other school was the continent school, the phenomenology,
represented Satre etc. The logic school failed since the work of Godel, who
proved an axiom system cannot prove itself is right, and died more or less as
the consequence of such a devastating proof. The phenomenology ended up in
“aghast”: men created meanings for themselves, despite the artificial
fabrication. Phenomenology identified a rather crucial fact that all knowledge
comes from the senses of people. But it did not build a systematic livable
philosophy on its own. At the end of the day, Satre turned to Humanism. They
both had fallen short because they could not go beyond the ontology set by
science, which waited for a new development in 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1970s, a new kind of science called complexity science was born. It
swiped away the deterministic view on the world, and gave an epic instead of
cosmetic narrative on humans. We human were evolved to be capable of love, to
think rationally, to be empathetic, to be artistic. The progress in modern
biology, complex system, nonlinear science has drawn another humanitarian epic
narrative, out of the Darwin jungle one — indeed we are
stardust, but we are also children of the sun: “Human social existence, unlike
animal sociality, is based on the genetic propensity to form long-term
contracts that evolve by culture into moral precepts and law. They evolved over
tens or hundreds of millennia because they conferred upon the genes prescribing
their survival and the opportunity to be represented in future generations. We
are not errant children who occasionally sin by disobeying instructions from
outside our species. We are adults who have discovered which covenants are
necessary for survival, and we have accepted the necessity of securing them by
sacred oath.” (Quote &lt;em&gt;Consilience&lt;/em&gt;, Wilson, 1999)
Though evolved from animals, and possessing their baser instincts, humans are
uniquely different from animals. The difference we may call the divine side
of humans. Though cosmetically insignificant, we are enough for ourselves; we
are enough for our planets; we are enough for our universe. This development
gives solid ontological foundation for liberty, morality (fraternity and
equality), rationality, and creativity. The philosophy built on such ontology
is called humanism now. I will write it as scientific humanism for clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as the memory of the wars faded away, history is repeating itself
again. As technology and expertise had become a more important factor in
production than labors, the power balance between worker union and capitalists
broke down. Power had become increasingly concentrated on the top 1 percent
who are not incentivized care for the rest. The tension accumulated ever since
information technology was born, and globalization started, began to erupt
after the fire light by the 2008 financial crisis. This time, socialism is of
no match, since headcount won’t count this time. The fetish for growth
incentivized by capitalism needs fixing. A new incentive mechanism that
underpins the society need to be worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, the scientific humanism is merely a philosophy, a view on life, not
even a well known one (as for as I know). I tend to think it has the potential
to build an alternative incentive mechanism in replace of the capitalism. And I
am learning how things have been doing so far now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 11:24:48 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/02/20/scientific-humanism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/02/20/scientific-humanism/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Postmodern Quandary</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who understand the word post-modernity, its presence arouses gray
melancholy. The contemporary era has faced a full spectrum of
problems. Culturally, postmodernism resigns to the alienation, ephemerality,
fragmentation and patent chaos of modern life and places individualized
aesthetics over science, rationality, politics and morality (Harvey, The
Condition of Postmodernity). Politically, procedural liberalism emphasizes an
unencumbered self at the expense of self-rule and public goods, and cannot
secure the liberty promised (Sandel, Democracy’s Discontent). Ecologically, the
seeming economical prosperity and extravagant lifestyle are overdrawing the
energy reserve and creating enormous materials wastes, pollution and
environmental complications, e.g. global warming (Clark, Ariadne’s Thread).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root of the problems are the result of 500 years’ emancipatory struggle
away from repressive gods, kings, and states (Öcalan, Manifesto for a
Democratic Civilization Vol I, II; Giddens, Modernity and Self-Identity;
Talisse, Democracy After Liberalism), without a substitute for the tranquility
and the sacred it destroyed. Underlying the facial seeking for rationality and
efficiency, the value system of social actors is money driven jungle-style
competition, inducing “fetishism of commodities”, hedonism and nihilism. The
collective actions in this complex social system guided by such value system
created the social economic condition that caused the cultural, politic and
environmental problems debriefed. Terrorism, chauvinism, religion
fundamentalism are complications of this illness (Castells, Network Society
Trilogy). Twenty years ago, Jacque judged the western culture is in decadence,
for “the loss it faces is that of Possibility” in his masterpiece From Dawn to
Decadence. Also, Castells states in End of Millennial that the key to build a
new vibrant new society is “by proposing new cultural codes with the potential
to transform the values of society”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:58:52 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/the-postmodern-quandary/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/the-postmodern-quandary/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two Types of Education</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two aspects of education: the Liberal Arts education and the
professional education. They combined could be called enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Liberal Arts education process consists of interaction between an imagined
outcome based on a preliminary interests, and its temporary results, between
piecemeal assignments and projects and feedback obtained, between questions
arising of confusion and answers to address them. The ultimate outcome is a
wake-up call that shocks one out of slumber that is self-deceitfully taken as
free will, and makes one self-conscious, not only of oneself, but also of the
society at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The professional education is the one that equips people with skills, at least to
survive, but more importantly, to solve unknown problems (here is how
professional education bridges to Liberal Arts education).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:38:07 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/two-types-of-education/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/two-types-of-education/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Education</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Utopian and Its Infrastructure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since civilization existed, humans had been longing for a Utopian society,
where people are eternally happy, yet the happiness was a mirage that burst
whenever a definition was attempted. The imagined society has been The Heaven, or Da
Tong in classic age, and Laissez-Faire, or Welfare Society after
Renaissance. Yet, after the thousands years of soul-crushing searching, in our
contemporary society, or in post-modernity, the possibilities of imagining such
a society seems to have ceased to exist, after the demolition of welfare society
since Reagon’s presidency, and the collapse of Soviet Union, though in less
developed areas, e.g., China, the people are still dreaming of the dream the
Westerners dreamed in 18th century, or the dream even in more distance past,
the God’s Heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Oh, Lord, where shall I find my comfort?
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust of Utopian dream, is not because of the failure of ideas; it is
because the incomplete of ideas, and the failure of perceiving the complexity
of implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past ideas have been trapped in reductionism thinking that
one idea would be the ultimate answer for the truth. However, the reality is
that light always is with darkness: it is not the question of absence of
darkness in the heaven, but the question of which of them has an upper
hand. The darkness is built in human nature: we evolved from animals, and they
are our animistic instincts — we kill for a living in the jungles. So are the
light; they are built in human nature as well: we evolved from animals to be a
unique species that is capable of love and morality that facilitate long-term
contract for mutual welfare, and more importantly, social welfare; of rational
thinking that discovers the laws of the universe and checks on the irrational
instincts. The darkness and light form a Tai Ching, blending in a way that
cannot be perceived without acute attentive reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;floated&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/taiching.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tai Ching&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Tai Ching&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The society consists of Homo Sapiens with dual nature is a Tai Ching as well: a
complex system has multiple phases. When the world is rife with violence, the
baser instinct to survive takes an upper hand, so Machiavelli wrote &lt;em&gt;The
Prince&lt;/em&gt;; when the world has civil societies consisting of a majority of well
educated middle class people with political awareness and leisure, the rationality and
morality take an upper hand, so Tocqueville wrote &lt;em&gt;Democracy in America&lt;/em&gt;; when
world does not have the means to educate the majority of the people, the elite
class that does have access to knowledge forms the aristocrats, priests, royal
families, so we have Catholicism, or Confucianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is not the statement that all men or women are created equal that
makes the world a happy place. Happiness is not hedonism; it is a serenity
comes after a long, normally excruciating process of practice to know what one
truly desires, based on rationality, morality, and the enjoy of miracle of just
living. Thus, to build a world that consists of happy people in the sense of
the light side of humans, education that is accessible to the majority is an
unavoidable cornerstone, otherwise, at best we would return to the feudal
society in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is to say, it is not that the institutions, or the ideas that are wrong
— they are partially right, but a lack of infrastructure to build the
precondition on which the ideas can properly function causes the collapse of the
society complex system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is to say, we need an infrastructure as cheap as food to provide
world-class education for massive enlightenment. So that the quest for equality
does not become radical destructive populism, and the quest for liberty does
not induce fetish capitalism, but a Tai Ching balance of both.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:35:30 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/utopian-and-its-infrastructure/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/utopian-and-its-infrastructure/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>机械柏拉图学院</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;9月17日下午，我们来聊一聊关于世界、关于生活的根本问题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;/images/mechanic_plato_academy.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot;  &gt; --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;活动基调&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;古者富贵而名摩灭，不可胜记，唯俶傥非常之人称焉。盖西伯拘而演《周易》；仲尼厄而
作《春秋》；屈原放逐，乃赋《离骚》；左丘失明，厥有《国语》；孙子膑脚，《兵法》
修列；不韦迁蜀，世传《吕览》；韩非囚秦，《说难》、《孤愤》。《诗》三百篇，大氐
贤圣发愤之所为作也。此人皆意有所郁结，不得通其道，故述往事，思来者。 — 《报
任安书》 司马迁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;自文明以降，先贤著书立说，多因天下失道，以“述往事，思来者”。中华方迈出两千年东
方之“黑暗时代”，然其文艺复兴又被百年动乱所打断。中国知识分子对自身文化的梳理远
未完成。希腊系文明经城邦时代开科学民主之先河、历黑暗时代神权威权统治之中世纪、
自佛罗伦萨文艺复兴、以经典自由主义造建崭新社会形态、经社会自由主义改良，在二十
世纪末，法兰西斯·福山以《The End of History &amp;amp; Last Man》一书乐观但“天真”地表达
人类体制的探索已经结束，人类社会迎来“世界的终结”。然零八年金融危机后，世界表面
的安宁被打破，英国脱欧，民粹主义盛行，川普总统，世界公民普适之日遥遥无期；中华
民间力量方才萌芽便已蒙刹；以自由之名诞生的工具精神（tools of personal
liberation）、黑客精神亦由屠龙少年被驯化为泯然众人；被称为人类最后的发明的人工
智能很可能将带来第四次工业革命，颠覆现有的社会下层基础。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;变革之时代多需哲学之变革。孔孟之道诞生于礼崩乐坏，周法不行之时；自由主义诞生于
文艺复兴，神权不再之时；存在主义诞生于世界大战，仿临近纪末日之时。无论是可生活
（inhabitable)之哲学，或可统治之哲学（政治哲学），现今社会至今我并未发现已成形
之答案。故吾辈所可做之事，乃继往圣之学，并“相信智能是有能力去想像未来的，基于值
得保留的那部分现在，从而作出对未来的一种投射，并为实现这样的一种未来而发明所需
要的工具，这是我们的救赎（John Dewey）。”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;以上是此活动之基调，望招纳志同道合之人，究往事，思来者。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;活动媒介&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;华夏的古老经常使我们忘记，中国其实多么年轻。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;用梁任公的术语说，“少年中国”仍然是“新民”。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;她步入这个拥挤的世界，已经不能再指望海阔天空的处女地。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;青春往往是痛苦而危险的，因为世界的表象和世界的律法形成了一对险恶的漩涡。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;在她最需要智慧的时刻，通常没有她所需要的语言。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;世界没有任何现成的语言能够适应她的需要。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;她只能一面发现世界，一面发明自己的语言。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;当她找到适当的语言，就会发现自己适当的位置。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;这时，诸神的天空不再变幻莫测。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;在此之前，世界仍然不会给她家园的感觉。&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;— 《从华夏到中国》 刘仲敬&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;虽谦虚被中华民族视为美德，整个民族时至今日仍充满了当年“天朝上国”的傲慢，长文论
述可参考殷海光《中国文化的展望》，而殊不知其所不知。此多非国人之过错，由于教育、
宣传、信息传播之原因，大量国人仍处在“青春期”。所以交流介质多数时间希望以&lt;em&gt;英文&lt;/em&gt;进行，以期招纳业已简单理解西方文明之人士，互通有无。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;活动内容&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;本次活动为投石问路，拟以《Dubliner》中较为简单的短篇故事为载体，寻世界新民。
《Dubliner》为James Joyce的短篇小说集，描述了爱尔兰在欧洲资产阶级革命之后巨大的
社会变革下都柏林中产阶级在寻找自己的位置、生活和认同感的故事。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因为阅读的是短篇小说，所以不会对参与过多的时间负担，我们将花两三个小时来阅读、
讨论Dubliner中的短篇小说，发现书中人物与我们所处时空的相似。&lt;em&gt;交流主要以英语进行。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;活动报名&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一次活动以十人为上限。报名采取先到先得，但后到者可通过陈述：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;参与动机；&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;学思历程（可选）；&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;阅读史（可选）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;来获取资格。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;注意：获取资格的优先级以陈述的深度最高，报名时间次之。因此，先报名者同样会由于
后来者的深度陈述而遗憾落选。所以推荐所有报名者书写陈述^_^。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;确认参与将会发予精美电子版《Dubliner》。报名结果将会通过邮件送达，所以一定要在
报名处填常用邮箱哟。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;报名截止时间为&lt;strong&gt;9月14日，周四晚十二点&lt;/strong&gt;，报名确认将在第二天周五晚十点前发出。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;活动注意事项&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;报名确认不能参加请尽快通知组织方，从而能给让出名额给其他人；无故缺席将会被记入
黑名单。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;报名链接&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huodongxing.com/event/2403775592100?td=3182774891054&quot;&gt;点这里&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:57:08 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/09/06/ji-xie-plato-academy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/09/06/ji-xie-plato-academy/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes on I-theory</title>
        <description>&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is a Hebbian style unsupervised learning algorithm that computes invariant
yet selective signature of a particular image.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Originally, the semantics meaning of the signature is the cumulative
distribution function (CDF) of a proxy distribution of the distribution of
the orbit ${ gI : g \in G }$ of $I$, where $I$ is the canonical image
template, and $G$ is transformation that may apply on $I$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proxy probability distribution is a one dimension probability
distribution induced by projecting each $gI$ to $R$ using a (possibly random)
template $t$ (taking inner product between $I$ and $t$).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The CDF is computed by using a Heaviside step function $H$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During computation of the CDF, uniform (haar) measure is used for $G$:
different $gI$ may be projected to the same value in $R$, thus the CDF at $x
\in R$ is a integral (summation) weighted by measure on group.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In practice, histogram is used and each neuron may be responsible to
represent a particular bin of the histogram (see Unsupervised learning of
invariant representations).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given the presence of the integral, the signature can also be computed using
moments, where the $H$ can be replaced with $f(x) = x^r$, since moments can
characterize distributions in certain extent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since the selectivity theorem requires the infinite number of templates,
i-theory defines Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) metric on the proxy distributions
(other metrics are possible), and uses it to prove a error bound when only a
finite number of templates are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Without using all the orbits (partially observable group), covariant
(equivariant) can be characterized in i-theory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Essentially this is a memory based system, where $gI$ is assigned uniform
measure, and the representation learned is generic (not tying with any target
function). All transforms have to be physical transform, since it needs to be
trained with training data in the form ``movies’’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus is on the properties of the signature, instead of the the space the
signature lives in, which could have rich structure. Topological structure,
metric structure of the group is not used. Probability inference does not
play a role here. Structure of the probability distribution is not used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 17:09:01 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/05/20/note-on-i-theory/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/05/20/note-on-i-theory/</guid>
        
        
        <category>NN</category>
        
        <category>Math</category>
        
        <category>Research</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
