<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shawn</title>
    <description>&lt;h1&gt;World Hacker's Notebook&lt;/h1&gt;</description>
    <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 11:54:20 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 11:54:20 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>菩提</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;身是菩提樹，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;心如明鏡台，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;時時勤拂拭，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;勿使惹塵埃。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;菩提本無樹，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;明鏡亦非台，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;本來無一物，&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;何處惹塵埃？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;故事&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在南北朝的時候，佛教禪宗傳到了第五祖弘忍大師，弘忍大師當時在湖北的黃梅開壇講學，手下有弟子五百餘人，其中翹楚者當屬大弟子神秀大師。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;神秀也是大家公認的禪宗衣缽的繼承人。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;弘忍漸漸的老去，於是他要在弟子中尋找一個繼承人，所以他就對徒弟們說，大家都做一首畿子（有禪意的詩），看誰做得好就傳衣缽給誰。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;這時神秀很想繼承衣缽，但又怕因為出於繼承衣缽的目的而去做這個畿子，違法了佛家的無為而作意境。
所以他就在半夜起來，在院牆上寫了一首畿子身是菩提樹，心為明鏡台。時時勤拂拭，勿使惹塵埃。
這首畿子的意思是，要時時刻刻的去照顧自己的心靈和心境，通過不斷的修行來抗拒外面的誘惑，和種種邪魔。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;是一種入世的心態，強調修行的作用。
而這種理解與禪宗大乘教派的頓悟是不太吻合的，所以當第二天早上大家看到這個畿子的時候，都說好，而且都猜到是神秀作的而很佩服的時候，弘忍看到了以後沒有做任何的評價。
因為他知道神秀還沒有頓悟。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;而這時，當廟裡的和尚們都在談論這首畿子的時候，被廚房裡的一個火頭僧—慧能禪師聽到了。
慧能當時就叫別人帶他去看這個畿子，這裡需要說明的一點是，慧能是個文盲，他不識字。
他聽別人說了這個畿子，當時就說這個人還沒有領悟到真諦啊。
於是他自己又做了一個畿子，央求別人寫在了神秀的畿子的旁邊，菩提本無樹，明鏡亦非台，本來無一物，何處惹塵埃。
有這首畿子可以看出慧能是個有大智慧的人（後世有人說他是十世比丘轉世），他這個畿子很契合禪宗的頓悟的理念。
是一種出世的態度，主要意思是，世上本來就是空的，看世間萬物無不是一個空字，心本來就是空的話，就無所謂抗拒外面的誘惑，任何事物從心而過，不留痕跡。
這是禪宗的一種很高的境界，領略到這層境界的人，就是所謂的開悟了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;弘忍看到這個畿子以後，問身邊的人是誰寫的，邊上的人說是慧能寫的，於是他叫來了慧能，當著他和其他僧人的面說：寫得亂七八糟，胡言亂語，並親自擦掉了這個畿子。
然後在慧能的頭上打了三下就走了。這時只有慧能理解了五祖的意思，於是他在晚上三更的時候去了弘忍的禪房，在那裡弘忍向他講解了《金剛經》這部佛教最重要的經典之一，並傳了衣缽給他。
然後為了防止神秀的人傷害慧能，讓慧能連夜逃走。於是慧能連夜遠走南方，隱居10年之後在莆田少林寺創立了禪宗的南宗。
而神秀在第二天知道了這件事以後，曾派人去追慧能，但沒有追到。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;後來神秀成為梁朝的護國法師，創立了禪宗的北宗。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 11:48:59 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/puti/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/puti/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Brave World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;我想，从今而始，新世界到来了。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 10:11:56 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/11/05/the-brave-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/11/05/the-brave-world/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Excerpts of The Glory and The Dream, Narrative History of America</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was reading this book, I did not take notes or do underlining because it
is from the library. I have much that I want to put it down. The stories of
Mrs. Roosevelt, the union movement, World War II, Korean War, the raise of
radio, the pocket radio in 60s, counter-culture in 60s, racial movement, Cuba
revolution etc. However, I only manage to do this now, about two months
later. The thread in my mind has faded way. I do not think I could skim the
book again to get those things. In the following is the ending of the book.
The end of the ending is particularly interesting. Have faith for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ending&quot;&gt;Ending&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a school of historians which holds that great events may tell us less
about the past than the trivia accumulated by ordinary people -the letters,
pressed flowers, prom programs, cherished toys and the like saved by those who
loved them and could not bear to throw them away.  From time to time
construction workers will stumble across such caches, sometimes entombed in old
mansions.  Occasionally they may find something almost as elaborate as the
Westinghouse time capsule which was buried at the New York World’s Fair
of 1939.  Such discoveries always excite curiosity, and the older ones stir
speculation over what this or that article meant to people at the time it was
put away.  With the growing mobility of Americans the accumulation of such
troves is rarer, but if members of the swing generation had once put away,
perhaps, in a storeroom the size of Fibber McGee’s fabled closet- it might
provide insight into what they had been like, what they had endured, what their
dreams had been, and which had been realized and which dashed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Envisaging such a cupboard, we see in front on the top shelf a steel tennis
racket, several dieting books, a wide necktie, and a pantsuit broad in the
beam.  Just behind them are a “Welcome Home POWs” bumper sticker, one for MIAs
(“Only Hanoi Knows” ), and a peace decal; then a brass-colored PT boat tie
clip, and cassette recordings of Camelot, Arlo Guthrie’s Alice s Restaurant,
and Carol Channing’s Hello, Dolly.  Behind them, well hidden in a corner
beneath a pile of tie-dyed jeans, are well- thumbed copies of Fanny Hill and
The Autobiography of a Flea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various items of clothing occupy much of the space on the second shelf: a
sheath dress, a gray flannel suit, a man’s narrow-brimmed felt hat, several
incredibly narrow neckties, a child’s coonskin cap, and a straw boater with the
legend i like ike on the hatband.  Concealed beneath them is an obsolete item
of female apparel: a diaphragm in a white plastic case.  Beyond is a curious
little silver lapel pin.  It resembles the bottom of a man’s shoe with a hole
in the sole.  Nearby are a My Fair Lady album, a record of Edith Piaf singing
“II Pleut,” a Winky Clink kit, a Mouseketeer cap, and a collapsed Bayby-Tenda.
Copies of Fireman Small and Peyton Place lie on top of miscellaneous papers: a
pamphlet on how to stop smoking, a Fish House Punch recipe, an Around the World
in Eighty Days program, a batch of bills from a diaper service, and an envelope
containing plans for a home bomb shelter (never opened).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the front of the third shelf is a Dior New Look skirt, an Eisenhower
jacket which appears to have been worn by a slender man, early nylons, a
freshman beanie, a copy of Tropic of Cancer, and under it a packet of three
Trojans.  (They sold for a dollar.) Various certificates: military discharge,
marriage license, college diplomas.  A ruptured duck pin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Army divisional patch.  Rationing stamps.  Navy dog tags, long tarnished.  A
packet of V-letters.  A Nazi helmet; a samurai sword.  A Kate Smith Columbia
record: “God Bless America.”  A rhinestone V-for-Victory pin.  The bottom shelf
is rather junky.  A pair of Thorn Mean saddle shoes, very dirty, stand on top
of an equally soiled reversible raincoat, beneath which is a sport coat with a
belted back.  A dead corsage is pressed between two 78 rpm records” Deep
Purple” and “Stardust.”  Beside them lie campaign pins reading “We Want
Willkie” and “FDR.”  A third pin is shaped like a sunflower.  Then: a shabby
Phiico radio in the form of an arch, a tattered copy of Gone With the Wind, a
copy of Ulysses in which only the last forty pages seem to have been read, Boy
and Girl Scout handbooks, and several square Big Little Books.  There is a
dusty Lionel train transformer, a jump rope, several marbles and one steelie, a
splintered hockey stick, a well-oiled first baseman’s mitt, a Shirley Temple
doll, a sheaf of bubble gum cards, a G-man cap gun.  Two Post Toasties box
tops.  A box of cherry bombs.  A Bolo ball attached by elastic to a paddle.  A
pair of brown corduroy knickers.  A hair ribbon.  An old stand-up telephone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, on the floor of the closet, are a batch of snapshots taken with a box
Brownie.  There are automobiles in them: a Model A Ford with the windshield
down in some, a Chevy sporting a sassy rumble seat in others, and in the older
ones, brown with age, a Model T. People are posing by the running boards.  It
is summer, yet the adults look very formal.  The men are wearing stiff collars,
the women vast hats and shapeless cotton dresses.  &lt;strong&gt;But it is the children who
seem oddest.  Like their parents they are quaintly dressed.  There is something
else, though.  It takes a moment to realize why they look so peculiar.  Then
you see it.  There is an intensity in their expressions.  They are leaning
slightly forward, as though trying to see into the future.  And they are
smiling.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 21:19:47 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/11/02/excerpts-of-the-glory-and-the-dream-narrative-history-of-america/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/11/02/excerpts-of-the-glory-and-the-dream-narrative-history-of-america/</guid>
        
        
        <category>History</category>
        
        <category>Excerpts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Key points of Understanding Deep Conv Net</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This note tries to summarize the keypoints of the paper by Mallat:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26953183&quot;&gt;Understanding deep convolutional networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key concepts: contraction, linearization, fibre, parallel transport,
multi-scale support vector&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, Convolutional Neural Network could be formalized using cascading
the following of operators that compose a function $f$, whose value is in $R$
for regression problems, and is the index of the sample’s class for
classification problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;x_j = \rho W_j x_{j-1}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $j$ indicates the depth of a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, neural network is a way to combat the curse of dimensionality. In
the paper, Mallat formalizes this process using linearization of hierarchical
symmetry, space contraction and sparse separation. In short, it is done by
defining a new variable $\Phi(x)$, where $\Phi$ is a &lt;em&gt;contractive&lt;/em&gt; operator
that reduces the range of variations of $x$, while still &lt;em&gt;separating&lt;/em&gt; different
values of $f: \Phi(x) \not= \Phi(x’)$ if $f(x) \not= f(x’)$. $\Phi$ should have
the properties to &lt;strong&gt;linearize hierarchical symmetries, does space contraction and
achieve sparse separation&lt;/strong&gt; to keep classification margin (value margin for
regression). $\Phi$ is called the new representation of $x$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linearization-of-symmetries&quot;&gt;Linearization of symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural network finds equivalence classes $\Phi(x)$ that linearize
$f$. $\Phi(x)$ is built by collapsing complex symmetry groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linearization&quot;&gt;Linearization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, linearization means to find a representation $\Phi$ that $f$ on
$x \in \Omega$, where the domain $\Omega$ is a high dimensional open set, which
could be $L^2(R^n)$ or $R^d$, could be approximated by a linear combination&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar{f} = \sum_i\Phi_i(x)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of linearization is to find important yet highly complex basis vector
that linearly contributes to $f$, so $f$ is a linear projection of
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi_i(x)&lt;/script&gt;. An example would be the word vector, like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;actor - man + woman =
actress&lt;/code&gt;. Similar phenomenon is observed in images as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it also means $\Phi(x)$ absorbs in the variability that is
not related to $f$. An example could be translation variability, which is
absorbed by subsampling in NN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficulty for me to understand what does Mallat mean by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``We can then optimize a low-dimensional linear projection along directions where
$f$ is constant.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is the meaning I have guessed. In summary, if $\Phi$ is fixed, the
optimization works on the linear projection’s weight. ``$f$ is constant’’ means
after the change of variable, the variability in the original space $\Omega$
has been absorbed, so a variability in the direction that does not change
$\Phi$ does not change $f$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;space-collapse&quot;&gt;Space collapse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to find $\Phi$ that linearizes $f$, which is to find $\Phi$ that
collapses the directions that $f$ remains constant. Mallat formalizes this
``collapse’’ in term of group theory, or more particularly the group of
transformations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word collapse is my own creation, which tries to summarize the key point of
building invariant representation $\Phi$ utilizing groups of
symmetry. It corresponds to the absorbing of variability in previous
section. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi_i(x)&lt;/script&gt; represents an equivalence class (could be the orbit of
the group, more on this later) of $x$. Collapse is the process of combining
those classes together to form an equivalence class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formally, if $f$ is invariant to an operator $g$ that preserves the value of
$f$, which is to say $f(gx) = f(x)$, we can safely incorporate $g$ in $\Phi(x)$
(putting $gx$ in an equivalence class), so any transformation $g$ on $x$, aka
$gx$, does not change $\Phi(x)$, consequently it does not change $f$. Acting as
an equivalence class, they contribute to the linearization of $f$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example could be the translation group as an example, $f(gx) = f(x - u)$,
where $u \in \Omega$, representing the displacement of the translation. $f$’s
value does not change by translation, so by averaging (subsampling) spatially,
a direction that $f$ remains constant is collapsed out. This direction is part
of a equivalence class formed by collapsing out the translation group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By pinpointing those equivalence classes $\Phi(x)$, linearization is achieved
by doing linearly projection on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-details&quot;&gt;More details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high level plan stops here. Those above two are the main components making
up the framework of NN. Now we fill in the details, aka sparse separation,
space contraction, separation of scales and complex interaction among
multi-scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-functional-form-of-phi&quot;&gt;The functional form of $\Phi$&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$\Phi$ is handcrafted basis when the time of dictionary learning or deep
learning has not come. It is a vector that captures important (in any criteria
matters for the problem at hand) features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contraction-for-sparsity&quot;&gt;Contraction for sparsity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some general criteria for basis $\Phi$, one of which may require them
be sparse. A sparse signal brings to better linear separation. Or in other
word, factors of variation are better disentangled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fixed basis vectors, such as wavelets in scattering network they are
defined to separate scale and frequency. Thus for signals that only contains a
few of those, the wavelet coefficients would be rather sparse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an adaptive basis vector, to promote sparsity, Mallat puts forward the
concept of space contraction, which is achieved through the non-linear
activation function, a modulus or a ReLU. It explicitly contract the volume of
the space to achieve a sparse representation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of fixed basis like wavelet, if the representation is already
sparse, non-linear activation won’t reduce the volume too much since most of
the dimensions are already zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diffeomorphism-calls-for-multi-scale-separation&quot;&gt;Diffeomorphism calls for multi-scale separation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diffeomorphism can also be modeled a group symmetry. Diffeomorphism could be
factorized as a translation and a scaling effects. So to linearize
diffeomorphism, a multi-scale basis to separate the scaling effects are needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;multi-scale-interaction&quot;&gt;Multi-scale interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not enough to only separate signal using basis vectors, but also to model
their interactions. This justifies a deep architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;combining-all-the-above-together&quot;&gt;Combining all the above together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we could map each symbol in the following to their functional roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;x_j = \rho W_j x_{j-1}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each row of $W$ is the basis vector; $\rho$ is the contraction operator to
promote sparsity; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_j = ... x_{j-1}&lt;/script&gt; is the recursive form that takes cares
multi-scale separation and interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_{j-1}x_{j-1}&lt;/script&gt; linearizes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_j x_j&lt;/script&gt;. If we adding
pooling in, it corresponds to collapsing the direction where $f$ remains
constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recast-in-term-of-differential-geometry&quot;&gt;Recast in term of differential geometry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mallat use the formalism in differential geometry to succinctly define the
hierarchically built $\Phi$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mallat, the power of Neural Network is it is able learn such a
representation that linearize hierarchical symmetry groups, which is formalized
using fibres of hierarchical symmetry groups. Nonlinear contraction reduces the
variability of each fibre, so removing the variability that is not directly
related to currently sample being processed. Fibres of current layer are
transported to fibres of next layers, which are fibres of large
groups. Cascadingly applying the parallel transport on a sample, we obtain
multi-scale support vectors that are sparse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is hard to map these math names to the operational name of conv
net. Here is my best guess up to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each channel of a conv filter is a part of the orbits.
The equivalence class is the cross-channel sum of orbits of filters. The index
$P_j$ is the indices of orbits, which could be understood as the spatial
indices (orbits of translation group) and channel indices (orbits of those
groups, such as rotation groups). Since we have done a summation, how each 2D
filter corresponds to each part of the orbit does not matter, thus we get an
equivalence class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each equivalence class is called a fibre, which is just the fancy in
differential geometry to call an operator. In this case, the fibre is just the
cascadingly built operator $ρW_j$ mentioned at the beginning section. $ρW_j$
computes an approximate mapping from fibre of layer $j-1$ to $j$, which is
called a parallel transport in $P_j$.
A parallel transport is defined by a group $G_j$ of symmetries acting on the
index set $P_j$ of a layer $x_j$.
It is called an approximate mapping because fibre is supposed to be an
equivalence class of orbits of $x_{j-1}$, and the transport be mapping from
those equivalence class. however $pW_j$ starts from $x_{j-1}$, not
equivalence classes of orbits of $x_{j-1}$. So it is assumed to be approximated
by applying $g$ to $x_j$, we get $\bar{g}$ on $x_{j-1}$. Again implicitly
$x_{j}$ will be unrolled to the equivalence class of orbit of this layer,
which is a larger groups which is semidirect products of groups of layer $j-1$,
and groups (corresponding to channels in layer $j$) of layer $j$. The
approximation only makes sense by corresponding each channel of a filter to be
a part of a orbit of $g$, as in the previous paragraph. The channel of filters
are the groups of layer $j-1$, while the number of filters (output channel
number in most convnet implementations) is the groups of the layer
$j$. Assuming each filter channel corresponds to a part of the
orbit, $g.x_{j} = g.[\rho W_j x_{j-1}] \approx \rho W_j[\bar{g}.x_{j-1}]$
in the paper makes sense, since the summation cross channel would absorb $g$ in
$W_{j}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the convolution is called convolutions along the fibres. Implicitly, $\rho
W_j$ expands $x_{j-1}$ to its orbits, then computes equivalence classes of
orbits of $x_{j}$ by cross-channelly adding the result of applying filters on
those orbits. If in this sense, $x_{j-1}$ is indeed an equivalence class of
orbits. I guess the approximation means that this is just an assumption, since
no constrains are enforced to make sure channels of a filter are orbits of
$x_{j-1}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model, network filters are guiding nonlinear contractions, to reduce the
data variability in directions of local symmetries. The classification margin
can be controlled by sparse separations along network fibres&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each fibre is complex basis vector. Sparsity ensures separateness. Mallat
introduces the concept of multi-scale support vector, explained in the
following. To avoid further contracting their distance, they can be separated
along different fibres indexed by $b$. The separation is achieved by filters
$w_{j,h.b}$, which transform $x_{j−1}$ and $x’_{j−1}$ into $x_{j}(g, h,
b)$and $x’_{j}(g, h, b)$ having sparse supports on different fibres $b$. The
next contraction $ρW_{j+1}$ reduces distances along fibres indexed by $(g, h)
\in G_j$,but not across $b \in B_j$,which preserves distances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 10:41:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/08/29/key-points-of-understanding-deep-conv-net/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/08/29/key-points-of-understanding-deep-conv-net/</guid>
        
        
        <category>CNN</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An idea to gather people's stories</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In post-religion world, the God has stepped down, even humanism. People start to
look for icons that is personal yet inspirational, who could set an example for
their life. The idea of this project is to collect the people who may a
tech-utopian, aka the people who believe by making progress in technology, and
ease the dissemination of knowledge and information, eventually, the power could
be brought to the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Shuttleworth&quot;&gt;Mark_Shuttleworth&lt;/a&gt;, the funder
of Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 09:35:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/08/27/a-idea-to-gather-peoples-stories/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/08/27/a-idea-to-gather-peoples-stories/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[Repost] Explosion of the Space Shuttle Challenger Address to the Nation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Accidentially heared the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/SBOVkptjJhE?t=3959&quot;&gt;speech&lt;/a&gt; given by
Reagan to the nation after Challenger crashed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an excerpt. Full transcript is after that. The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://history.nasa.gov/reagan12886.html&quot;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt; is from NASA website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;excerpts&quot;&gt;Excerpts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve grown used to wonders in this century. It’s hard to dazzle us. But for 25
years the United States space program has been doing just that. We’ve grown
used to the idea of space, and perhaps we forget that we’ve only just
begun. We’re still pioneers. They, the members of the Challenger crew, were
pioneers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it is hard to understand, but sometimes painful things like this
happen. It’s all part of the process of exploration and discovery. It’s all
part of taking a chance and expanding man’s horizons. &lt;strong&gt;The future doesn’t belong
to the fainthearted; it belongs to the brave&lt;/strong&gt;. The Challenger crew was pulling
us into the future, and we’ll continue to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a coincidence today. On this day 390 years ago, the great explorer Sir
Francis Drake died aboard ship off the coast of Panama. &lt;strong&gt;In his lifetime the
great frontiers were the oceans, and an historian later said, “He lived by the
sea, died on it, and was buried in it.”&lt;/strong&gt; Well, today we can say of the
Challenger crew: Their dedication was, like Drake’s, complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crew of the space shuttle Challenger honored us by the manner in which they
lived their lives. &lt;strong&gt;We will never forget them, nor the last time we saw them,
this morning, as they prepared for their journey and waved goodbye and “slipped
the surly bonds of earth” to “touch the face of God.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-speech&quot;&gt;Full Speech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, I’d planned to speak to you tonight to report on the
state of the Union, but the events of earlier today have led me to change those
plans. Today is a day for mourning and remembering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nancy and I are pained to the core by the tragedy of the shuttle Challenger. We
know we share this pain with all of the people of our country. This is truly a
national loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nineteen years ago, almost to the day, we lost three astronauts in a terrible
accident on the ground. But we’ve never lost an astronaut in flight; we’ve
never had a tragedy like this. And perhaps we’ve forgotten the courage it took
for the crew of the shuttle; but they, the Challenger Seven, were aware of the
dangers, but overcame them and did their jobs brilliantly. We mourn seven
heroes: Michael Smith, Dick Scobee, Judith Resnik, Ronald McNair, Ellison
Onizuka, Gregory Jarvis, and Christa McAuliffe. We mourn their loss as a nation
together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the families of the seven, we cannot bear, as you do, the full impact of
this tragedy. But we feel the loss, and we’re thinking about you so very
much. Your loved ones were daring and brave, and they had that special grace,
that special spirit that says, “Give me a challenge and I’ll meet it with joy.”
They had a hunger to explore the universe and discover its truths. They wished
to serve, and they did. They served all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve grown used to wonders in this century. It’s hard to dazzle us. But for 25
years the United States space program has been doing just that. We’ve grown
used to the idea of space, and perhaps we forget that we’ve only just
begun. We’re still pioneers. They, the members of the Challenger crew, were
pioneers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I want to say something to the schoolchildren of America who were watching
the live coverage of the shuttle’s takeoff. I know it is hard to understand,
but sometimes painful things like this happen. It’s all part of the process of
exploration and discovery. It’s all part of taking a chance and expanding man’s
horizons. The future doesn’t belong to the fainthearted; it belongs to the
brave. The Challenger crew was pulling us into the future, and we’ll continue
to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had great faith in and respect for our space program, and what
happened today does nothing to diminish it. We don’t hide our space program. We
don’t keep secrets and cover things up. We do it all up front and in
public. That’s the way freedom is, and we wouldn’t change it for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll continue our quest in space. There will be more shuttle flights and more
shuttle crews and, yes, more volunteers, more civilians, more teachers in
space. Nothing ends here; our hopes and our journeys continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to add that I wish I could talk to every man and woman who works for
NASA or who worked on this mission and tell them: “Your dedication and
professionalism have moved and impressed us for decades. And we know of your
anguish. We share it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a coincidence today. On this day 390 years ago, the great explorer Sir
Francis Drake died aboard ship off the coast of Panama. In his lifetime the
great frontiers were the oceans, and an historian later said, “He lived by the
sea, died on it, and was buried in it.” Well, today we can say of the
Challenger crew: Their dedication was, like Drake’s, complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crew of the space shuttle Challenger honored us by the manner in which they
lived their lives. We will never forget them, nor the last time we saw them,
this morning, as they prepared for their journey and waved goodbye and “slipped
the surly bonds of earth” to “touch the face of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 08:42:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/07/30/repost-explosion-of-the-space-shuttle-challenger-address-to-the-nation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/07/30/repost-explosion-of-the-space-shuttle-challenger-address-to-the-nation/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Repost</category>
        
        <category>Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Note On Representation of Operator</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A note to remind me of some intuition ruminated. Do not have the time to write
down detailed proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about spectral theorem of matrix, adjoint operator, SVD and tensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spectral-theorem&quot;&gt;Spectral Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The representation theory of linear functional is essentially one dimension
version of group representation theory. The $w$ in the inner product $\langle
x, w \rangle$ representation of functional $f(x)$ is essentially the normal of
the hyperplane, which is the functional’s representation in the dual space. The
process of applying $f$ on $x$ is a process of projection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a general operator $T: X \rightarrow Y$, whose representation is denoted
$A$, if the bases of the $X, Y$ are orthogonal, the adjoint operator $T^{*}$ of
$T$’s representation is $A^{T}$(on the condition that bases of $X, Y$ is chosen
to be orthogonal). The process of applying $T$ on $x$ is a process of first
doing multiple projection, then sum those projection together. The fact that
adjoint operator has the spectral theorem is just because in certain bases,
when we are applying the multiple projection, we are not projecting at all, but
just scale along the hyperplane. The process of changing bases, applying
scaling, then changing bases back written in form of matrix multiplication is
$M^{-1}\Lambda M$, which is the spectral decomposition of representation of $T$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adjoint-operator-is-just-the-transpose&quot;&gt;Adjoint Operator is Just the Transpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projection perspective also explains why $T^{*} = A^{T}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let $Ax = y$. Each $x_i$ contributes to $y_i$ linearly. So just like a linear
equation has a unique solution as long as $A$ is of full rank, there must be a
one-to-one relationship between $T$ and $T^{*}$, which is formalized using
representation theory of functional again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;svd&quot;&gt;SVD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVD just factorizes the multi-projection into a rotation matrix and a scaling
matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tensor&quot;&gt;Tensor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tensor is a generalized operator that handles multi-linearity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 17:02:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/05/01/note-on-representation-of-operator/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/05/01/note-on-representation-of-operator/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Math</category>
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Quick Survey on Distributed Log Processing: Unison and Logstash</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having multiple machines to train neural networks, I was trying to think how
could I automatically gather all the training logs, so I could analyze them in
one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a survey on technologies available. The ones that I found are: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/code&gt; seems to be the optimal solution, though may be a little
an overkill. However, I settled to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; in the end. The rationale
behind this is I have to get around many VPNs. The VPNs I used, or maybe most
VPNs setups, won’t let the machines in LAN of the VPN network ping back to the
machine that uses VPN to connect. It may just not come from a security reason,
though it could be; it may just because it is not necessary to set up the route
table to the IP addresses allocated to the connecting machine. So in this case,
the log cannot be sent back to the connecting machine, as the way &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/code&gt;
does. A solution is needed to initialize the centralization from the connect
machine site. So &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/code&gt; is ruled out, and I settled with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a quick note on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; works, which took me a while to
figure out. For an practical introduction to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Logstash&lt;/code&gt;, see the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slashroot.in/logstash-tutorial-linux-central-logging-server&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introductory-note&quot;&gt;Introductory Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/unison/download/releases/stable/unison-manual.html#basics&quot;&gt;Unison&lt;/a&gt;
is a file-synchronization tool for Unix and Windows. It allows two replicas of
a collection of files and directories to be stored on different hosts (or
different disks on the same host), modified separately, and then brought up to
date by propagating the changes in each replica to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Unison&lt;/code&gt; supports transmission via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;socket&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rsh&lt;/code&gt;. Each of
those protocols has its own setups, except for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; protocol — it
synchronizes files within the single machine. For instance, to use ssh, the two
machines to be able to ssh to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; is used is similar with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scp&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cp&lt;/code&gt; in the sense that they
are all a command line source destination style. An example would be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unison -testserver /tmp/ ssh://192.168.72.1//tmp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of a source or destination is
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[protocol:]//[user@][host][:port][/path]&lt;/code&gt;. The one with no host name is
supposed to your local machine. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-testserver&lt;/code&gt; option above is used to test
whether the network between the local machine and the remote machine is
reachable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid typing the addresses each time, since &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; is about syncing, not
copying, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; offers a thing called profile. The command above, without the
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-testserver&lt;/code&gt; option, converts to a profile is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;root = /home/use1/work/sync/
root = ssh://192.168.72.1//home/user1/work/sync
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more sophisticated profiles, see the office
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/unison/download/releases/stable/unison-manual.html#profile&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question following is where do we store profiles?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; will store all its logistics files under the folder pointed by
environment variable &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;UNISON&lt;/code&gt;, which if not specified, is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.unison&lt;/code&gt; under the
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt; folder. A profile file us named in the format of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.prf&lt;/code&gt;. Suppose the
above profile is saved as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;test.prf&lt;/code&gt;. To use that profile, type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unison &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I spent some time to figure out is how it actually sync between
machines, so it won’t mess up my data. Roughly, it adds another layer of logic
above &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt;, which is suggested from the document&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Transfers are optimised using a version of the rsync protocol, making it ideal
for slower links. Unison has a clear and precise specification, and is
resilient to failure due to its careful handling of the replicas and its
private structures.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic is added I think is the way to get some fingerprints of the files, so
it knows which files is updated when syncing, and only sync those are really updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Touching a file without changing its contents should never affect whether or
not Unison does an update. (When running with the fastcheck preference set to
true—the default on Unix systems—Unison uses file modtimes for a quick first
pass to tell which files have definitely not changed; then, for each file that
might have changed, it computes a fingerprint of the file's contents and
compares it against the last-synchronized contents. Also, the -times option
allows you to synchronize file times, but it does not cause identical files to
be changed; Unison will only modify the file times.)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So calling unison at either end will sync the files right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sync-between-more-than-machines&quot;&gt;Sync Between More than Machines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The built-in doc of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt;, which is available via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison -doc tutorial&lt;/code&gt;,
has a section discussing how &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unison&lt;/code&gt; could be used to sync between more than
machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Unison to Synchronize More Than Two Machines&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Unison is designed for synchronizing pairs of replicas. However, it is
possible to use it to keep larger groups of machines in sync by
performing multiple pairwise synchronizations.

If you need to do this, the most reliable way to set things up is to
organize the machines into a “star topology,” with one machine
designated as the “hub” and the rest as “spokes,” and with each spoke
machine synchronizing only with the hub. The big advantage of the star
topology is that it eliminates the possibility of confusing “spurious
conflicts” arising from the fact that a separate archive is maintained
by Unison for every pair of hosts that it synchronizes.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not get what does it mean in the first reading. After that, I guess the
method it suggests is to establish a pair-wise sync among machines with certain
topology, which is to say: one needs to set up multiple profiles; each profile
sync between two machines; those machines form a topology so there is a hub
that will have a centralized sync state among all machines if you sync in the
right order.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 10:53:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/03/15/a-quick-survey-on-log-processing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/03/15/a-quick-survey-on-log-processing/</guid>
        
        
        <category>CS</category>
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
        <category>Linux</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Note on Installing Ubuntu on Newer Machines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the note supposed to note something peculiar things I met during
setting up Ubuntu on a newer machine, which is to say, with UEFI replacing
BIOS, GPT replacing MBR, Display Port and HDMI replacing VGA and DVI, and with
several GPUs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to time reason, I fell back to my old way of installing Ubuntu, and have
not figured out what is the right way to install the newer machine mentioned
above, but the note is to note down possible guess, and the things have been
figured out, so I may have a thread to follow next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I entered what was called BIOS of the machine, which is called
UEFI(Unified Extensible Firmware Interface), I was amazed that it was an almost
desktop GUI. The official lab machine of mine has a similar firmware, but since
I was not supposed to have access to it, I did not play with it much. I think
my most recent laptop should have also used UEFI, but I did not have any memory
what it is like, I guess I did not need to change things so I did not enter it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gpu-control-from-boot-to-os&quot;&gt;GPU Control From Boot to OS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I tried to figure out is how a GPU could be installed
properly. In other words, how could a GPU inserted in a socket could be
detected by the motherboard, then OS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally a PC motherboard has an integrated card, and an optional discrete
graphical unit could be installed GPU card through PCIE sockets. There is a
switch in the UEFI to tell the motherboard where to look for a graphical
unit. Also, even if the GPU is not powered up, I could have a hint on the
monitor to tell me to what happened. So I think a GPU has a basic function unit
that offers motherboard basic graphical function so it could be used till the
machine boots into an OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first problem I have met is there was no output when I connect DVI adapter
of the monitor to a TITAN Black that was inserted in the latter socket of the
motherboard, and could only get output when I connect the adapter to the GPU
inserted in the first PCIE socket. The GPU is not a TITAN Black but a 760.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two guesses why this situations happen. The first is UEFI only detect
GPU at the first PCIE socket and ignores all the remaining. This is reasonable
since no one is supposed to use multiple GPUs during boot time. But it seems I
have tried put a TITAN Black at the first socket, though I cannot clearly
remember it. So another guess is my current UEFI does not support TITAN at boot
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the UEFI transfer the control to OS, the drivers in UEFI should not
function anymore. So drivers need to be installed in the OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open source NVIDIA card driver, Nouveau, will be installed when installing
Ubuntu. I thought only when a NVIDIA GPU is physically inserted, its open
source driver would be installed. However, it seems the open source driver will
be installed even without a card. Maybe it is because in this case, a GPU card
could be used right after installation without re-installing kernel modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nouveau has to be removed if I want to install the newest driver from NVIDIA
through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file, otherwise they would conflict. To do this, a file
needs to be added to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/etc/modprobe.d/&lt;/code&gt; with the following contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# generated by nvidia-installer
blacklist nouveau
options nouveau modeset=0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is actually generated by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file. I think it tells kernel not to
load nouveau module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then regenerate your kernel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;update-initramfs -u
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To completely wipe out &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nouveau&lt;/code&gt; — though I think even without doing it, it
would work, run the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get remove xserver-xorg-video-nouveau
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file, one needs to log into a text console. A way I could find
that is commonly suggested on the web is to switch to one virtual terminal by
`Ctrl+Alt+F1’, then stop the X service&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo stop lightdm   or
sudo lightdm stop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did not work for me. So I need to reboot into text mode by editing
grub. More concretely, when the grub menu pops up, press &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; on the item, and
find &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;splash quiet&lt;/code&gt;, and change it to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;text&lt;/code&gt;, then press &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;F10&lt;/code&gt; to boot using
current edited entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing before running the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file will build GPU
driver to kernel, but only once. So if your OS gets upgraded, you won’t be able
to log in desktop again. To work get around this, we need to install &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dkms&lt;/code&gt;, so
each time the kernel gets upgraded, all modules already built will be
automatically built again into the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install dkms
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All are settled, just run the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file to install the driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see what modules has been managed by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dkms&lt;/code&gt;, use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dkms status&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing that tricked me up is to tell motherboard to use discrete
graphical unit after the driver has been installed. Otherwise, I could still
make it till the GUI login page, but after I have input my password, the screen
just flash a little, and ask me to log in again. I guess the problem is
since motherboard is configured to use integrated graphical unit, so the
discrete one is actually inactive, when &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xorg.conf' tells &lt;/code&gt;X11` to use the
discrete graphical unit, nothing is there. The solution is just to fall back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have some guess on how &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X11&lt;/code&gt; make use of multiple GPUs. I have two
versions of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xorg.conf&lt;/code&gt;, one from my official lab machine, and one from the one
I am setting up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Section &quot;Device&quot;
    Identifier     &quot;Device0&quot;
    Driver         &quot;nvidia&quot;
    VendorName     &quot;NVIDIA Corporation&quot;
    BoardName      &quot;GeForce GTX TITAN Black&quot;
EndSection

Section &quot;Device&quot;
    Identifier     &quot;Device1&quot;
    Driver         &quot;nvidia&quot;
    VendorName     &quot;NVIDIA Corporation&quot;
    BoardName      &quot;GeForce GTX TITAN Black&quot;
    BusID          &quot;PCI:1:0:0&quot;
    Screen          1
EndSection
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other one is just&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Section &quot;Device&quot;
    Identifier     &quot;Device0&quot;
    Driver         &quot;nvidia&quot;
    VendorName     &quot;NVIDIA Corporation&quot;
EndSection
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is generated by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nvidia-settings', the second one is generated by
&lt;/code&gt;*run` file. I have three TITAN Black installed on the motherboard with the
second configuration file, and they are all functional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guess now is if no bus id is specified in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xorg.conf&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X11&lt;/code&gt; could pick any
one, and prefer to the one with lowest PCI id or GPU id.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side note. To get the bus id of a card, use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lspci&lt;/code&gt;, which output corresponds
to GPU is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;01:00.0 VGA compatible controller: NVIDIA Corporation GK110B [GeForce GTX TITAN Black] (rev a1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;01:00.0&lt;/code&gt; is the bus id, though I am still now know why the period becomes a colon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;note-on-cuda&quot;&gt;Note On CUDA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all those efforts to install NVIDIA driver through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*run&lt;/code&gt; file, I found
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cuda&lt;/code&gt; installation(using the network deb provided by NVIDIA) just overrided
the driver I have just installed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure whether dkms will be automatically installed, or nouveau be
automatically blacklisted, though the installation of cuda does not mention it,
which is to mean they probably will take care of this. If this is so the
installation of NVIDIA driver and CUDA will be much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I notice the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xorg.conf&lt;/code&gt; is not changed after the ``new’’ driver being
installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bios-mode-or-uefi-mode-ubuntu&quot;&gt;BIOS mode or UEFI mode Ubuntu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last set of note is about installing Ubuntu in BIOS mode or UEFI mode,
which corresponds to using MBR or GPT partition table, and may be some other
difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time when choosing the boot media, even if your USB only has one Ubuntu
on it, the boot menu would show up as entries, one for normal BIOS mode
ubuntu(which is just named Ubuntu), one for UEFI mode(which has a UEFI in the
name). I have not tried the second one. The UEFI is a pretty new thing to me,
since the last time I learned something about it, UEFI is still in its
infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If UEFI is chosen, the partition table of the hard disk where the boot loader
would be installed must be GPT, which is written in the new standard. The boot
loader of MBR and GPT are different(obviously). For GPT, an explicitly
formatted and allocated partition seems to be needed(not verified). As for MBR,
as everyone knows, the space for the boot loader will always be left out. Also,
to boot from a GPT partitioned disk, a boot flag need to be marked on the disk,
otherwise, OS won’t boot. There are still many other difference I have not
figured out yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linuxsecrets.com/blog/15questions-troubleshooting/2015/09/10/1651-how-to-remove-nouveau-and-install-nvidia-drivers&quot;&gt;How to Remove Nouveau and Install Nvidia Drivers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 13:48:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/note-on-installing-ubuntu-on-newer-machines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/03/08/note-on-installing-ubuntu-on-newer-machines/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Linux</category>
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
        <category>CS</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>VLC下使用中文字幕</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;记如何在VLC下使用中文字幕。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;默认状态下，VLC会遇到两个问题，一是解码的codecs所用不对，而是用于显示字体的渲染
器(render)所用字体不对。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第一个问题的解决办法一是更改VLC所用的codecs；二是修改文件的codecs为utf-8。第一
种方法在&lt;a href=&quot;http://bbs.feng.com/read-htm-tid-344593.html&quot;&gt;这里&lt;/a&gt;有介绍。第二种方法
我发现Vim可以完美完成，特此记之。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;用Vim打开字幕文件，然后使用如下命令：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;:set fileencoding=utf-8
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;保存，退出。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;第二个问题的解决也来自之上的
&lt;a href=&quot;http://bbs.feng.com/read-htm-tid-344593.html&quot;&gt;链接&lt;/a&gt;。为防止链接失效，特此重述
方法：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;打开VLC的&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferences&lt;/code&gt;窗口（&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ctrl+P&lt;/code&gt;），点击右下角的&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;all&lt;/code&gt;，在左边的索引中依次选择
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Video -&amp;gt; Subtitles/OSD -&amp;gt; Text renderer&lt;/code&gt;，右边的设置区第一项为&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Font&lt;/code&gt;，点击&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Browse&lt;/code&gt;按
钮选择一项中文字体，如&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;WenQuanYi Micro Hei&lt;/code&gt;。更改完成之后需要重启VLC。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 22:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/vlcxia-shi-yong-zhong-wen-zi-mu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2016/02/16/vlcxia-shi-yong-zhong-wen-zi-mu/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
        <category>Linux</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
