<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Presentation | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/presentation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-02T15:02:39+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to do presentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/09/how-to-do-presentation/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T21:33:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/09/how-to-do-presentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just got some illuminating advice about doing presentation. They come from the
teaching team of ME310 course of Stanford University. Share it here.</p>

<p>Will provide more after as I learn more.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Virtually all photos are ambiguous on first sight by persons not previously
 involved with your project.  THEREFORE, all photos are made more informative
 when annotated with accents, labels, call-outs, whatever.  This also applies to sketches and CAD images.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Avoid complex (multi-part) images.  Focus on one-message per slide.  This often translates to one
graphic, table, diagram, or photo per slide.  If it is worth showing, it is worth making it
intelligible with a minimum of time and attention by the audience. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>SHOW ME, don’t tell me.  Use images rather than words.  Follow the ancient dictum to show, not tell.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Walk the audience through the flow of the diagram, image, visualization if the image is a relatively 
complex (more than 3 elements).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Prioritize, what are the 1-3 most important things you want the audience to remember. 
Craft your narrative  around these KEY points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Simplify/Clarify, make each slide as clear, unambiguous and memorable as possible.
Delete uninformative graphics, backgrounds, and logos.  Make everything READABLE
from anywhere in the audience given the presentation technology (that you have tested).</p>
  </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
