<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: LaTeX | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/latex/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-16T16:38:49+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Note on texlive from Ubuntu Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/note-on-texlive-from-ubuntu-source/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-02T21:49:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/note-on-texlive-from-ubuntu-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some note on the installing LaTeX packages from network.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>It is very convenient to install packages using <code>tlmgr</code>. However, sometimes
the mirror you are trying to connect would be extremely slow, which makes it
feel like tlmgr has stuck.</p>

<p>If you have not been deal with texlive installation for a long time, like me
today, the first thoughts stuck me is that there is something wrong with
texlive installation given that I was doing a fresh installation on a new
laptop I did not familiar. Only after about a hour’s debugging, the idea that
maybe it is the network issue struck me.</p>

<p>Here I want to note down some points about how tlmgr choose its mirror servers,
so I won’t be figuring out the same problem next time.</p>

<p>By default, <code>tlmgr</code>’s default repository url is a multiplexor, which will
choose a mirror in the closest network proximity to your location. See the
right pane of this <a href="ctan.org/mirrors">page</a>.</p>

<p>To set such behavior of <code>tlmgr</code>, the command is like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
tlmgr option repository ctan
</code></p>

<p>where <code>ctan</code> is the nickname for tlmgr for the multiplexor mirror.</p>

<p>Today the multiplexor gave me a server that is not working my LAN
network. Luckily that I get a workable mirror from my PC and use that to solve
the network problem.</p>

<p>The url of a mirror is like this:
<code>http://ftp.yzu.edu.tw/CTAN/systems/texlive/tlnet</code>. The example here is the
mirror that works for me this time.</p>

<p><em>NOTE FOR ME</em>:</p>

<p>I have set this mirror as default for my laptop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Math Equations on Octopress 2.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/07/07/writing-math-equations-on-octopress-2-dot-0/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-07T16:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/07/07/writing-math-equations-on-octopress-2-dot-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am trying to be a researcher in Artificial Intelligence, with current focus on
Machine Learning. Thus I wrote a number of math. However, at the first time I
set up octopress, I did not find anything that could help me set up relevant
engine to render math on octopress. Now I have found it! There are a great
amount of notes needed organizing and sorting…</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I followed the instruction <a href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/2012/03/10/writing-math-equations-on-octopress/">here</a>
to set up MathJax for octopress. Why would I write another one tutorial?</p>

<p>Basical steps are almost the same. However, I guess the author are still using
octopress 1.0 that time. On octopress 2.0, it provides additional place to let
user customize octopress without messing with the code of octopress. For
octopress, the step in original post to add script of MathJax, a.k.a, adding the
following snippet in <code>source/_layouts/default.html</code> could to changed to
<code>source/_includes/custom/head.html</code>.</p>

<p><code>html
&lt;!-- mathjax config similar to math.stackexchange --&gt;
&lt;script type="text/x-mathjax-config"&gt;
MathJax.Hub.Config({
  jax: ["input/TeX", "output/HTML-CSS"],
  tex2jax: {
    inlineMath: [ ['$', '$'] ],
    displayMath: [ ['$$', '$$']],
    processEscapes: true,
    skipTags: ['script', 'noscript', 'style', 'textarea', 'pre', 'code']
  },
  messageStyle: "none",
  "HTML-CSS": { preferredFont: "TeX", availableFonts: ["STIX","TeX"] }
});
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS_HTML" type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;/script
</code></p>

<p>In octopress 2.0, most of cutomization the user want to make can be made just by
changing files under <code>source/_includes/custom/</code>.</p>

<p>Other steps could stay unchanged.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Equipped with Both Word and LaTeX]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/27/equipped-with-both-word-and-latex/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T10:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/27/equipped-with-both-word-and-latex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is painful to type complex tables in LaTex. A better way is to integrate the
power between LateX and Word. This two posts deal with creating more firepower
by using Visio, Word along with LaTeX.</p>

<p><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/05/23/convert-word-tables-to-eps-for-inclusion-in-latex/">Convert Word tables to EPS for inclusion in LaTeX</a></p>

<p><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/09/04/exporting-visio-2003-illustrations-to-eps/">Exporting Visio 2003 illustrations to EPS</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bibtex entry types and fields description]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/18/bibtex-entry-types-and-fields-description/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-18T09:59:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/18/bibtex-entry-types-and-fields-description</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="entry-types">Entry Types</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>@article</strong>: Entry for an article from a journal or magazine.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, journal, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: volume, number, pages, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@book</strong>: Entry for a book with a definite publisher.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author or editor, title, publisher, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: volume or number, series, address, edition, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@booklet</strong>: Entry for a printed and bound work without the name of a publisher or
sponsoring organization.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: title.</li>
      <li>optional fields: author, howpublished, address, month, year, note.
<!-- more --></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@conference</strong>: Is the same as * @inproceedings below.</li>
  <li><strong>@inbook</strong>: Entry for a part (chapter, section, certain pages) of a book.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author or editor, title, chapter and/or pages, publisher,
year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: volume or number, series, type, address, edition, month,
note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@incollection</strong>: Entry for part of a book that has its own title.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, booktitle, publisher, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: editor, volume or number, series, type, chapter, pages,
address, edition, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@inproceedings</strong>: Entry for an article in conference proceedings.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, booktitle, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: editor, volume or number, series, pages, address, month,
organization, publisher, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@manual</strong>: Entry for technical documentation.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: title.</li>
      <li>optional fields: author, organization, address, edition, month, year,
note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@mastersthesis</strong>: Entry for a Master’s thesis.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, school, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: type, address, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@misc</strong>: Entry for a work that does not fit under any of the others.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: none.</li>
      <li>optional fields: author, title, howpublished, month, year, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@phdthesis</strong>: Entry for a PhD thesis.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, school, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: type, address, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@proceedings</strong>: Entry for conference proceedings.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: title, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: editor, volume or number, series, address, month,
organization, publisher, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@techreport</strong>: Entry for a report published by a school or other institution,
usually as part of a series.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, institution, year.</li>
      <li>optional fields: type, number, address, month, note.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>@unpublished</strong>: Entry for an unpublished work with an author and title.
    <ul>
      <li>required fields: author, title, note.</li>
      <li>optional fields: month, year.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-fields">The fields</h2>

<p>The fields that may be used within a bibliographic entry are listed below
together with their meanings. They are always given in the form:</p>

<p>field name = {field text}</p>

<p>or</p>

<p>field name = “field text”</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>address</strong>: The address of the publisher or other institution. For major
publishing houses, it is sufficient to give just the city. For smaller
publishers, giving the full address is recommended.</li>
  <li><strong>annote</strong>: An annotation that may be used by non-standard bibliography styles to
produce an annotated bibliography. The standard BIBTEX styles ignore it.</li>
  <li><strong>author</strong>: The name(s) of the author(s).</li>
  <li><strong>booktitle</strong> The title of a book when only part of it is being cited.</li>
  <li><strong>chapter</strong>: A chapter or section number.</li>
  <li><strong>crossref</strong>: The key of another entry in the database that shares many of the
same field entries.</li>
  <li><strong>edition</strong>: The edition of a book, usually written in full and capitalized, as
‘Second’. The standard styles will change it to lower case as necessary.</li>
  <li><strong>editor</strong>: The name(s) of the editor(s). If there is also an author field, then
this gives the editor of the book or collection in which the citation appears.</li>
  <li><strong>howpublished</strong>: States anything unusual about the method of publishing. Should
be capitalized. Example: ‘Privately published’.</li>
  <li><strong>institution</strong>: The name of the sponsoring institution for a technical report.</li>
  <li>journal The name of a journal or magazine. Abbreviations are provided for the
most common ones.</li>
  <li><strong>key</strong>: An addition for alphabetizing purposes when the author infor- mation is
missing. This is not the same as the key for identifying the entry to a \cite
command.</li>
  <li><strong>month</strong>: The month in which the work was published or, if unpublished, when it
was written. Abbreviations exist in the form of the first three letters of the
(English) names.</li>
  <li><strong>note</strong>: Any additional information that should be added. Capitalize the first
letter.</li>
  <li><strong>number</strong>: The number of a journal, magazine, technical report, or work in a
series. Journals are usually identified by volume and number; technical
reports are issued a number by the institution; books in series sometimes have
a number given to them.</li>
  <li><strong>organization</strong>: The sponsoring organization for a conference or a manual.</li>
  <li><strong>pages</strong>: A page number or a range of pages, in the form 32,41,58 or 87–101 or
68+. The last form indicates page 68 and following pages. A single hyphen
given for a range will be converted by the standard styles to the double
hyphen to produce a dash, as ‘87–101’.</li>
  <li><strong>publisher</strong>: The publisher’s name.</li>
  <li><strong>school</strong>: The name of the academic institution where a thesis was written.
series The name of a series or set of books. When citing a book from a series,
the title field gives the name of the book itself while the optional series
specifies the title of whole set.</li>
  <li><strong>title</strong>: The title of the work, obeying the capitalization rules listed in</li>
  <li><strong>type</strong>: The type of technical report, for example, ‘Research Note’.</li>
  <li><strong>url</strong>: The universal resource locator, or Internet address, for online documents;
this is not standard but supplied by more modern bibliography styles.</li>
  <li><strong>volume</strong>: The volume number of a journal or multi-volume book.</li>
  <li><strong>year</strong>: The year in which the work was published or, if unpublished, in which it
was written. It should normally consist of four numerals, such as 1993.</li>
</ul>

<p>Additional field names may be included, which BIBTEX will simply
ignore. For example, to add the abstract of an article in the database,</p>

<p>abstract = {text of an abstract}</p>

<p>This can be of use in other applications as well as for database manage-
ment.</p>

<p>from: Guide to LaTeX, fourth edition, Helmut Kopka and Patrick W.Daly</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LaTeX Note]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/latex-note/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T11:08:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/latex-note</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Notes about LaTeX.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="multiline-equations">Multiline Equations</h2>

<p>You can present equations with several lines, using the array statement. Inside
its declaration you must :</p>

<ul>
  <li>Define the number of columns</li>
  <li>Define column alignment</li>
  <li>Define column indentation</li>
  <li>Indicate column separator with &amp; symbol &amp;</li>
</ul>

<p>Example: {rcl} means: 3 columns with indentations respectively right, center and
left.</p>

<h3 id="multiline-equations-without-equation-number">Multiline Equations Without Equation Number</h3>

<p>To use it without equation number, use displaymath environment.</p>

<p><code>latex
\begin{displaymath}
	\begin{array}{rcl}
	z &amp; = &amp; a \\ f(x,y,z) &amp; = &amp; x + y + z
	\end{array}
\end{displaymath}
</code></p>

<h3 id="multiline-equations-with-equation-number">Multiline Equations with Equation Number</h3>

<p>If you want  equation number, use equation environment.</p>

<p>You have two choice, use eqnarray or change displaymath to equation.</p>

<p>eqnarray is a quick way to write three columns eqations, like this:</p>

<p><code>latex
\begin{eqnarray}
	z &amp; = &amp; a \\ f(x,y,z) &amp; = &amp; x + y + z
\end{eqnarray}
</code></p>

<p>If you want more customized feature, use equation instead:</p>

<p><code>latex
\begin{equation}
	\begin{array}{rcl}
	z &amp; = &amp; a \\ f(x,y,z) &amp; = &amp; x + y + z
	\end{array}
\end{equation}
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
