<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Teaching | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/teaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-30T11:46:55+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Teaching and Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/09/21/on-teaching-and-learning/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-21T20:37:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/09/21/on-teaching-and-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some notes on teaching and learning.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The way we teach reflects the way we learn and the way we communicate. Teaching
gives me another perspective on how may I could be taught or just, learn from
others. Such experience has led me a long way to realize my deficiency.</p>

<p>I attended a workshop on teaching today and want to note down something
learned. It is the first time I got systematical training on how to teaching,
which is equivalent to how to learn.</p>

<p>The following stuffs come from the handout in the workshop.</p>

<h3 id="seven-research-based-principles-for-smart-teaching">Seven Research-based Principles for Smart Teaching</h3>

<p>There are seven principles in teaching, which also means in learning.</p>

<ol>
  <li>prior knowledge</li>
  <li>structuring knowledge</li>
  <li>motivation</li>
  <li>self-awareness on the one’s situation</li>
  <li>synthesis of different parts of acquired knowledge </li>
  <li>feedback</li>
  <li>emotional feeling, social and intellectual climate</li>
</ol>

<p>This is a systematical summary of elements that involves in the learning
process. Prior knowledge is what you already have; structuring knowledge is how
you condense your knowledge and build inner connection between different
separate parts; motivation is power house behind all your efforts;
self-awareness is about a clear awareness of one’s current situation — what
one have known, what one do not know, what one know one do not know; synthesis
is where something new could happen; feedback is how people get to know their
mistakes, so they could fix them, and learn new things; emotional stability and
social support is very important for long term learning.</p>

<p>After some thinking, it seems that nothing is really new for me, but the
summary is helpful.</p>

<h3 id="on-motivation">On Motivation</h3>

<p>Another important part on teaching and learning discussed is what motivate
people to do better on tasks that need cognitive thinking.</p>

<p>I long have known only money is not enough. Today I got a very good summary:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pay people enough to take the issue of money off the table.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The factors that motivate to do great work is autonomy, mastery and
purpose. There should many materials online talking on this given this is a
research output from scientists.</p>

<h3 id="three-skills-on-communication">Three Skills On Communication</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Storytelling</li>
  <li>Contextualizing</li>
  <li>Sketching</li>
</ol>

<p>All those are kind of one thing. People learn from examples, so we need
storytelling; people learn from examples that they know the most, so we need
contextualize the examples with their experience; people learn bit by bit,
dynamically, so we need to present it bit by bit, like sketching a picture.</p>

<p>It is easier said that done. Practice is important.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
