<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Wavelet | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/wavelet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-03T16:34:53+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Progress Buffer for Big Picture Building]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/05/07/progress-buffer-for-big-picture-building/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-07T08:37:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/05/07/progress-buffer-for-big-picture-building</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think I will fully devote to a project from now on. To be able to back on the
work to build an overall big picture of perception problem of artificial
intelligence in the future, I try to summarize the progress here.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="wavelet">Wavelet</h2>

<h3 id="transition-from-fourier-to-wavelet">Transition from Fourier to Wavelet</h3>

<p>The learning of one dimensional Fourier transform part of Fourier transform is
finished. The key of transition from Fourier analysis to wavelet analysis in
transient signal analysis is learned, which will be described in the following:</p>

<p>Fourier transform is actually a scan over all frequency spectrum on the
signal. For a time-limited signal, or mathematically non-periodic signal, the
value of the signal outside the time-limited interval is zero not because it is
indeed zero in nature but we do not care about its value. So if we use all
spectrum of Fourier transform to get its new representation in frequency
domain, the coefficients whose period are far longer than the time span or far
shorter than the time span will be highly inaccurate — only when the integral
or inner product is taken a integer multiplication of period length, the
coefficients we get is accurate. So in windowed Fourier transform, the
frequency whose period is far longer than the window is synthesized using
different time notes of the signal while the one whose period is far shorter
than the window is synthesized by different high frequency in the same time
note.</p>

<p>Discrete Fourier transform is an approximate of continuous Fourier transform,
which is directly called Fourier transform in previous paragraph. The
approximate is made actual taking the time span of the time-limited signal as
such signal’s period. Similar approximation is also made in the frequency
domain. So we get a periodic frequency span. This is why we have to ensure the
sampling rate is high enough to guarantee that after the periodization of
frequency part, different periods do not overlap with each other.</p>

<p>So to overcome this problem is the key reason to introduce wavelet analysis,
whose bases’ time span are dynamically determined to suit the corresponding
frequency they want to decouple, or in another word, to detect.</p>

<h3 id="goals-next-step">Goals Next Step</h3>

<p>How exactly this idea is implemented thirty years ago should be further
investigated <strong>on the purpose of this research goal</strong>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How could Fourier and wavelet analysis bridges the gap between the physical
entity and things that may have semantic meaning?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What the sensors of human beings are receiving are actually just physical
signals — the different strength of illumination of light, different
amplitude and frequency of air vibration. The problem solved by scientists in
18th and 19th are most linear problem that deals with the nature instead of how
human deals with nature. The light and air pressure vibration are both
superposition of various basic building blocks of nature’s atom —
electromagnet wave and mechanical vibration wave. Frequency, amplitude and
phase of them are the first layer nature of them. For human beings, the learned
nature of them is actually detecting patterns. The gap between those two would
be very important to understand the perception problem of human race.</p>

<p>To address this gap, wavelet analysis and its high dimensional form could be a
promising direction. To know exactly where this direction could lead, the
following questions and guess should be addressed:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wavelet that does not use complex exponential directly may be understood as
a layer that stacked on the complex exponential, which is the frequency
nature of the signal – the atom of signal. This may be the reason why
theorem proving of wavelet I have encountered now all depends on Fourier
transform.</li>
  <li>How different kinds of wavelets are designed? One key here is that we want
the optimal time and frequency localization for one particular wavelet
basis. But there must be more in this. Some work have mentioned the
vanishing moment of wavelet. Those design may bring to some very deep
physics facts that is very illuminating.</li>
  <li>One dimensional analysis is actually the special case of higher dimensional
analysis. Everything is a vector in the real world. After getting
familiarity with one dimensional theory, the leap from one dimensional to
higher dimensional could lead to the direct intuition to the real world and
the solving of problem that involving the basic properties of higher
dimensional space, such as 2D and 3D rotation, scaling of signals.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="execution-plan">Execution Plan</h3>

<p>Fortunately, the survey about which books to read has just been made.</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Insight Into Wavelets, from Theory to Practice</em> is relatively detailed
enough and contains pertinent amount of practice. It seems to cover relevant
Math, such as function space, nested space, enough intuition and historical
development, the design of wavelet and enough examples. This book may be the
main thread to follow when I back to learn it again.</li>
  <li><em>Ten lectures on wavelets</em> is another candidate main thread to follow. Its
level of detail and conversation style will be further checked when I back to
learn it again.</li>
  <li><em>A Friendly Guide to Wavelets</em> should be used in complement with the first
book. This book is too contingent with examples and proof detail, but its
explanation on intuition is good.</li>
  <li><em>A First Course in Wavelets with Fourier Analysis</em> has not been investigated
much. Its try to deal with Fourier and wavelet at the time could make it
miserable, but referring to it from time to time may be helpful to see their
connection after having learned Fourier and wavelet enough.</li>
  <li><em>The World According to Wavelets The Story of a Mathematical Technique in the
Making</em> is all about history and intuition. The second half that deals with
math has not been read yet. After having learned wavelet, this small book
could be helpful on wavelet’s connection with other discipline and historical
development.</li>
  <li><em>A wavelet tour of signal processing</em> is a reference book. It deals with the
big perspective on the transition from wavelet method to dictionary
learning. This is the book to read after I have learned wavelet well.</li>
  <li><em>Conceptual Wavelets in Digital Signal Processing</em>, <em>A primer on wavelets and
their scientific applications</em>, <em>Ripples In Mathematics</em> and <em>The Illustrated
Wavelet Transform Handbook</em> are more about mechanics of wavelet. Those
mechanics could be helpful after the overall picture of wavelet is gotten.</li>
  <li><em>Wavelets and Subband Coding</em>, <em>Multirate Systems And Filter Banks</em> and
<em>Wavelets and Filter Banks</em> are about more the discrete version of
*wavelet. Those will be helpful when I am working on implementation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bayesian-statistics">Bayesian Statistics</h2>

<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>

<p>There has been twenty years of work on computer vision and machine learning
using Bayesian methods. The initial taking off initialized by Hinton also
origins from statistical method — Deep Belief Net. There are several reasons
to understand Bayesian related methods:</p>

<ol>
  <li>To acquire the ability to understand previous important work and work on
deep learning involving Bayesian methods.</li>
  <li>Statistics is important for biologically inspired work. Neurons in brain
never get activated alone. It is their statistics pattern that matters.</li>
  <li>It is another way to think about problem. If we view the branch of applied
mathematics as modeling the world from a low level, relatively deterministic
perspective, probability viewed it from a high level, semantic way. It is
important to have probability to deal with high level part of deep learning
system.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="goal-next-step">Goal Next Step</h3>

<p>The first step goal is to understand the fundamental intuition behind
probability and statistics, just like understanding the construction of number
system while studying functional analysis, then how exactly Bayesian methods
depart from traditional frequentism. Computational perspective of Bayesian
method such as sampling could wait.</p>

<h3 id="execution-plan-1">Execution Plan</h3>

<p>The main plan to follow is the thread on Bayesian statistics on
Metaacademy. Books are also important for reference and systemtization of
learning.</p>

<h4 id="basic-probability-and-statistics">Basic Probability and Statistics</h4>
<ul>
  <li><em>An Introduction To Probability Theory And Its Applications</em> is the classic
book on probability. It gets the intuition and motivation right. If knowledge
which needs deeper learning arises, this is the book to consult.</li>
  <li><em>Probability Jim Pitman</em> is an undergraduate textbook on probability.</li>
  <li><em>Statistical Inference</em> is the book to read after having a good understanding
of probability.</li>
  <li><em>Mathematical Statistics and Data Analysis</em> is a good reference for
statistics. It is relatively simpler than <em>Statistical Inference</em>, which it a
good fallback candidate if I have a hard time understanding the book.</li>
  <li><em>Bayesian Data Analysis</em> After the basic foundation of probability and
statistics is laid. This is the book to read to know Bayesian methods.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="multivariate-statistics">Multivariate statistics</h4>
<ul>
  <li><em>Modern Multivariate Statistical Techniques</em> and <em>An Introduction to
Multivariate Statistical Analysis</em> is the book to consult when jumping into
real world data.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="modern-probability-theory">Modern Probability Theory</h4>
<ul>
  <li><em>Probability and Random Processes Grimmett</em> tries to cover stuffs that needs
measure theory in using language that without measure theory. It could be a
bridge to the gap of modern probability and classic probability.</li>
  <li><em>Probability Essentials</em> describes the thread of modern probability tersely.</li>
  <li><em>Probability, Theory and Examples</em> is like Mallat’s wavelet tour. It is a
book to read after you have relative good understanding of modern probability
theory. It could offer you a bigger picture.</li>
  <li><em>Foundation of Modern Probability</em> is the most advanced book which may only
be needed by PhD in probability.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="real-analysis">Real Analysis</h4>
<ul>
  <li><em>Principles of Mathematical Analysis</em> is the book to consult in undergraduate
level.</li>
  <li><em>James Munkres Topology</em> is the book to consult about topology.</li>
  <li><em>Folland. Real Analysis Modern Techniques and their Application</em> is the book
to learn real analysis seriously.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="link-between-communities">Link Between Communities</h2>

<p>A major breakthrough could be made is that the work on sparse and redundant
dictionary learning in signal processing community, traditional Bayesian
statistics machine learning community, neuroscience community and the community
working on experimental deep learning could be linked together.</p>

<p>What CNN tries to learn is basically a sparse and redundant dictionary that is
used to capture semantic patterns of sensed signal. Signal processing community
could offer theoretical guidance. Neurosciece could offer biological
experimental facts and deep learning community could offer simulation
experiments facts and lastly, Bayesian statistics community could offer ways to
deal with the high level relationship between atom in the dictionary.</p>

<h2 id="ending">Ending</h2>

<p>I think this is all of it. Hope I will be back soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
