<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Analysis | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/analysis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-30T09:08:11+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Do We Create Meaningful Many Dimensional Space?]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/how-do-we-create-meaningful-many-dimensional-space/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T20:58:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/how-do-we-create-meaningful-many-dimensional-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post should be the third notes on understanding fundamentals of Analysis,
or in a more broad sense, understanding fundamental of Mathematics, though some
other randoms post are written previously.
The <a href="/blog/2013/12/24/axiomization-of-natural-number/">first</a>
 is about the axiomization of Natural Number. It gives the exact definition of
natural number, whose concept is taken for granted for most people. The
<a href="/blog/2014/09/30/why-and-how-we-construct-real-number-system/">second</a>
is about the construction of Real Number System. It offers a complete field
which all the remaining Mathematics is built on.</p>

<p>The above two posts are both in essential, one dimensional. They are the
infrastructure of univariate function, univariate calculus and other univariate
Math subjects. After building the one dimensional infrastructure, the next step
is to step in the world of more than one – two dimensional, three dimensional,
finite dimensional, and the infinite dimensional, which all will be called many
dimensional space in this post.</p>

<p>So this is about how do we create meaningful many dimensional space that
suitable for the real world problem. In such space, we could deal with, two
dimensional plane, three dimensional space, ultimately countably infinite
dimensional space and uncountably infinite dimensional space, furthermore, the
one of the most important subjects in modern analysis – function space.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-leap-to-abstract-mathematics">The Leap to Abstract Mathematics</h2>

<p>Such transition is a great leap in the development of Mathematics. It makes
Mathematics become more and more abstract. The inevitability is showed in the
following. As having been numbered before, there are at least four extremely
common many dimensional space we must deal with: two dimensional, three
dimensional, which we are familiar with; countably infinite dimensional space,
for instance, countable sequences, which is quite common; uncountably infinite
dimensional space, for instance the space of all continuous function defined on
$R$, which some may not be very familiar. Actually, there is a lot more than
that since at least we would have a number of spaces such as 7D and 8D etc.. So
mathematicians cannot deal with those spaces be copying the way they deal with
$R$. They have to find a way to see those thing in common. In the popular word
of programmers, they need to abstract them. Ha ha, programming is great, right?</p>

<p>Consequently, here comes Abstract Algebra, General Topology and ultimately,
Functional Analysis. Let get to know what these three terms are about(but it is
highly probable that you have no idea what I am talking about given learning
Math is far from learning concepts): Abstract Algebra is about abstracting common
operations that is used in $R$, which is called using the terminology algebraic structure. For
instance, a ring is an algebraic structure with operations generalizing the
arithmetic operations of addition and multiplication. So such operation will
not only be able to be applied to number, but to polynomials, matrices and
etc..[1] More word may be find in this rather old post on
<a href="/blog/2013/12/24/basis-of-algebra-structure/">Basic of Algebra Structure</a>;
General Topology is about the mathematical study of shapes and topological
spaces. It is an area of mathematics concerned with the properties of space
that are preserved under continuous deformations including stretching and
bending, but not tearing or gluing[2]. The sets with the same properties are
called open set. Abstract Algebra abstracts operations of $R$. General Topology
abstracts objects or points of $R$. With objects and operations on those
objects, we could analyze them, where comes Functional Analysis(Though
Functional Analysis is just about analyze functions, all machinery developed
above is to try to deal with function space. So the problem and technique in
Functional Analysis could all be applied to other many dimensional space).</p>

<h2 id="hilbert-space">Hilbert Space</h2>

<p>Once we have abstract stuff, things could become very weird given that we could
tweak the stuff anyway we want. But the key is to remember why we initiate the
search for an abstract solution for solving real world problem. So the light to
guide the abstract construction is to let things meet natural intuitions. This
is the point I learned hardest while teaching myself functional analysis, which
is the thread that guides me to bridge the gap between those highly abstract
concepts to the details in the real world problems I aim to solve.</p>

<p>Hilbert Space is the solution to the question posed at the beginning – finding
a meaningful many dimensional space. From now on, why Hilbert Space fits with
natural intuition will be elaborated. But keep in mind that though
understanding intuition playing a very important role in learning Mathematics,
it is never sufficient, a large amount of information is skipped at the time
Abstract Algebra and General Topology is introduced above. It is the process to
learning them, to do exercise that gives me such intuition.</p>

<p>A natural step following one number, denoted $\xi$, is to list a tuple
$(\xi_{1}, \xi_{2})$. $\xi_{1}$ could be the size of one department and
$\xi_{2}$ could be the price of the department. We take it in tuple maybe
because to want to investigate something that is related to those two
both. Then naturally, we would like to extend it to $(\xi_{1} \ldots
\xi_{n})$, then $(\xi_{1} \ldots \xi_{n}), n = 1 \ldots \infty$,
which is called countably infinite, then $(\xi_{1} \ldots \xi_{n})$, where we
regard $\xi_{i}$ is as dense(note the dense does not mean its usual meaning in
topology) as point in $R$(this sentence is actually mathematically wrong given
the incountablity of the set, but it makes the point through more easily),
which is called uncountably finite. Each instance of previous examples is a
point in its space. For instance, $(\xi_{1} \ldots \xi_{n}), n = 1 \ldots
\infty$ is a point in the space of all possible value of $\xi_{i}$. The point
is actually called vector and the space is noted as Vector Space defined on
Field $R$ or $C$ if it is complex.</p>

<p>Again, the natural question to ask is how much similarity with $R$ we could
keep while generalizing? This is the process we construct the meaningful many
dimensional space. The answer is that we want to get completeness, compactness,
connectivity, which are contents of topology and metric space, “absolute value”
of point, which is the content of Normed Vector Space, “length” of “lines”
which is the content of Real Analysis and others. Given the limitation of time,
none of them will be covered here. The point of this post is to try to note
down the hardest to understood properties kept after generalization –
geometric intuition on 2D or 3D space.</p>

<p>What is the geometric intuition I am talking about?</p>

<p>In Normed Vector Space, we could assign any norm we want, for instance, $L^{p}$
norm. But it seems  2-norm, also Euclidean norm that is the most natural norm
for we human. But why it is the most natural one? How do we define natural?</p>

<p>The following are some direct answer:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='https://cloud.githubusercontent.com/assets/2428233/6881526/a9f838a8-d59d-11e4-8b39-52e744eff47e.png' width='' height='' title='Geometric Proof of Pythagoras Theorem'><span class='caption-text'>Geometric Proof of Pythagoras Theorem</span></span></p>

<ol>
  <li>As we rotate one vector, its length will not change in 2-norm, but not other
norms.</li>
  <li>It makes Pythagoras Theorem held. So when we drop the coordinate system, and
see vectors in pure geometric way, its length will still be the same.</li>
</ol>

<p>But those all special phenomenon of one underlying truth – 2-norm could be
derived from inner product(Besides completeness, it is inner product that plays
the most important role in the definition of Hilbert Space), and inner product
gives angle a sensible definition.</p>

<p>Before we elaborate the point, let us think a minute about what exactly angle
is? This is again one blind spot that we take for granted, at least me.</p>

<p>Try searching on its wikipedia page. Actually we cannot define angle like we
define natural number using Peano Axiom. We are told it is some thing that is
between two straight line or defined it through trigonometric function, which
is essentially ratio, in high school. Underlying those definition, we are
actually define it through its behavior. This makes sense, since ultimately,
angles do not exist on their own and are the relation between lines.</p>

<p>But we could model such relationship using one entity – inner product. Angle
could be defined as:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

\theta = arccos\frac{<x, y>}{||x||||y||}
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>Through this way, angle is connected with value(coordinates) of lines(vectors)
naturally. As angle is kept, our intuition is actually kept. More specifically
the intuition of rotation, orthogonality and projection are all kept. Those are
what we call natural.</p>

<p>To make sense of it, it is recommended to prove polarization identity using
property of inner product and law of cosine using elementary geometry
method(polarization identity and law of cosine are the same theorem in different
names in different contexts).</p>

<h2 id="reference">Reference</h2>
<ol>
  <li>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ring_(mathematics)</li>
  <li>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topology</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Understand Compact in Mathematical Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/10/06/how-to-understand-compact-in-mathematics-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T22:20:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/10/06/how-to-understand-compact-in-mathematics-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="preface">Preface</h2>

<p>My journey of teaching myself mathematics begins with learning the
number theory, understanding why matrix is invented. Thus up to now,
most of the effort was spent on matrix algebra and matrix calculus.</p>

<p>Recently, I am trying to understand wavelet theory. The main
motivation behind it is to find a set of basis to approximate
functions, which seems to involve a lot of analysis. Therefore, I
beginning to teach myself analysis like a math major student from
scratch.</p>

<p>This post is about another concept called <strong>compact</strong>. You can find
previous post about real number system <a href="/blog/2014/09/30/why-and-how-we-construct-real-number-system/">here</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="definitions">Definitions</h2>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> A subset $K$ of metric space $X$ is said to be
  <em>compact</em> if every open cover of $K$ contains a finite subcover.</p>

<p>As a number of other mathematical definition, they have reused the
structure built before, which means they have a lot of information
beneath the surface. So let’s define what is</p>

<ol>
  <li>metric space, this one is assumed to be known.</li>
  <li>open cover</li>
  <li>finite</li>
  <li>subcover</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="open-cover">open cover</h2>
<p><strong>Definition</strong> By an <em>open cover</em> of a set $E$ in a metric space $X$
  we mean a collection <script type="math/tex">\{G_{\alpha}\}</script> of open subsets of $X$ such
  that <script type="math/tex">E \subset \cup_{\alpha}G_{\alpha}</script>.</p>

<p><em>The concept of open is assumed to be known.</em></p>

<p>It is a rather mathematical definition, however, as having been
emphasized over and over, there is always a simple intuition behind
one abstract idea. The intuition of open cover is to use open, which
means we do not make arbitrary judgement about the boundary of the
ball ball to cover the area that is taken up by the $E$. The idea of
compact is to accumulate those no judgemental balls to acquire some
global properties about the set. As we will see later.</p>

<h3 id="subcover">subcover</h3>

<p>A subcover is one element of <script type="math/tex">G_{\alpha}</script>. The intuition is that one
subcover is just one open ball.</p>

<h2 id="finite">finite</h2>

<p>Though the concept of finite and infinite predates college, it seems
that I do not pay enough attention to them till now. But note that
even without mentioning this concept, the meaning of finite in the
definition of compact is still straightforward.</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> For any positive integer n, let $J_{n}$ be the set
  whose elements are the integers $1, 2, \ldots, n$; let $J$ be the
  set consisting of all positive integers. For any set $A$, we say:</p>

<ol>
  <li>$A$ is finite if $A ~ J_{n}$ for some $n$ (the empty set is also
considered to be finite).</li>
  <li>$A$ is infinite if $A$ is not finite.</li>
  <li>$A$ is countable if $A ~ J$.</li>
  <li>$A$ is uncountable if $A$ is neither finite nor countable.</li>
  <li>$A$ is at most countable if $A$ is finite or countable.</li>
</ol>

<p>The above definition uses the notion of equivalence.</p>

<h3 id="equivalence">Equivalence</h3>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> If there exists a $1-1$ mapping of $A$ onto $B$, we say
  that $A$ and $B$ can be put in $1-1$ <em>correspondence</em>, or that $A$
  and $B$ have the same <em>cardinal number</em>, or briefly, that $A$ and
  $B$ are equivalent, and we write $A \sim B$.</p>

<h2 id="compact-explained">compact explained</h2>

<p>Now, let’s try to understand the idea of compact. First we see one set
that is not compact. Then we try to see the reason why compact is put
forward. The main intuition is, I think, which is not cited from
anywhere else, so it may be wrong, that the introduce of compact
bridges the gap between the set’s global properties and local
properties, infinite properties and finite properties.</p>

<h3 id="example">Example</h3>

<p>The open interval $I = (0, 1)$ is not compact.</p>

<p>To see why, let <script type="math/tex">G_{n} = (\frac{1}{n}, 2), n = 1, 2, 3 \ldots</script>. Each
<script type="math/tex">G_{n}</script> is an open cover of $I$ and as $n \rightarrow \infty$,
<script type="math/tex">G_{n}</script> could cover $I$. However, if we only take finite number of
subcover of <script type="math/tex">G_{n}</script>, we cannot cover $I$.</p>

<p>However, if we let $I$ to be a closed interval, say $I = [0, 1]$, it
is compact. A general theorem about this is described as every
k-cell(try Google what k-cell is if you have no idea what it is) is
compact. Proof here will be omitted(Proof can be found on Theorem 2.40
of Ref 1). The intuition behind the proof is that if an open cover $G$
could be found, then if any finite subcovers of $G$ cannot cover the
k-cell, you can always add more but finite number of subcovers to
cover all of $G$.</p>

<p>So why only a difference of open and closed makes such a difference?</p>

<p>In my view, the key difference is the limit point. If we do not makes
arbitrary statement about the limit point, which is the boundary in
this case, abnormal phenomenon could happen when approaching the limit
point. As in this case, when point, denoted $x$, is approaching zero,
if some function $f$ defined on the interval and $f$ has $x$ in the
denominator, $f$ may be boundless.</p>

<p>Thus, compact models the process that a point is approaching its limit
step by step(open ball by open ball) without making arbitrary
statement about the boundary. Consequently, compact has a number of
connection with continuity and convergence.</p>

<p>In the following, we would see more examples that compact is in action
to have a feeling about its effect.</p>

<p>Before that, let us introduce an important theorem that connect
finite with infinite.</p>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> If <script type="math/tex">\{K_\alpha\}</script> is a collection of compact subsets of
  a metric space $X$ such that intersection of every finite
  subcollection of<script type="math/tex">\{K_\alpha\}</script> is nonempty, then $$\cap
  K_{\alpha}$$ is nonempty. </p>

<p><strong>Proof</strong> Fix a member <script type="math/tex">K_{1}</script> of <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}\}</script> and put
  <script type="math/tex">G_{\alpha} = K^{c}_{\alpha}</script>. Assume that no point of <script type="math/tex">K_{1}</script>
  belongs to every <script type="math/tex">K_{\alpha}</script>. Then the sets <script type="math/tex">G_{\alpha}</script> form an
  open cover of <script type="math/tex">K_{1}</script>; and since <script type="math/tex">K_{1}</script> is compact, there are
  finitely many indices <script type="math/tex">\alpha_{1}, \ldots, \alpha_{n}</script> such that
  <script type="math/tex">K_{1} \subset G_{\alpha_{1}} \cup \ldots \cup G_{\alpha_{n}}</script>.
  But this means that <script type="math/tex">K_{1} \cap K_{\alpha_{1}} \cap \ldots \cap K_{\alpha_{n}}</script> is empty, in contradiction to our hypothesis.</p>

<p><strong>Corollary</strong> If <script type="math/tex">\{K_{n}\}</script> is a sequence of nonempty compact sets
  such that <script type="math/tex">K_{n} \supset K_{n + 1}, (n = 1, 2, 3, \ldots)</script>, then
  <script type="math/tex">\cap^{\infty}_{1} K_{n}</script> is not empty.</p>

<p>This corollary actually bridges finite and infinite together.</p>

<p>Now, let’s see the theorem in action.</p>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> Let $P$ be a nonempty perfect set in $R^{k}$. Then $P$ is
  uncountable.</p>

<p><strong>Proof</strong> Since $P$ has limits points, $P$ must be infinite. Suppose
  $P$ is countable, we denote the points of $P$ by <script type="math/tex">x_{1}, x_{2}, x_{3}, \ldots</script> By analysis the interval between those points, we
  could find the contradiction we want.</p>

<p>Let <script type="math/tex">V_{1}</script> be the neighborhood of <script type="math/tex">x_{1}</script>. If <script type="math/tex">V_{1}</script>
  consists of all $y \in R^{k}$ such that <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
|y - x_{1}| < r %]]&gt;</script>, then the
  closure <script type="math/tex">\bar{V}_{1}</script> of <script type="math/tex">V_{1}</script> is the set of all $y \in R^{k}$
  such that <script type="math/tex">|y - x_{1}| \leq r</script>.</p>

<p>Suppose <script type="math/tex">V_{n}</script> has been constructed, so that <script type="math/tex">V_{n} \cap P</script> is
  not empty. Since every point of $P$ is a limit point of $P$, there
  is a neighborhood <script type="math/tex">V_{n+1}</script> such that 1. <script type="math/tex">\bar{V}_{n+1} \subset V_{n}</script>, 2. <script type="math/tex">x_{n} \notin V_{n+1}</script>, 3. <script type="math/tex">V_{n+1} \cap P</script> is not
  empty. The induction goes on.</p>

<p>Put <script type="math/tex">K_{n} = \bar{V}_{n} \cap P</script>. Since <script type="math/tex">\bar{V}_{n}</script> is closed
  and bounded, <script type="math/tex">\bar{V}_{n}</script> is compact(Theorem 2.41 Ref 1). Since
  <script type="math/tex">x_{n} \notin K_{n+1}</script>, not point of $P$ is in <script type="math/tex">\cap^{infty}_{1} K_{n}</script>. Since <script type="math/tex">K_{n} \subset P</script>, this implies that
  <script type="math/tex">\cap^{infty}_{1} K_{n}</script> is empty. But each <script type="math/tex">K_{n}</script> is nonempty,
  by 3, and <script type="math/tex">K_{n} \supset K_{n+1}</script> by 1, this contradicts the
  corollary above.</p>

<p>Proof is complete.</p>

<p>In this proof, the global property of the $P$ is proved by reducing
the contradiction into infinite intersection of small sets of
$P$. This shows some feelings about the bridge mentioned above.</p>

<h2 id="one-more-example">One More Example</h2>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> Compact subsets of metric spaces are closed.</p>

<p><strong>Proof</strong> The proof also starts from the intuition that if the subset
  is open, we cannot approach the boundary of the subset, since they
  are not part of the set, in a finite step.</p>

<p>Before we prove the theorem, a common misunderstanding of the compact
should be pointed out. It is also straightforward to think that if one
set $G$ is compact, it could be covered by a finite subcover,
therefore, any subsets of $G$ could also be covered by such
subcover. Consequently, any subsets of $G$ is also compact.</p>

<p>The misunderstanding under this reasoning is that compact is defined
by all open covers, which means it has to rule out all possible open
covers. Note that the open covers of $G$ cannot cover all open covers
of its subsets. For example, a open cover could cover one subset
$G_i$ of $G$, which indeed is an open cover of $G_i$, but this open
cover is not one of $G$.</p>

<p>Now, the proof is begun(Ref 2).</p>

<p>We want to prove if $A \subseteq X$ is not closed, then $A$ is not
compact. We tackle the problem from the boundary. Since $A$ is not
closed, there is one point $p \in (cl, A) but \notin A$. For $n \in
N^{+}$, let</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
U_n = \{x \in X: d(x, p) > \frac{1}{n}\}
</script>

<p>$U_n$ is a open cover of $A$, however, no finite subsets of $U_n$
would cover $A$.</p>

<h2 id="one-more-example-1">One More Example…</h2>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> Closed subsets of compact sets are compact.</p>

<p><strong>Proof</strong> Ref 1. The intuition behind this proof is that for each
  finite open cover of $K$, there exists a finite subcover that could
  cover $F$, which means $F$ is compact.</p>

<p>Suppose $F \subset K \subset X$, $F$ is closed (relative to $X$), and
$K$ is compact. Let ${V_{\alpha}}$ be an open cover of $F$. If we
add one more open set $F^{c}$, then ${V_{\alpha}} \cup F^{c}$
becomes the open cover of $K$. Since $K$ is compact, there exists
finite subcovers that would cover $K$. By excluding $F^{c}$, those
subcovers are also a finite cover of $F$, which means $F$ is compact.</p>

<h2 id="one-more-examples">One More Examples</h2>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> Let (S, d) be a metric space. If <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}\}_{\alpha \in A}</script>
is a collection of compact sets such that the intersection of every
finite subcollection of <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}\}_{\alpha \in A}</script> is nonempty,
then <script type="math/tex">\cap_{\alpha \in A}K_{\alpha}</script> is nonempty.</p>

<p><strong>Proof</strong> Consider $K$, for any set in the collection <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}\}</script>
, we claim that there exists a $p \in K$ such that
<script type="math/tex">p \in K_{\alpha}, \forall \alpha \in A</script>. 
If not, we could prove contradiction.</p>

<p>Suppose not, $\forall p \in K$, there exists $\alpha$ that
<script type="math/tex">p \notin K_{\alpha}</script>. <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}^C\}</script> consists of an open cover of
$K$(since each <script type="math/tex">K_{\alpha}</script> is closed, thus their complement is
open). We know that $K$ is compact, there exists a finite sub covers
of <script type="math/tex">K_{\alpha}</script> covers $K$</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\{K_{\alpha_{i}}^{C}\}_{i=1,\ldots,n}
</script>

<p>But this implies that</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
K \subseteq K_{\alpha_{1}}^C \cup K_{\alpha_{2}}^C \cup \ldots \cup K_{\alpha_{n}}^C
</script>

<p>Then 
<script type="math/tex"> K \cap u_{\alpha_{1}}^C \cap K_{\alpha_{2}}^C \cap \ldots \cap K_{\alpha_{n}}^C = \emptyset </script>
.(If <script type="math/tex">x \in K_{\alpha_{j}}^C</script>, for some $j = 1,\ldots,n$. Then <script type="math/tex">x \notin K_{\alpha_{j}}^C</script>.
It follows that <script type="math/tex">x \notin K \cap u_{\alpha_{1}}^C \cap K_{\alpha_{2}}^C \cap \ldots \cap K_{\alpha_{n}}^C</script> and
<script type="math/tex">K \cap u_{\alpha_{1}}^C \cap K_{\alpha_{2}}^C \cap \ldots \cap K_{\alpha_{n}}^C = \emptyset </script>)
Since finite <script type="math/tex">K_{\alpha_{j}}^C, j=1,\ldots, n</script> will contain $K$, thus
containing <script type="math/tex">\{K_{\alpha}\}</script>. But for every finite subcollection of
<script type="math/tex">K_{\alpha}</script> their intersection should not be empty. This causes
contradiction.</p>

<p>Then there exists some $p$ such that <script type="math/tex">p \in \cap_{\alpha \in A}</script>, and
<script type="math/tex">\cap_{\alpha \in A} \neq \emptyset</script>.</p>

<p><em>Proof is finished. Ref 3</em></p>

<p>To see why compact is necessary, see this example below.</p>

<p>Let <script type="math/tex">I_n = (0, 1/n)</script>, each intersection between $I_m$ and $I_n$ is
not empty, however, as $n \rightarrow \infty$, the intersection is
empty.</p>

<p>This example shows that compact is mainly aims at the limit property
of set.</p>

<p>The intuition underlies this also related to the intuition put forward
at the first place. If we can guarantee one point in the set in the
finite case, we could also guarantee it in the infinite case. It
bridges the gap between finite and infinite.</p>

<h2 id="more-examples">More Examples</h2>

<p>To see more example and theorems, you can continue to read</p>

<ol>
  <li>Theorem 7.13 of Ref 1.</li>
  <li>Theorem 3.11 of Ref 1.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="reference">Reference</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Walter Rudin Principles of Mathematical Analysis, Third Edition</li>
  <li><a href="http://math.stackexchange.com/questions/597828/compact-sets-of-metric-spaces-are-closed">math.stackchange</a></li>
  <li>Some pdf <a href="/docs/about_compact.pdf">here</a>. Obtained from <a href="/docs/about_compact.pdf">here</a></li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why and How We Construct Real Number System]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/09/30/why-and-how-we-construct-real-number-system/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-30T01:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/09/30/why-and-how-we-construct-real-number-system</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="preface">Preface</h2>

<p>My journey of teaching myself mathematics begins with learning the
number theory, understanding why matrix is invented. Thus up to now,
most of the effort was spent on matrix algebra and matrix calculus.</p>

<p>Recently, I am trying to understand wavelet theory. The main
motivation behind it is to find a set of basis to approximate
functions, which seems to involve a lot of analysis. Therefore, I
beginning to teach myself analysis like a math major student from
scratch.</p>

<p>The first hard concept I met is the construction of real number
system. I skipped this concept the first time I am learning
analysis. In retrospect, I mainly focused on the concept of peano
axiom to construct natural number system then because matrix algebra
mainly deals with integer. However, the main objective of wavelet
theory is to find a set of basis that can approximate functions,
regardless of continuous and discrete. There is no escape this time.</p>

<p>The articles about peano axiom is on another PDF file, which I haven’t
sorted it out on the blog. Some time in the future.</p>

<p>I guess this will be the beginning of a series of post about
analysis. The first one here is about construction of real number
system. Let us begin.</p>

<h2 id="some-words">Some Words</h2>

<p>The purpose of this post is to explain the intuition behind to
construct the real number system, so it will not be mathematically
sound and incremental. You should be familiar with the following
concept:</p>

<ol>
  <li>(ordered)field</li>
  <li>ordered set</li>
  <li>some knowledge about set and set operation</li>
  <li>Cauchy sequence</li>
  <li>Archimedean property</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="motivation-sketch">Motivation Sketch</h2>

<p>The following are key points that motivate mathematicians to construct
a new number theory that is called real number system.</p>

<ol>
  <li>There are numbers that rational number cannot incorporate. In other
word, there is gaps in rational number line.</li>
  <li>It may be surprising that for some $E \subset Q$, you cannot find
the extreme point of $E$ in $Q$.  This point is somehow a rephrase
of the previous point – there are gaps and least upper bound may
residue in the gap.</li>
</ol>

<p>Therefore, to make the number line to be without gaps, in our daily
word, continuous, the real number system is constructed.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="folk-story">Folk Story</h2>

<p>For most practical purposes in our daily life, the Field of Rational
can be said to be more than adequate as a number system. After all,
when we take a measurement with our ruler, we can read at best to the
markings on the ruler and those markings are simply fractions of the
length of the ruler. Even when we use an electronic calculator and
obtained a result whose figures covered the whole screen, we simply
round off to our desired accuracy with not much complaint. Now, when
we round off something, we are simply getting a result that can be
expressed as a fraction. So what exactly is wrong with the Field of
Rational?</p>

<p>Most people’s idealization of the real numbers is that they are
markings on an imaginary number line. This number line is a sort of
conceptual ruler that mathematicians can use to measure their abstract
objects exactly. This means that the number line will always give us
the exact value, and not just any approximated value, of any quantity
we are measuring. Of course, some sort of standardization of the
division mark should be used so that everybody’s absolute value agree
but that is beside the point. Now, if the Field of Rational gives us
such an ideal number system, then we should be able to cover the whole
of the number line with rational numbers.  If this cannot be achieved,
then there will be at least one point on the number line that have no
markings, and what value are we going to assign an object whose length
happen to hit that mark?</p>

<h2 id="inadequacy-of-q">Inadequacy of $Q$</h2>

<h3 id="gap-in-q">Gap in $Q$</h3>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong>: There exists no rational $r$ such that $r^{2} = 2$.</p>

<p>Suppose that such $r$ does exist. We may assume that $r &gt; 0$,
otherwise we take $-r$.</p>

<p>Any rational number could be expressed in the form of $\frac{n}{m}$,
great command divisor of $m, n$ will be one, thus $n$ and $m$ will not
be both even.</p>

<p>so we have</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
  \frac{n^{2}}{m^{2}} = 2
  n^{2} = 2m^{2}
</script>

<p>In the equation above, $n^{2}$ will be even, thus $n$ will be
even. Consequently, $m$ will be even, which contradict with the
prerequisite that $n, m$ will not be both even.</p>

<p>Therefore, $r$ will not belong to $Q$.</p>

<h2 id="no-extremum-point-in-some-set-in-q">No extremum point in some set in $Q$</h2>

<p>To see this, we also consider the example of square root of 2.</p>

<p>For every $p$ in $A$ we can find a rational $q$ in $A$ such that $p &lt;
q$ and for every $p$ in $B$ we can find a rational $q$ in $B$ such
that $q &lt; p$.</p>

<p>To do this, we associate with each rational $p &gt; 0$ the number</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
  q = p - \frac{p^{2} - 2}{p + 2} = \frac{2p + 2}{p + 2}
</script>

<p>Then</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
  q^{2} - 2 = \frac{2(p^{2} - 2)}{(p + 2)^{2}}
</script>

<p>If $p$ is in $A$ then $p^{2} - 2 &lt; 0$, we have $q &gt; p$ and $q \in
A$. The case when $p$ is in $B$ is visa vice.</p>

<p>From this example, we find that we cannot find the maximum of one set
in $Q$, which contradict with our intuition that the number line is
continuous. To make the number line continuous, the real number system
is constructed.</p>

<h2 id="least-upper-bound-property">least-upper-bound property</h2>

<p>Before we construct the real number system, we first define some
relevant definition.</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> Suppose $S$ is an ordered set, and $E \subset S$. If
  there exists a $\beta \in S$ such that $x \leq \beta$ for every $x
  \in E$, we say that $E$ is bounded above, and call $\beta$ an <em>upper
  bound</em> of $E$.</p>

<p>Lower bound is defined in the same way.</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> Suppose $S$ is an ordered set, $E \subset S$, and $E$
  is bounded above. Suppose there exists an $\alpha \in S$ with the
  following properties:</p>

<ol>
  <li>$\alpha$ is an upper bound of $E$.</li>
  <li>If $\gamma &lt; \alpha$ then $\gamma$ is not an upper bound of $E$.</li>
</ol>

<p>Then $\alpha$ is called the <em>least upper bound</em> of $E$ or supremum of
$E$, and we write</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
  \alpha = sup E
</script>

<p>The <em>greatest lower bound</em> or <em>infimum</em>, of a set $E$ which is bounded
below is defined in the same manner, denoted as $\alpha = inf E$.</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> An ordered set $S$ is said to have the
  <em>least-upper-bound property</em> if the following is true:</p>

<p>If $E \subset S$, $E$ is not empty, and $E$ is bounded above, then
$sup E$ exists in $S$.</p>

<h2 id="real-number-system">Real Number System</h2>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> There exists an ordered field $R$ which has the
  least-upper-bound property.</p>

<p>The members of $R$ is are called <em>real numbers</em>.</p>

<p>Now we stop for a moment and to reiterate the understanding one should
possess when reaching this point. The gaps in rational number line
motivate mathematicians to construct real number system $R$, and the
most essential traits which makes $R$ different from $Q$ is that $R$
has least-upper-bound property, which means it has its extreme in its
own.</p>

<p>So, how could we construct such a system, called real number
system by us, that fulfills least-upper-bound property?</p>

<p>The intuition of two approaches will sketched. The first one is
Cantor’s approach and the second one is Dedekind’s approach. Cantor’s
approach is described first since it is easier for me to understanding
when learning.</p>

<h3 id="cantors-approach">Cantor’s Approach</h3>

<p><strong>Definition</strong> Let $\Gamma$ denote the set of all Cauchy sequences in
  $Q$. We say <script type="math/tex">(r_{n}), (s_{n}) \in \Gamma </script> are equivalent and we
  write <script type="math/tex">(r_{n}) ~ (s_{n})</script> if given any rational $\epsilon &gt; 0$,
  $\exists k \in N$ such that <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
|r_{n} - s_{n}| < \epsilon, \forall n \geq k %]]&gt;</script>.</p>

<p>We denote the equivalent class $[r_{k}]$.</p>

<p>Thus real number is defined by pushing rational number to their
limit. Each equivalent class in the sequence described above is a real
number. All of them is denoted as $R$.</p>

<p>If $R$ is going to be an ordered field, it must have its
properties. It could be proved that it indeed does. Here those proof
will be skipped because they are rather tedious and only one proof
will be showed, which is the problem real number system is created to
solve.</p>

<p><strong>Theorem</strong> The least upper bound property holds in $R$.</p>

<p>The main intuition behind this proof is that we can always find a
Cauchy sequence that is arbitrary close to the real number point we
want. It use a power of two as the sequence, if we takes a power of
ten, it is similar with our decimal point system.</p>

<p>Let $A$ be a nonempty subset of $R$ that is bounded above by, say,
$m$. Then by the Archimedean property, we can find $M \in Z$ with $m
\leq M$. Let $a$ be in $A$ and let $n$ be an integer with $n &lt; a$. For
$p \in N$ set <script type="math/tex">S_{p} = \{k2^{-p} | k \in Z\ and\ n \leq k2^{-p} \leq M\} \cup \{m\}</script>.
 Note that <script type="math/tex">S_{p} \neq \emptyset</script> and is finite. Now let
<script type="math/tex">a_{p} = min \{x | x \in S_{p}\ and\ x\ is\ an\ upper\ bound\ for\ A\}</script>.</p>

<p>Note that if $p &lt; q$, then</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

  a_{p} - 2^{-p} < a_{q} \leq a_{p}
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>The intuition behind this is that as $p$ becomes larger, the granuity
of $k2^{-p}$ becomes finer.</p>

<p>Since, for example, <script type="math/tex">a_{p} - 2^{-p}</script> is not an upper bound for $A$,
while <script type="math/tex">a_{q}</script> is an upper bound. But this implies that</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

  |a_{p} - a_{q}| \leq 2^{-p} for\ all\ p < q
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>from which it follows that <script type="math/tex">{a_{k}}_{k \in N}</script> is a Cauchy
sequence. Let $L = [a_{k}]$</p>

<p>We claim that $L$ is a least upper bound for $A$. Suppose $x \in A$
and $x &gt; L$. Choose $p$ such that $2^{-p} &lt; (x - L)$(using the
Archimedean property). Since <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} - 2^{-p} < a_{q} %]]&gt;</script> for $p &lt; q$ and
<script type="math/tex">{a_{p}}_{p \in N}</script> is a decreasing Cauchy sequence, it follows that
<script type="math/tex">a_{p} - 2^{-p} \leq L</script>, we obtain <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} < x %]]&gt;</script>, which is a
contradiction. Therefore, $L$ is an upper bound for $A$.</p>

<p>Suppose that $H$ is an upper bound for $A$ and that $H &lt; L$. Choose
$p$ such that $2^{-p} &lt; L - H$. Take $x \in A$ such that <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} - 2^{-p} < x %]]&gt;</script>.
 Then <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} - 2^{-p} < x %]]&gt;</script>. Then <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} - 2^{-p} < H %]]&gt;</script>.
 Adding, we get <script type="math/tex">% &lt;![CDATA[
a_{p} < L %]]&gt;</script>. But, as noted above, $L \leq a{p}$ for
all $p \in N$, so this is a contradiction.</p>

<h3 id="dedekind-cut">Dedekind Cut</h3>

<p>Since Dedekind’s approach is at least as complex as Cantor’s approach,
only the intuition behind the construction is presented below:</p>

<p>Dedekind viewed each point, $x$, on the number line as a cut that
split the rational into 2 sets.</p>

<h2 id="reference">Reference</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Construction of The Real Number System <a href="/docs/CONSTRUCTION_OF_THE_REAL_NUMBER_SYSTEM.pdf">pdf</a></li>
  <li>Chapter 1, Fundamental of Mathematical Analysis <a href="/docs/construction_of_real_number_and_complex_number.pdf">pdf</a></li>
  <li>Principles of Mathematical Analysis, 3rd Edition</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
