<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-16T16:38:49+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Needfinding Introduction]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/needfind-introduction/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T19:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/21/needfind-introduction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reading note of a Needfinding book, which I cannot find its author.</p>

<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>
<p>Leaders in any organization were those people who found important new problems
to work on, not necessarily those who ultimately solved the problems. The
greatest impact that designers could have on product development, then, was at
the earliest stages of product definition.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Note: Find what to solve is always more important than solve the specific problem.
In a technical sense, this means you have a big picture on what you are
working. This provides you with guidance. But on the other side, you have to
have the enough skillset to be able to know how you can solve the problems.</p>

<p>Needfinding is the act of discovering people’s explicit and implicit needs so
that designers can create apppropriate solutions.</p>

<p>Needfinding has come to include elements of design planning: providing guidance
and strategies for what a successful solution might be.</p>

<p>Needfinding has thus evolved into a methodology that’s a hybrid of both design
research and design planning. That hybridity is one of Needfinding’s core
strenths.</p>

<p>Question: what does design research and design planning means?</p>

<h2 id="core-principles-of-needfinding">Core Principles of Needfinding</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Look for needs, not solutions.</li>
  <li>Make research and design seamless.</li>
  <li>Spend time in the participants’ world.</li>
  <li>Look beyond the immediately solvable problem</li>
  <li>Let the participants set the agenda</li>
  <li>Collect eclectic forms of data</li>
  <li>Make findings tangible and prescriptive</li>
  <li>Iterate to refine the findings.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playbook for Strategic Foresight and Innovation Reading Notes Series -- Chapter Five]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/12/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-five/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-12T11:04:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/12/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-five</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This chapter is about connecting your idea generated from previous work to
market, to reality, through which you find lingering assumptions, critical
areas untouched and converge your ideas.</p>

<p>Four methods are provided.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="white-spots">White Spots</h2>

<p>White spots means unexplored market space. In my view, the point of this method
is to give you a start point – find two most critical demision of you context
map, draw a 2X2 matrix based on them, fill what the market already have, what
are expected to have and what are imagined to have but cannot. Then you find
the missing point of the market.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/white_spots.png ‘White Spots Illustration’ ‘White Spots Illustration’ %}</p>

<p>The process gives a hint to begin.</p>

<h2 id="paper-mockup">Paper Mockup</h2>

<p>This one is similar to the future telling method. However, the latter focus on
the function you want to have by testing in senario with imagination. This one
is more about bring a rought physical prototype with the function you want by
the fastest way.</p>

<p>To try it on real scenario, on real people, you get the realization of your
concept and feedback about your idea.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/paper_mockup.png ‘Paper Mockup Illustration’ ‘Paper Mockup Illustration’ %}</p>

<p>Some nice questions prompt thoughts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Which aspects of your prototype did the audience focus on? Why?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Which elements of your idea did your team leave out of your prototype? Why?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Which part of the prototype exist today, and which parts need to be built?
Which pieces cannot exist today?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>How should you document and capture the lessons from building and presenting
this prototype?</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Some advice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Deliberately deep your design rough, so that it looks incomplete and thus
invites constructive feedback from others.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="dark-horse-prototype">Dark horse prototype</h3>

<p>At the phase of generating your team’s ideas, there are ones being discarded.
However, it happens that the greatest ideas are among the ones that are
discarded. So find one of them and do a prototype could give your a valuable
lesson.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/dark_horse.png ‘Dark Horse Illustration’ ‘Dark Horse Illustration’ %}</p>

<h2 id="change-path">Change Path</h2>

<p>This part is about planning – to find a start point to get you moved and to
identify the milestones in the process of achieving your idea.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Simply knowing what to do tomorrow helps break inertia. Ask yourself, what am I
going to do on Monday? Who am I going to call?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>{% img center /images/change_path.png ‘Change Path Illustration’ ‘Change Path Illustration’ %}</p>

<h2 id="stop">Stop</h2>

<p>This series stops here. There are still two chapters left but they are less
relevant to what I am doing right now, so I decide not to read them for the
time being.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playbook for Strategic Foresight and Innovation Reading Notes Series -- Chapter Four]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/09/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-four/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T10:53:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/09/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-four</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The perspective chapter is about knowing what has been done, what works and what
not, and why some works and some not.</p>

<p>This chapter stops discovering the past but focus on the future. What
opportunities lie on in the future.</p>

<p>The overall idea of this chapter is clear. Three methods are provided.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="generational-arcs">Generational Arcs</h2>

<p>Generational Arcs try to catch the big picture of the target people – the
age versus population distribution. This is a rough mathematical model to
estimate the current state and how will the state shift in the future.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/generational_arc.png “Generational Arcs Illustration” “Generational Arcs Illustration” %}</p>

<p>From the modeling result, we may get a sense of the amount of our target peole
and how it would change in the future.</p>

<h2 id="future-user">Future User</h2>

<p>This method have finer granunity. It tries to summarize the typical
characteritics and the change may happen in the future of one group of people in
the target population – there may be more than one persona to represent
different groups in the Generational Arcs.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/future_user.png “Future User Illustration” “Future User Illustration” %}</p>

<p>From the characteritics found, we could have a more concrete person, in other
word, persona, to work on.</p>

<h2 id="future-telling">Future Telling</h2>

<p>And future telling focus not on the characteritics but on the scenario. In what
scenario would the user in now and in the future?</p>

<p>{% img center /images/future_telling.png “Future Telling Illustration” “Future Telling Illustration” %}</p>

<p>This is like the procedural programming. You first go the program in your mind
once before getting it coded. But the Future Telling should be more physical –
a mock scenario is expected to be done.</p>

<p>From the insight found from the mock scenario, what the product will be like
would become more concrete.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playbook for Strategic Foresight and Innovation Reading Notes Series -- Chapter Three, Perspective]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/08/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-three/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-08T21:26:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/08/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-three</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This chapter is about knowing the background of your research topic. There are
some inner laws in the process of design. This chapter provides a clear
definition between different phases of doing background reseach, or in other
word, benchmarking.</p>

<p>Three methods are provided.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h3 id="context-map">Context Map</h3>

<p>Capture what plays an important role in the problem or idea you want
to deal with. It emphasizes on the quantity of the factors influencing
the problem. It says eight factor, no more to make the problem too
complex or no less to capture enough dimensions.</p>

<p>Some notes about drawing the context map. Essentially, it should be no
difference from listing a list of factors. However, it is the graph
structure that matters. So it would be helpful to make sure the map is
big enough for taking notes for the team members.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/context_map.png “Context Map Illustration” “Context Map Illustration” %}</p>

<h3 id="progression-curves--janus-cones">Progression Curves &amp; Janus Cones</h3>

<p>The two methods are all about get the backgound of your problem from a
perspective involving time.</p>

<p>At first, the difference between Progression Curves and Janus Cones confuses me.</p>

<p>Context Map emphasizes on factors. This method emphasizes on efforts
already put in the problem, the pattern of events happened, and how these events
have led to its current state.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/progression_curves.png “Progression Curves Illustration” “Progression Curves Illustration” %}</p>

<p>But, Janus Cones also emphasizes on events. The book says, Janus Cones is to
discern a possible pattern of relationships among many related(and even
unrelated) events. Progression Curves also talks about events.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/janus_cones.png “Janus Cones Illustration” “Janus Cones Illustration” %}</p>

<p>From the words talking about Progression Curves, “you can draw a progression curve
for each demision of your context map”, I think Janus Cones is the combination
of a bunble of Progression Curves, and it emphasizes on the relation between
event that are in different progression curves.</p>

<h3 id="some-comments">Some comments</h3>

<p>In my view, those methods are also very useful for the academic research life I
am going to pursue. Hope could try it out in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playbook for Strategic Foresight and Innovation Reading Notes Series -- Chapter Two]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/07/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-two/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-07T16:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/12/07/playbook-for-strategic-foresight-and-innovation-reading-notes-series-chapter-two</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This chapter is a should-read-twice chapter. Similar to previous
chapter, this chapter tries to provides a overview for
reader. However, it is more specific.  It breaks the innovation process
down and dicuss them separately.</p>

<p>Actually, this is the second time that I have read this chapter – not
the should-read-twice meaning what I meant just now. At the first
time, the reading was not mandatory, so I did not persist reading all
the book. And for the second time, I completely forget what I learnt
at the first time. This chapter is hard to comprehend without action.</p>

<p>Now, the reading notes begin.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="why-a-playbook">Why a playbook</h2>
<p>At the beginning, the author stresses the role of this book – playbook.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A playbook is a notebook containing the descriptions and diagrams of all the
possible plays and strategies used by a team.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This book is about coaching you and your teammates. And it is hard, like
everything else that is great.</p>

<h2 id="some-definitions">Some definitions</h2>
<p>Then the author makes clear some definitions to make sure readers understand two
important basic concept of this playbook.</p>

<h3 id="strategic-foresight">Strategic Foresight</h3>

<p>Acknowledge the ambiguity of the future. Use methods to get a view the future
and influence it.</p>

<h3 id="innovation">Innovation</h3>

<p>This is what everyone knows, finding, building and taking a new idea into the
marketplace.</p>

<h3 id="radical-innovation">Radical Innovation</h3>

<p>The difference between Innovation and Radical Innovation is Radical Innovation
create huge ideas which have huge impact.</p>

<h2 id="break-down-the-innovation-process">Break down the innovation process</h2>
<p>Then beginning with the start of the innovation process, the author breaks it
down and discuss:</p>

<ol>
  <li>What type of growth do we seek, which determines what kinds of ideas we want
to think of.</li>
  <li>For an idea, where do we get our inspiration?</li>
  <li>The roles people play when the innovation process starts.</li>
  <li>The influence the contexts of industries will bring to the innovation
process.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="learning-process">Learning process</h2>

<p>After the breakdown of the innovation process, the author provides guide about
how to learn and use the method provided in this playbook.</p>

<h2 id="finish">Finish</h2>
<p>As I have written, this is a should-read-twice chapter. Or more precise, this is
learning instructions. When finishing reading this book and going to apply the
methods, go back and check the advice offered by the author.</p>

<p>There are 10 valuable advices at the end of this chapter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
