<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Xml | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/xml/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-21T20:42:47+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comparison Betwwn Yaml Libconfig & Xml]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/04/09/comparison-betwwn-yaml/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-09T22:27:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/04/09/comparison-betwwn-yaml</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I have gotten in touch with several different techniques for program
configuration file. Here I note down some of their characteristics, which may
explain why they are created in concurrence with each other.</p>

<p>They are Xml, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YAML">Yaml</a> and <a href="http://www.hyperrealm.com/libconfig/">libconfig</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="xml1">Xml[1]</h2>

<p>There are two main uses for XML: One is a way to represent low-level data, for
example configuration files. The second is a way to add metadata to
documents; for example, you may want to stress a particular sentence in a
report by putting it in italics or bold.</p>

<p>The first usage for XML is meant as a replacement for the more traditional ways
this has been done before, usually by means of lists of name/value pairs as is
seen in Windows’ INI or Java’s Property files. The second application of XML is
similar to how HTML files work. The document text is con- tained in an overall
container, the &lt;body&gt; element, with individual phrases surrounded by <i> or <b>
tags. For both of these scenarios there has been a multiplicity of techniques
devised over the years. The problem with these disparate approaches has been
more apparent than ever, since the increased use of the Internet and extensive
existence of distributed applications, particularly those that rely on
components designed and managed by different parties. That problem is one of
intercommunication. It’s certainly possible to design a distributed system that
has two components, one outputting data using a Windows INI file and the other
which turns it into a Java Properties format. Unfortunately, it means a lot of
development on both sides, which shouldn’t really be necessary and detracts
resources from the main objective, developing new functionality that delivers
business value.</b></i></p>

<p>XML was conceived as a solution to this kind of problem; it is meant to make
passing data between different components much easier and relieve the need to
continually worry about different formats of input and output, freeing up
developers to concentrate on the more important aspects of coding such as the
business logic. XML is also seen as a solution to the question of whether files
should be easily readable by software or by humans; XML’s aim is to be both.
You’ll be examining the distinc- tion between data-oriented and
document-centric XML later in the book, but for now let’s look a bit more
deeply into what the choices were before XML when there was need to store or
communi- cate data in an electronic format.</p>

<h2 id="yaml">Yaml</h2>
<p>YAML is a recursive acronym for “YAML Ain’t Markup Language”. Early in its
development, YAML was said to mean “Yet Another Markup Language”, but it was
then reinterpreted (backronyming the original acronym) to distinguish its
purpose as data-oriented, rather than document markup.[2]</p>

<p>Yaml is designed for data serialization, which builds command data structures
into the language.</p>

<h2 id="libconfig3">libconfig[3]</h2>

<p>There are several open-source configuration file libraries available as of this
writing. This library was written because each of those libraries falls short
in one or more ways. The main features of libconfig that set it apart from the
other libraries are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A fully reentrant parser. Independent configurations can be parsed in
concurrent threads at the same time.</li>
  <li>Both C and C++ bindings, as well as hooks to allow for the creation of
wrappers in other languages.</li>
  <li>A simple, structured configuration file format that is more readable and
compact than XML and more flexible than the obsolete but prevalent Windows
“INI” file format.</li>
  <li>A low-footprint implementation (just 37K for the C library and 76K for the
C++ library) that is suitable for memory-constrained systems.</li>
  <li>Proper documentation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
  <li>[1] Beginning Xml 5th Edition</li>
  <li>[2] http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YAML</li>
  <li>[3] http://www.hyperrealm.com/libconfig/libconfig_manual.html</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
