<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: C++ | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/c-plus-plus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-18T13:34:59+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Code Completion & Navigation for C/C++ in Emacs]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/on-code-completion-for-c-slash-c-plus-plus/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-11T09:21:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/on-code-completion-for-c-slash-c-plus-plus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Due to the same reason that I decided to add <code>company</code> to provide faster and
more accurate completion functionality, I switched from
<a href="http://cedet.sourceforge.net/">CEDET</a> to
<a href="https://github.com/Sarcasm/irony-mode">irony</a> +
<a href="https://github.com/leoliu/ggtags">ggtags</a>.</p>

<p>Here is the note TODO</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="irony">Irony</h2>

<h3 id="installation">Installation</h3>

<p>To setup <code>irony</code>, in the <a href="https://github.com/Sarcasm/irony-mode">README</a> of
<code>irony</code>’s git repo, the installation process provided by the author is pretty
workable. The only thing may need to be noted is that what packages you need to
install if you are not going to compile <code>libclang</code> from source.</p>

<p>In Ubuntu, you need those two packages: <code>libclang-dev</code> and <code>clang</code>. By
mentioning only <code>libclang</code>, it gives me the feeling that I do not need an
executable of <code>clang</code>, however, there is some errors occurs without
<code>clang</code>. But due to the trial and error when making <code>irony-mode</code> to work, I am
not sure it is really caused by lacking of <code>clang</code>.</p>

<h3 id="make-it-work">Make It Work</h3>

<p>You need to let <code>clang</code> know where to find you source file for it to parse
it. To achieve this, <code>irony</code> provides a concept called
<a href="https://github.com/Sarcasm/irony-mode#compilation-database">compilation database</a>. Refer
to it to know how to make <code>irony</code> work. The following is some remarks.</p>

<p>Basically, the most important compilation flags are the include folder path for
header files. Since <code>irony</code> does not aim to provide code navigation function,
all information it needs are in header files.</p>

<p>One problem that bugs me a lot when I was setting up <code>irony</code> is that <code>clang</code> in
<code>irony</code> and <code>gcc</code> handles <code>-I</code> flag differently. The path must immediately
follows the <code>-I</code>, with no spaces. If there are spaces, <code>irony</code> could not find
the corresponding paths.</p>

<h3 id="limitations">Limitations</h3>

<p>During my testing with <code>irony</code>, I found that it could not handle definition
with template, which is used a lot in C++ numerical library. The limitation
also makes sense since that declarations are generated dynamically during
compilation for template definition, so maybe you could not get relevant
information just by parsing the template definition.</p>

<h2 id="ggtags">ggtags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/global/">gtags</a> is better
<a href="http://ctags.sourceforge.net/">ctags</a> in various ways. See the
<a href="https://github.com/leoliu/ggtags">table</a> provided by
<a href="https://github.com/leoliu/ggtags">ggtags</a>’s developers.</p>

<h3 id="setup-system-tags">Setup System Tags</h3>

<p>I copy this section from this
<a href="http://tuhdo.github.io/c-ide.html#sec-7-2">tutorial</a> in case I may forget it.</p>

<p><code>GNU Global</code> has an environment variable named <code>GTAGSLIBPATH</code>. This variable holds
<code>GTAGS</code> database of external libraries that your project depends on but not
inside your project. For example, your project may rely on system headers such
as <code>stdio.h</code>, <code>stdlib.h</code>… but these headers are internal to your project. However,
remember that you can only jump to tag definitions of external dependencies,
and nothing else (such as files or references). But, again, once you are inside
the external library, you can start jumping around sicne it becomes your
current project.</p>

<p>To make <code>GNU Global</code> sees your system headers, follow these steps:</p>

<p>Export this environment variable in your shell init file, such as <code>.bashrc</code> or
<code>.zshrc</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
export GTAGSLIBPATH=$HOME/.gtags/
</code></p>

<p>Execute these commands in your terminal:</p>

<p>```bash
# Create a directory for holding database, since
# you cannot create a database in your system paths
mkdir ~/.gtags</p>

<h1 id="create-symbolic-links-to-your-external-libraries">Create symbolic links to your external libraries</h1>
<p>ln -s /usr/include usr-include
ln -s /usr/local/include/ usr-local-include</p>

<h1 id="generate-gnu-global-database">Generate GNU Global database</h1>
<p>gtags -c
```</p>

<p>The <code>-c</code> option tells <code>GNU Global</code> to generate tag database in compact format. It
is necessary because if your project contains C++ headers like <code>Boost</code>, without
<code>-c</code> your <code>GTAGS</code> database can be more than 1 GB. Same goes for <code>ctags</code>. The <code>GNU
Global</code> devs explained that it is because the <code>GTAGS</code> database includes the image
of tagged line, and the <code>Boost</code> headers have a lot of very long lines.</p>

<p>After all the above steps, restart with a shell loaded with that variable. To
verify Emacs gets the variable, <code>M-x getenv</code> and enter <code>GTAGSLIBPATH</code> and see
if your predefined value is available. Executing <code>ggtags-find-tag-dwim</code> or
<code>helm-gtags-dwim</code> jumps to the definition of a system tag like a normal tag.</p>

<p>The disadvantage of using <code>GNU Global</code> is that currently it cannot include
files without extension. In the C++ system include directory like
<code>/usr/include/c++/4.8/</code>, it contains files without extension such as
<code>iostream</code>, <code>string</code>, <code>set</code>, <code>map</code>…. so you can write <code>#include</code> directives
without having to append <code>.h</code> at the end. <code>GNU Global</code> devs are considering to
add support for this use case.</p>

<h2 id="some-remarks">Some Remarks</h2>

<ul>
  <li><code>semantic-mode</code> is still used to provide method overview for ECB. It is
configured to only parse current buffer, which is rather acceptable in speed.</li>
  <li>If you want to know more about CEDET, here is
<a href="http://alexott.net/en/writings/emacs-devenv/EmacsCedet.html">a nice introductory post</a>
explaining it.</li>
  <li>Though <code>CEDET</code> gets disabled, company still takes advantage of some part of
tools provided by <code>CEDET</code>. One of them is
<a href="http://cedet.sourceforge.net/ede.shtml">EDE</a>, the project
manager. See the github README page of
<a href="https://github.com/randomphrase/company-c-headers">company-c-headers</a> to see
how could you use <code>EDE</code> to tell <code>company</code> to use system include path.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">helm</a> is an alternative to
<a href="https://www.masteringemacs.org/article/introduction-to-ido-mode">ido</a>. Maybe
it could be tried while I have more time.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/abingham/emacs-ycmd">emacs-ycmd</a> is another completion
framework for Emacs.</li>
  <li><code>irony</code> offers a flychecker, since I already uses the google style and
cpplint, I will not try <code>flycheck-irony</code> for the time being, though it may
offer advantages such as full compilation error detection.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
