<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hadoop | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/hadoop/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-02T15:02:39+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simulate Hadoop(MapReduce) Using Linux Command Line]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/03/20/simulate-hadoop-mapreduce-using-linux-command-line/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T12:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2014/03/20/simulate-hadoop-mapreduce-using-linux-command-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a number of blogs writing about this topic. Why another one?</p>

<p>The problem comes from the <code>sort</code> part of the pipeline(if you have no idea what
I am talking about, you will later). Most of the blogs and comments purely
using the standalone <code>sort</code> command, which is not the way hadoop doing sorting.
To sort the right way, sort should be used this way: <code>sort -k 1,1 -t $'\t'</code>.
Explanation will be provided later.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>You should understand what the following command does to keep reading:</p>

<p><code>bash
cat DATA.txt | python mapper.py | sort | python reducer.py &gt; RESULT.txt
</code></p>

<p>In the <code>sort</code> part of this command, without any options and arguments, <code>sort</code>
use non-blank to blank transition as the separator to divide each line in the
file into columns, not the tab character, and it will compare the entire line
by default. This will result in erroneous behavior when the dataset becomes
large.</p>

<p>To make <code>sort</code> action precisely as hadoop’s sort function. <code>sort -k 1,1 -t $'\t'</code> should be used.
<code>-t $'\t'</code> lets <code>sort</code> use tab character as separator to
divide columns. But tab character cannot be directly typed as <code>\t</code>. <code>$'\t'</code> is a
bash variable that will expand into tab character when evaluated. 
<code>-k 1,1</code> lets <code>sort</code> sorts the line by the content from first column to first
column, which is the key in hadoop sorting process.</p>

<p>Finally, a note about the algorithm <code>sort</code> command uses. It uses merge sort.
You can see a large number of tmporary files are created in <code>/tmp</code> file while
sorting large amount of data.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
