<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PhD | SHAWN LEE]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/categories/phd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-02T11:09:32+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[有思想的学姐]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/06/you-si-xiang-de-xue-jie/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-06T23:08:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/06/you-si-xiang-de-xue-jie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>有思想的学姐，不知以后能不能碰到。</p>

<h1 id="section">[转载] 0506飞跃手册序言</h1>

<p>圣经上说</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>已有之事，后必再有；已行之事，后必再行；日光之下，并无新事。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>小时候觉得这句话太消极，那时候认为与众不同是人生意义最重要的体现。
如果真的太阳下面都
没有新鲜事，
那人生岂非注定了是无意义的重复?等到慢慢长大，
才明白这句话或许可以另
作它释，与其说它强调了凡尘俗事的重复，到不如说它指出了人类这个种族的相似。几千年
前记录下的爱恨离别上下求索今天还依然在同一个太阳下激情不减地进行着。
即使是光芒万
丈的伟人，想必他/她的童年也不会不天真，青年也不会太淡定，人的行为真的大有模式可
循。所以编录这本手册，除了传承六系的奋斗精神、对师兄师姐们表示感激之外，也是为了
给以后的师弟师妹们留下一些记录，
希望他们在意气风发时能从中得到经验，
彷徨沮丧时也
可有所慰藉。</p>

<p>留学就像一条船、一辆车，
它本身无法给你人生的意义，但你可以通过它来寻找自己的
天地。就像有句话说的那样，
“你必须自己开始。假如你自己不以积极的爱去深入生存，假
如你不以自己的方式去为自己揭示生存的意义，
那么对你来说，
生存就将依然是没有意义的”
。
从这个角度讲，
如果有一天你决定离开申请道路踏上另一条更让你快乐的旅程，
或者度过几
年大学时光后蓦然回首发现留学才是你真正的心中寄托，
不要过于懊悔或焦灼，
人生是个连
续的过程，你依然有很多时间去追寻，重要的是你已经越来越明白自己渴望什么。</p>

<p>第一期飞跃手册中说</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>当我们一代复一代，走向世界顶尖的学府，开拓我们的心志，
在世界的舞台上实现我们的价值，
我们会形成一个潮流。
这样一个潮流会造福后来的科大人，
让他们被潮水推着更加轻快的走过我们曾经艰难行进的路途。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>的确，
留学是一种奋斗方式，
目的是帮助我们实现更大的人生价值。
只是当我们借着这潮水来到了千里之外，
历经了拼搏
和成长之后，
希望那时会有另一股潮流，
指引我们顺利返航。
如果若干年后还能作某一期
“返航手册”的编者，那会是一件很幸福的事吧。</p>

<p>After all， how can you come home if you never really leave?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Repost] This is What It Takes to Complete PhD Degree]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/this-is-what-it-takes-to-complete-phd-degree/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-05T19:43:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/this-is-what-it-takes-to-complete-phd-degree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="time-allocation">Time Allocation</h2>

<p>How people allocate research time varies enormously, not only from person to
person, but, for a given person, from week to week or quarter to quarter.</p>

<p>Some people work on an inspiration or deadline-driven basis, sometimes putting
in long hours, then doing nothing for a few days.</p>

<p>Others maintain a steady schedule, coming to the lab at a certain time in the
morning and leaving a certain time in the evening.</p>

<p>Neither is right or wrong or better or worse; it is a question of finding what
works best for you.</p>

<p><strong>As an advisor, what I look for is long-term productivity.</strong></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>A successful Ph.D student should typically display some degree of productivity
and progress **over the course of a reasonably long period, like a summer, a
quarter, or more typically, a year.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This would include signs of increased understanding, confidence and maturity,
and some visible output or “deliverable”, like a complete paper.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is not unusual if on a particular day, or even week, you don’t find yourself
inclined to do much research.</p>

<p>Take time off now and then; if you find you can’t concentrate, a vacation might
do more good than trying to sit in the lab and push yourself to work.</p>

<p><strong>You come back refreshed and productivity increases.</strong></p>

<p>I don’t want to “micro-manage”: how you allocate time on a short-term basis is
up to you. But if a long period passes without significant progress, you should
worry, and talk to me about it.</p>

<p>If you don’t know whether you are making “enough” progress, ask. Don’t be shy
about that.</p>

<p>Above I discussed how time allocation varies across people and their moods, and
how the long-term and short-term views differ.</p>

<p>With those discussions in mind, it is still useful, both for me and for you, to
get a sense of how you allocate time or other resources to research.</p>

<p>I am not trying to “check up” on you!</p>

<p>Rather this information will give both of us some sense of your productivity. It
will help me to “extrapolate”, meaning guage your progress towards completing
the Ph.D by a certain date.</p>

<p>Remember that the time in the question below is to be taken on the average,
across a long period, like a summer or a quarter or even a year.</p>

<p>Approximately how many hours a week do you spend on research, in an “average”
week? Include time spent thinking about research problems, writing technical
papers, or discussing research topics with other people including your advisor.</p>

<ol>
  <li>0–5 hours</li>
  <li>5–10 hours</li>
  <li>10–15 hours</li>
  <li>15–20 hours</li>
  <li>20–25 hours</li>
  <li>25–30 hours</li>
  <li>30–40 hours</li>
  <li>Over 40 hours</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="working-with-others">Working with others</h2>

<p>Good research needs a social context.</p>

<p>You learn better and produce more by interacting with others.</p>

<p>Besides of course talking to your advisor, talk to other students and engage in
joint work with them. Of course you must find a good balance between your own
pace and that of others: there is a happy medium between too solitary and too
social.</p>

<p>How often do you have technical discussions with other students?</p>

<ol>
  <li>More than once a day</li>
  <li>Once a day</li>
  <li>Once a week</li>
  <li>Once a month</li>
  <li>Once a quarter</li>
  <li>Never</li>
</ol>

<p>Besides interactions within the department, try to build up outside contacts and
co-workers. You meet people at conferences or while at summer jobs. You might be
able to interact profitably with them later.</p>

<h2 id="long-term-productivity">Long-Term Productivity</h2>

<p>PhD demands long-term productivity. That’s something you don’t get from
theoretical based education.</p>

<p>This not only applies to PhD, to be successful in any under-takings in your
life, can you show sustained interest for long-term.</p>

<p>This blog is a perfect example. Age of Happy Schools Blog is about 2291 days
(give or take few days).</p>

<p>Number of published is over 3000. That’s more than 1 article per day for last 6+
years.</p>

<p>So, the question to you :  Do you have long-term productivity or can you learn
to be productive for longer period’s of time?</p>

<p>Let me look from a different perspective. If you think you lack long-term
productivity, then you should do PhD. Now you know what it takes to complete PhD
Degree.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Repost] The PhD Exprience: Phase by Phase]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/the-phd-experience-phase-by-phase/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-05T19:35:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/the-phd-experience-phase-by-phase</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="choosing-an-area-and-an-advisor">Choosing an area and an advisor</h2>

<p>It is never too late to change areas. If you don’t like where you are now,
switching to a different area or advisor can make a marked difference. Try to
explore before settling down.</p>

<p>You should feel you have some understanding of the importance of the area you
choose, that it is worth your investment of time in it. Your advisor should be
able to inspire you about the work and give you a sense that it is worth it and
worth your time.</p>

<p>When you pick an advisor, ask yourself why you chose that person. Good reasons
include that you like that advisor’s area, that he or she can inspire you, that
you understand each other and get along. A poor reason is that you are afraid
you won’t get through and maybe this person is your best bet to make it.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="gauging-progress-am-i-on-track">Gauging progress: am I on track?</h2>

<p>The best way to know is to ask. Progress is measured in a number of ways. Direct
output, like papers is the most obvious. I also look at how your understanding
and knowledge of the materiel is developing.</p>

<h2 id="whats-phd-students-job">What’s PhD student’s job?</h2>

<p>Nothing, really. Students sometimes view a project suggested by an advisor as a
“job” they need to get done.</p>

<p>That may be appropriate for systems work; it is not in theoretical work.</p>

<p>There is really no “job” I need you to do. You are working for yourself, not for
me.</p>

<p>When I suggest projects they are only suggestions for things we can do together
or that you might do yourself.</p>

<h2 id="phd--phase-by-phase">PhD : Phase by phase</h2>

<p>Referring to the research path above, my minimal expectation at the end of Phase
1 is that you have a deep understanding of the subject of your first project.</p>

<p><strong>You should know it inside out.</strong></p>

<p>You should know what happens if something in your construction is twiddled, and
how it compares to other constructs.</p>

<p>This phase should typically take at most a year from when you begin research.</p>

<p>By the time you are in Phase 2, you should be “swimming” fairly comfortably in
the materiel.</p>

<p>You should be able to pick up new concepts rapidly and do simple proofs in your
head.</p>

<p>You should be able to make connections across different sub-areas, have some
sense of what is known and not known, and be at ease with basic techniques.</p>

<p>By the time you are in Phase 3 you should have a sense of taste, critical sense
and maturity in addition.</p>

<h2 id="research-publications-versus-thesis">Research Publications versus thesis</h2>
<p>The quantity and quality of publications you should look for varies with your
Ph.D goal.</p>

<p>If you want to head into research, whether at a research lab or in academia,
they will look at your publication record, not your thesis.</p>

<p>You want more than a minimal Ph.D.</p>

<p>You want to have had recognized publications and exposure.</p>

<p>Students headed this way shouldn’t really even be thinking about a “thesis”:
this is only a formality for the university and less than you need.</p>

<p>Try to do good research and get recognition in the research community.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-enough">What is enough?</h2>

<p>The minimal Ph.D is probably about four papers, but there is no hard and fast
rule.</p>

<p>Sometimes you may have stronger papers, or a larger contribution to co-authored
papers than in other cases, in which case fewer papers may be enough.</p>

<p>In other cases you may have more minor results or a lower contribution to
co-authered papers, in which case you may need more.</p>

<p>Remember if you want to head into research, whether at a research lab or in
academia, they will look at your publication record, not your thesis, and you
want recognized publications and exposure in the research community.</p>

<p>In addition to papers I expect you to develop communication skills, both written
and verbal. You should be able to plan and give clear talks and to write clear
and correct technical papers. There is no under-estimating the importance of
communication.</p>

<h2 id="when-is-phd-research-enough">When is PhD Research enough?</h2>

<p>Accomplishment is measured by output, not time.</p>

<p>For time, one can only talk about the typical.</p>

<p>The typical time-frame is five years, assuming the first year is spent in
coursework and you start research the second year.</p>

<p>Finishing in less time than that is neither unusual nor unusually difficult.</p>

<p>If it looks like you may take more than five years, it is not a good sign. At
that point, funding and lab space start getting denied, so beware.</p>

<h3 id="questions">Questions</h3>

<p>With regard to my rate of progress towards my Ph.D goal</p>

<ol>
  <li>I think I’m ahead of the game</li>
  <li>I think I’m about on track</li>
  <li>I’m worried I’m behind</li>
  <li>I haven’t a clue: why doesn’t someone tell me?</li>
  <li>Don’t ask now, because tomorrow I’m going to work twice as hard</li>
</ol>

<p>With regard to understanding and knowledge of the materiel</p>

<ol>
  <li>I think I’m ahead of the game</li>
  <li>I think my accomplishments and understanding are about where they should be</li>
  <li>I’m worried my accomplishments and understanding are below where they should be</li>
  <li>I haven’t a clue: why doesn’t someone tell me?</li>
  <li>Don’t ask now, because tomorrow I’m going to work twice as hard</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Repost] Is PhD right for me]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/is-phd-right-for-me/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-05T19:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/is-phd-right-for-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Credit : Thanks to Mihir Bellare – Professor in the Department of Computer
Science and Engineering at the University of California, San Diego who gave
permission to share his article. Professor Bellare wrote the PhD Experience for
his prospective and current PhD Students.</p>

<h1 id="is-phd-right-for-me">Is PhD Right for me?</h1>

<p>You should try to come to a frank appraisal of whether a Ph.D is the right thing
for you. You need to be totally honest with yourself about this. You need to
consider the question at several levels:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Is going for a Ph.D the right thing for me?</li>
  <li>If so, is the area I am pursuing now right for me?</li>
  <li>If so, is the advisor I have now right for me?</li>
</ol>

<p>My goal here is to make you think about these things. Here are some things to
think about and pitfalls to avoid in answering these questions.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Don’t be scared or turned off by what is below; I am only playing devil’s
advocate to get you to think!</p>

<h2 id="dont-kid-yourself">Don’t kid yourself</h2>

<p>Liking research it is liking DOING it, not liking thinking about where it puts
you, or liking to view yourself as someone who does it.</p>

<p>Separate the process from any perceived goal.</p>

<p><strong>You will only be happy in research if you enjoy the process, the day-to-day nuts
and bolts of it.</strong></p>

<p>If to you it is only a means to some end, you are unlikely to enjoy yourself.</p>

<h2 id="story-of-my-friend">Story of My Friend</h2>

<p>I had a friend once who from childhood had a dream of being a mathematician. She
loved the idea of being a person of the intellect. That way of life appealed to
her. However, at the time she had this dream, she had no idea what mathematics
really involved.</p>

<p>She followed mathematics and theoretical computer science in college and grad
school. However, she had a really hard time setting herself to the task.</p>

<p>Working on math problems was tiresome for her. It was very hard to have the
discipline to sit down and do this boring thing.</p>

<p>She was not at all dumb; far from it, being extremely intelligent.</p>

<p>The problem was that although she wanted to be a mathematician, she actually
hated doing the stuff. But you can’t be it without doing it.</p>

<p>What is exhibited here is the gap between a picture of how you want to see
yourself and what is involved in actually being that.</p>

<p><strong>Be wary of falling in love with a high-level goal when you find the nuts and
bolts tiresome.</strong></p>

<p>When you sit down daily to do your work in the lab, working on your research
problem, writing the paper, are you bored?</p>

<p>Is it hard to motivate yourself to be there?</p>

<p>Is it really not fun?</p>

<p>Are you saying, “I have to do this?”</p>

<p>Those are bad signs. It is not fun everyday, and all of it is not fun, but those
of us that are in this business enjoy a large fraction of the process.</p>

<p>For me, for example, thinking about a research problem is not work. It is
probably about the most fun thing I can think of doing.</p>

<p>You don’t have to be that fond of it, but if to you it is just work, to be done
and gotten rid off as soon as possible, you are in the wrong business.</p>

<p>You might with a great deal of discipline finish your Ph.D, but experience has
shown that even then you will not have a real sense of accomplishment or
happiness. You will also make my life difficult. (Professor’s Life)</p>

<p>Again, liking research it is liking DOING it, not liking thinking about where it
puts you. Be wary of childhood dreams; they are often formed without any idea of
what is actually involved in the process of attaining them.</p>

<h2 id="am-i-smart-enough-to-do-phd">Am I smart enough to do PhD?</h2>

<p>That’s the wrong question. There is no such thing as “smart enough”.</p>

<p>If you love playing the piano, play it. You don’t expect to be Alfred Brendel or
Vladimir Ashkenazy. But you are doing something productive for yourself and
those around you.</p>

<p>Research is the same. If you enjoy doing it, pursue it.</p>

<p><strong>You will usually find that you can contribute something.</strong></p>

<p>As you go on, you will discover your strengths and find you have something
unique to offer.</p>

<p>Maybe there are others who are smarter in some way; they can compute complex
probabilities in their head faster than you can, or whatever. But your
contributions may be valuable in other ways.</p>

<p>As discussed above, research has many components.</p>

<p>Problem solving, identifying issues, presentation, modeling, and criticism are
amongst them.</p>

<p><strong>See what aspects best suit your abilities and personality. There is probably a
niche for you somewhere.</strong></p>

<p>What is written above about kidding yourself does NOT refer to ability or
perception of ability; it refers to motivation and honesty about motivation.</p>

<p>I (professor) want to be sure you are pursuing research for the “right” reasons.</p>

<h2 id="self-confidence">Self-confidence</h2>

<p>Self-confidence affects our performance and success in all walks of life, from
sports to socializing to dating.</p>

<p>It plays a role in research too.</p>

<p>Sometimes I meet students who don’t have confidence. This can lead to a disinclination to work.</p>

<p><strong>Fear of failure leads to inactivity.</strong></p>

<p>People  ”freeze up” because they are so worried they aren’t “good enough”.</p>

<p>If this sounds familiar, at least you know you are not alone.</p>

<p>Increasing your self-confidence is very much a personal issue, but here are some reflections from my experience.</p>

<p>You can find confidence only within yourself. Don’t expect to get it from others, even your advisor. Someone telling you that you did well is useful to boost morale, but in the end you must believe in yourself.</p>

<p>If you are afraid of failure you will have a hard time succeeding.</p>

<h2 id="bicycle-vs-research">Bicycle vs Research</h2>

<p>You have to fall a few times to learn to skate or ride a bicycle.</p>

<p>Research is worse.</p>

<p>Once you learn to ride a bicycle you don’t fall again, but in research you never
stop failing.</p>

<p>You will fail far more often than you succeed. But it is from your failures that
you learn. They increase your understanding and maturity.</p>

<p>If you find the process of research fun, failure to solve a problem is not
daunting. In fact, it leads to all kinds of discoveries. So you need to learn to
not care about failing, but use it to get new ideas.</p>

<p>One nice thing about research is that nobody need know when you failed.</p>

<p>You write papers only about your successes. But that is also deceptive, because
you don’t see the failures of others. But they are there. Even the top people
don’t always succeed. Gauss failed sometimes, as did Einstein.</p>

<p>Try to ask yourself exactly why you lack confidence. Be entirely honest with
yourself. Go back to the discusions above about your motivations.</p>

<h3 id="question">Question</h3>

<p>How much self-confidence do I have with regard to research? (Mark all that apply)</p>

<ol>
  <li>I’m the hottest thing ever</li>
  <li>Enough to pursue a problem for a while and be reasonably sure, if I abandon
it, that it is not solvable</li>
  <li>Enough to pursue a problem for a while and be reasonably sure, if I abandon
it, that it would be pretty hard, even for experts</li>
  <li>I give up pretty quick</li>
  <li>I can’t even start thinking for fear of not solving it</li>
</ol>

<p>from: http://www.happyschoolsblog.com/is-phd-right-for-me/</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Repost] The PhD Experience: What's Involved]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/the-phd-experience-whats-involved/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-05T19:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawnLeeZX.github.io/blog/2013/11/05/the-phd-experience-whats-involved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Mihir Bellare – Professor in the Department of Computer Science and
Engineering at the University of California, San Diego who gave permission to
share his article.</p>

<p>Professor Bellare wrote the PhD Experience for his prospective and current PhD
Students. He talks about the research “way of life”, relationship with your
advisor, and the expectations and goals of the PhD program. I have split his
article into 4 parts to make it easy to read and understand and discuss.  This
is the Part 1 of “The PhD Experience”</p>

<!-- more -->

<h1 id="the-phd-experience--why-a-phd">The PhD Experience : Why a Ph.D?</h1>

<p>There are many reasons people are trying to get a Ph.D. It is useful both for
you and for me to know your reasons. Why are you pursuing Ph.D in computer
science? (Mark all that apply).</p>

<ol>
  <li>I enjoy research</li>
  <li>I want to teach, and a Ph.D is required for that</li>
  <li>A Ph.D will help me get a higher salary</li>
  <li>I needed to leave my home country and this was the best route</li>
  <li>My parents expect it</li>
  <li>My sibling(s) did it</li>
  <li>I really wasn’t interested in anything after my Bachelor’s, and grad school
was the easiest route</li>
  <li>Other (explain):</li>
</ol>

<p>What are your goals after graduating with your Ph.D? (Mark all that apply).</p>

<ol>
  <li>Get a research-oriented academic position</li>
  <li>Get a teaching-oriented academic position</li>
  <li>Work in a research lab</li>
  <li>Work for some hot Internet corporation</li>
  <li>Consult</li>
  <li>Start my own company</li>
  <li>Other (explain):</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="what-is-involved">What is involved?</h2>

<p>Perhaps the most common vision of entering students on (theoretical) research is
that they will have to solve some hard problem that nobody solved before. That
will be their thesis.</p>

<p>Maybe, but in general research is about a lot more than problem solving. It is
about conceptualizing, finding issues and directions, definitions, exposition
and critical insight. Problem solving is always there, but the role it plays
varies.</p>

<p>A common situation is to be developing a new model or notion. This will involve
making definitions, and then developing algorithms and analyses. When you have
new models, the technical aspects of some of the first solutions may be quite
simple. You might then wonder why nobody else did it. The reason is they did not
ask that question, or look at it in that way. Don’t look down on simplicity;
good research is often simple.</p>

<p>Your starting research project is not likely to be to solve some known hard
problem, unless you want it that way! More likely it is something like the
above, where one can make progress step by step.</p>

<p>Don’t start by thinking about a thesis or a thesis topic. Your goal is to
produce papers.</p>

<h2 id="what-can-i-get-from-a-phd">What can I get from a Ph.D?</h2>

<p>The Ph.D experience is about much more than learning to do deep work in some
technical area. Here are some of the more general things I expect you to get.</p>

<p>You should get a sense of confidence in the power of rational thought and the
range of its applicability. Everything in life is a problem of some sort of the
other. How often do we think about it that way, and approach methodically the
job of solving it? After a Ph.D you should have the inclination and ability to
research anything, whether it be mortgages, biology, cooking or Toyota engines,
and the expectation that you will understand it.</p>

<p>You should get the confidence and inclination to question all that is around you
and seek out new ways of doing it or seeing it. You should be more likely to ask
why things are done a certain why, and how it could be made better.</p>

<p>A Ph. D should give you the confidence that you can jump into a new area, pick
it up quickly, and have something interesting to say about it, even if other
people have looked at this area for a long time. More than depth in any one area
it should give you the courage to jump from area to area.</p>

<p>You might increase your appreciation for creativity, in other people and in all
areas of life. You might view art differently, or think differently about music
you hear, more appreciative of what it took to do this and how it departed from
the previous works. You should learn to value creativity and seek it out.</p>

<p>It will install a sense of taste and a critical sense. It should make you
unwilling to accept the common standards and norms, and to put them to the test
of your own intellect and opinions. You should naturally find yourself
questioning things. You should be willing to contradict conventional widsom.
That doesn’t mean being a rebel just for the sake of it; you are too mature for
that. It just means being constructively critical.</p>

<h2 id="how-i-envison-working-with-you-the-path-to-the-phd">How I envison working with you: The path to the Ph.D</h2>

<p>The way a student and advisor work together differs of course from student to
student. But here is the kind of path I try to show students. Not all students
follow this kind of path. It is just a rough guideline.</p>

<h3 id="phases">Phases</h3>

<p>In the first phase I will typically try to give you a well-defined project that
could lead, if successfully completed, to a reasonable quality publication. This
starting project should have clear questions, goals, and deliverables, meaning a
student should be clear on what is the target and what needs to be done to get
there. We would typically work together on properly formulating the questions,
solving them, writing up a solution, submitting it to an appropriate conference,
and, if it is accepted, preparing a presentation, so that the student gets a
view of the whole process.</p>

<p>In the second phase I could continue to suggest projects, ranging from
well-defined to fuzzy, but you are more on your own with respect to solving the
problems and writing up the solutions.</p>

<p>By then you should be well enough advanced that you can find your own questions
as well as the answers. That’s the third phase.</p>

<h3 id="meetings">Meetings</h3>
<p>I expect to meet with you at least once a week during regular quarters and
probably more often if you work here in the summer. You are also free to drop by
at non-scheduled times, or send e-mail.</p>

<p>Working together is fun. I enjoy it and hope you will too. So if you want to
discuss a problem don’t feel shy to stop by. A good deal of research is
spontaneous and social, arising from interactions with your peers or advisor.</p>

<p>You may not have something substantial to report at a meeting. That’s OK, as
long as it’s not a habit. See the section on time allocation below.</p>

<h3 id="questions">Questions</h3>
<ol>
  <li>I see my advisor</li>
  <li>Not often enough</li>
  <li>About as often as I want</li>
  <li>About as often as I can stand</li>
  <li>Way too much</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="meeting-preparation">Meeting preparation</h3>
<p>Prepare for your meetings. If you plan to present a scheme or an analysis or
some solution, prepare the presentation so that you can make it clearly and
well. Plan the order in which you will say things, and think about what you will
write on the whiteboard, and where. There are several important reasons for
this.</p>

<p>Our communication goes better and quicker if you prepare well, and this makes
better use of our limited time. If I have to spend more time understanding you,
you get lower quality feedback and it is harder to work together towards a
solution. Don’t underestimate the importance of the quality of your presentation
to the fruitfulness of our interaction. If I find it difficult to understand
you, I pay less attention and tune out, and if it continues over time, have less
and less inclination to know what you are up to, and that is probably not to
your advantage.</p>

<p>Students often launch into the middle of their current technical problem. It is
at the forefront of your mind because you have been working on it. It is not
necessarily at the forefront of mine: I have many projects, and my memory is
flakey in my advancing old age. Please bear with me here. Start from the
beginning, checking up where I am and what I remember. Present things in logical
sequence, slowly.</p>

<p>Think of your presentations to me as practice for ones to other people and
larger audiences.</p>

<p>Preparation for presentation is different from the actual technical work. No
matter how deep you are into your problem, you have to think separately about
how to present it concisely and clearly.</p>

<p>Not all meetings call for presentation, so don’t go overboard either. You may
not be presenting anything.</p>

<h3 id="question">Question</h3>

<p>With regard to my preparation and presentation for meetings with my advisor:
(Mark all that apply)</p>

<ol>
  <li>I prepare carefully</li>
  <li>I prepare a little</li>
  <li>I just waltz in</li>
  <li>I want more feedback about how to do it and when I am doing it well or badly</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="meeting-notes">Meeting notes</h3>
<p>Some of you remember what we discuss, others don’t and I have to repeat it next
time. I suggest you bring a notebook with you to our meetings and take notes.
Don’t hesitate to spend time doing that or to ask me to stop while you do. Ask
for clarifications or repetitions if necessary. Make sure we are clear with each
other about the technical issues and what to do next. If we have to go over the
same thing again at the next meeting, time is wasted for both of us.</p>

<h3 id="meeting-wrap-ups">Meeting wrap-ups</h3>
<p>Try to be clear about where you think you are headed in the period up to the
next meeting. What are the tasks, questions, deliverables, if any? Have this
written down if you are unsure you will remember it.</p>

<h3 id="questions-1">Questions</h3>
<p>With regard to what I get out of meetings: (Mark all that apply)</p>

<ol>
  <li>I find the meetings productive and get what I want from them</li>
  <li>I get something out of them but would like to get more</li>
  <li>I leave meetings more confused than when I went in</li>
  <li>I leave meetings unsure about what I am to do next</li>
</ol>

<p>Here is how the meetings could be made more productive for me …</p>

<p>from: http://www.happyschoolsblog.com/how-to-complete-phd-degree/</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
